January

Wednesday, January 1

Moses was by far the meekest of all the men on the face of the earth.—[Num. 12:3].

When Moses was a member of the Egyptian royal family, he was not meek. In fact, he had been so quick-tempered that he killed a man who he judged was acting unfairly. Moses assumed that Jehovah would agree with his actions. Jehovah spent 40 years helping Moses to understand that he needed more than courage to lead the Israelites; he needed to be meek. And to be meek, he also needed to be humble, submissive, and mild. He learned that lesson well and became an excellent overseer. (Ex. 2:11, 12; Acts 7:21-30,[36]) Today, family heads and elders do well to imitate Moses. When treated disrespectfully, do not become easily offended. Humbly acknowledge any faults you have. ([Eccl. 7:9,][20]) Submissively follow Jehovah’s direction on how to handle problems. And always answer mildly. ([Prov. 15:1]) Family heads and overseers who respond that way please Jehovah, promote peace, and set an example of how to be meek. w19.02 8 ¶1; 10 ¶9-10

^ (Num. 12:3) Now the man Moses was by far the meekest of all the men* on the face of the earth.

Or “was very humble (mild-tempered), more so than any other man.”

^ (Ex. 2:11, 12) Now in those days, after Moses had become an adult,* he went out to his brothers to look at the burdens they were bearing, and he caught sight of an Egyptian beating a Hebrew, one of his brothers. 12 So he looked this way and that, and seeing no one, he killed the Egyptian and hid him in the sand.

Or “as Moses was becoming strong.”

^ (Acts 7:21-30) But when he was abandoned,* the daughter of Pharʹaoh took him and brought him up as her own son. 22 So Moses was instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians. In fact, he was powerful in his words and deeds. 23 “Now when he reached the age of 40, it came into his heart to make a visit on* his brothers, the sons of Israel. 24 When he caught sight of one of them being unjustly treated, he defended him and avenged the one being abused by striking down the Egyptian. 25 He thought that his brothers would grasp that God was giving them salvation by his hand, but they did not grasp it. 26 The next day he appeared to them as they were fighting, and he tried to reconcile them in peace, saying: ‘Men, you are brothers. Why do you mistreat each other?’ 27 But the one who was mistreating his neighbor pushed him away, saying: ‘Who appointed you ruler and judge over us? 28 You do not want to do away with me the way you did away with the Egyptian yesterday, do you?’ 29 On hearing this, Moses fled and lived as a foreigner in the land of Midʹi·an, where he became the father of two sons. 30 “After 40 years had passed, an angel appeared to him in the wilderness of Mount Siʹnai in the flame of a burning thornbush.

Or “exposed.”

Or “to check the conditions of.”

^ (Acts 7:36) This man led them out, performing wonders and signs in Egypt and at the Red Sea and in the wilderness for 40 years.

^ (Eccl. 7:9) Do not be quick* to take offense, for the taking of offense lodges in the bosom of fools.*

Lit., “hurry in your spirit.”

Or possibly, “is the mark of a fool.”

^ (Eccl. 7:20) For there is no righteous man on earth who always does good and never sins.

^ (Prov. 15:1) A mild* answer turns away rage, But a harsh* word stirs up anger.

Or “gentle.”

Or “painful.”

Thursday, January 2

He was moved with pity for them.—[Mark 6:34].

Note the reason why Jesus felt pity, which can reflect fellow feeling. He observed that the people “were as sheep without a shepherd.” Maybe Jesus saw that some of them were poor and were working long hours to provide for their families. Perhaps others were dealing with the loss of a loved one. If so, Jesus could likely relate to their situation. He may have faced some of these problems himself. Jesus was concerned about others, and he felt moved to bring them a message of comfort. ([Isa. 61:1, 2]) What do we learn from Jesus’ example? Like Jesus, we are surrounded by people who are “as sheep without a shepherd.” They struggle with many problems. We have what they need—the Kingdom message. ([Rev. 14:6]) So in imitation of our Master, we preach the good news because we “have pity on the lowly and the poor.” ([Ps. 72:13]) We feel for people, and we want to do something to help them. w19.03 21-22 ¶6-7

^ (Mark 6:34) Well, on getting out, he saw a large crowd, and he was moved with pity for them, because they were as sheep without a shepherd. And he started to teach them many things.

^ (Isa. 61:1, 2) The spirit of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah is upon me, Because Jehovah anointed me to declare good news to the meek. He sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, To proclaim liberty to the captives And the wide opening of the eyes to the prisoners,  2 To proclaim the year of Jehovah’s goodwill* And the day of vengeance of our God, To comfort all who mourn,

Or “favor.”

^ (Rev. 14:6) And I saw another angel flying in midheaven,* and he had everlasting good news to declare to those who dwell on the earth, to every nation and tribe and tongue* and people.

Or “in midair; overhead.”

Or “language.”

^ (Ps. 72:13) He will have pity on the lowly and the poor, And the lives* of the poor he will save.

Or “souls.”

Friday, January 3

May Jehovah be praised, who daily carries our load.—[Ps. 68:19].

We have many reasons to love Jehovah. Not only does he supply the good things we enjoy each day but he also teaches us the truth about himself and his purposes. (John 8:31, 32) He has given us the Christian congregation to guide and support us. He helps us carry our burdens now, and he offers us the hope of living forever in perfect conditions in the future. ([Rev. 21:3, 4]) When we meditate on how much Jehovah has already done to show that he loves us, we are drawn to love him. And when we love Jehovah, we gain a balanced view of fear. We fear hurting the One we have come to love so much. When you continue to recognize how much you benefit from Jehovah’s guidance, your love for him and his standards will grow. Then nothing Satan offers you will entice you away from serving Jehovah. Imagine yourself a thousand years from now. You will look back on your decision to get baptized as the best decision you ever made! w19.03 6 ¶14; 7 ¶19

^ (Ps. 68:19) May Jehovah be praised, who daily carries our load, The true God of our salvation. (Selah)

^ (John 8:31, 32) Then Jesus went on to say to the Jews who had believed him: “If you remain in my word, you are really my disciples, 32 and you will know the truth, and the truth will set you free.”

^ (Rev. 21:3, 4) With that I heard a loud voice from the throne say: “Look! The tent of God is with mankind, and he will reside with them, and they will be his people. And God himself will be with them. 4 And he will wipe out every tear from their eyes, and death will be no more, neither will mourning nor outcry nor pain be anymore. The former things have passed away.”

Saturday, January 4

Who can find a capable wife? Her value is far more than that of corals.—[Prov. 31:10].

The entire family benefits when each member expresses appreciation. The more marriage mates show gratitude to each other, the closer they become. They also find it easier to forgive each other’s mistakes. A husband who appreciates his wife not only notices the good things she says and does but also “rises up and praises her.” ([Prov. 31:28]) And a wise wife lets her husband know specifically what she appreciates about him. Parents, how can you teach your children to show appreciation? Remember that your children will imitate what you say and do. So set a good example by saying thank you when your children do things for you. In addition, teach your children to say thank you when people do things for them. Help your children understand that expressing gratitude comes from the heart and that their words can do much good. w19.02 17 ¶14-15

^ (Prov. 31:10) Who can find a capable* wife? Her value is far more than that of corals.*

Or “an excellent.”

See Glossary.

^ (Prov. 31:28) Her children rise up and declare her happy; Her husband rises up and praises her.

Sunday, January 5

Until I die, I will not renounce my integrity!—[Job 27:5].

That is a statement of vital importance. Job refused to give in to Satan’s assault, and we can do the same. Satan makes the same charges about each of us. How are you involved? In effect, he says that you do not really love Jehovah God, that you will stop serving him to save yourself, and that any integrity you have is false! ([Job 2:4, 5;][Rev. 12:10]) How does that make you feel? It is hurtful, is it not? However, think about this: Jehovah trusts you enough to offer you a marvelous opportunity. Jehovah is allowing Satan to test your integrity. Jehovah is confident that you can keep your integrity and help to prove Satan a liar. And He promises to help you do that. ([Heb. 13:6]) What a privilege to be trusted by the Sovereign of the universe! Do you see why integrity is so important? It enables us to refute Satan’s lies and to uphold our Father’s good name and support his way of ruling. w19.02 5 ¶9-10

^ (Job 27:5) It is unthinkable for me to declare you men righteous! Until I die, I will not renounce* my integrity!

Or “I will not take away from myself; I will maintain.”

^ (Job 2:4, 5) But Satan answered Jehovah: “Skin for skin. A man will give everything that he has for his life.* 5 But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike his bone and flesh, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”

Or “soul.”

^ (Rev. 12:10) I heard a loud voice in heaven say: “Now have come to pass the salvation and the power and the Kingdom of our God and the authority of his Christ, because the accuser of our brothers has been hurled down, who accuses them day and night before our God!

^ (Heb. 13:6) So that we may be of good courage and say: “Jehovah* is my helper; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?”

See App. A5.

Monday, January 6

The hour is coming when everyone who kills you will think he has offered a sacred service to God.—[John 16:2].

Jesus told the apostles of the trials that lay ahead of them. Then, pointing to his own example, he urged them to “take courage!” (John 16:1-4a,[33]) Many years later, Jesus’ disciples were still following his self-sacrificing course and displaying courage. At great cost to themselves, they supported one another in their various trials. (Heb. 10:33, 34) Likewise today, we follow Jesus’ example of showing courage. For instance, it takes courage to assist our brothers who are persecuted because of their faith. At times, our brothers may be unjustly imprisoned. When that happens, we must do all that we can for them, including speaking up in their behalf. ([Phil. 1:14;][Heb. 13:19]) Another way we show courage is by continuing to preach “with boldness.” ([Acts 14:3]) Like Jesus, we are determined to preach the Kingdom message, even though people may oppose and persecute us. w19.01 22-23 ¶8-9

^ (John 16:2) Men will expel you from the synagogue. In fact, the hour is coming when everyone who kills you will think he has offered a sacred service to God.

^ (John 16:1-4) “I have said these things to you so that you may not be stumbled. 2 Men will expel you from the synagogue. In fact, the hour is coming when everyone who kills you will think he has offered a sacred service to God. 3 But they will do these things because they have not come to know either the Father or me. 4 Nevertheless, I have told you these things so that when the hour for them to happen arrives, you will remember that I told them to you. “I did not tell you these things at first, because I was with you.

^ (John 16:33) I have said these things to you so that by means of me you may have peace. In the world you will have tribulation, but take courage! I have conquered the world.”

^ (Heb. 10:33, 34) At times you were publicly exposed* both to reproaches and to tribulations, and at times you shared* with those who were having such an experience. 34 For you expressed sympathy for those in prison and you accepted joyfully the plundering of your belongings, knowing that you yourselves have a better and an enduring possession.

Lit., “were exposed as in a theater.”

Or “stood side by side.”

^ (Phil. 1:14) Now most of the brothers in the Lord have gained confidence because of my prison bonds, and they are showing all the more courage to speak the word of God fearlessly.

^ (Heb. 13:19) But I especially urge you to pray so that I may be restored to you the sooner.

^ (Acts 14:3) So they spent considerable time speaking with boldness by the authority of Jehovah, who bore witness to the word of his undeserved kindness by allowing signs and wonders to be performed through them.

Tuesday, January 7

Let us consider one another so as to incite to love and fine works, not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another.—Heb. 10:24, 25.

What can help you to give encouraging comments at the meetings? Most important is that you prepare for each meeting. When you plan ahead and prepare well, you will feel more confident about commenting. ([Prov. 21:5]) What is involved in preparing well for the meeting? Begin each study session by asking Jehovah to give you holy spirit. ([Luke 11:13;][1 John 5:14]) Then take a few minutes to look over the lesson. Analyze the title, subheadings, illustrations, and teaching boxes. As you now study each paragraph, read as many of the cited scriptures as you can. Meditate on the information, giving special attention to points you wish to comment on. The better you prepare, the more you will benefit and the easier it may be for you to comment.—[2 Cor. 9:6]. w19.01 9 ¶6; 11-12 ¶13-15

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Prov. 21:5) The plans of the diligent surely lead to success,* But all who are hasty surely head for poverty.

Or “advantage.”

^ (Luke 11:13) Therefore, if you, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more so will the Father in heaven give holy spirit to those asking him!”

^ (1 John 5:14) And this is the confidence* that we have toward him, that no matter what we ask according to his will, he hears us.

Or “freeness of speech.”

^ (2 Cor. 9:6) But as to this, whoever sows sparingly will also reap sparingly, and whoever sows bountifully will also reap bountifully.

Thursday, January 9

The holy ones in the earth, the majestic ones, bring me great delight.—[Ps. 16:3].

The psalmist David did not limit his circle of friends to just his peers. Can you recall the name of a “majestic” one who became his dear friend? His name was Jonathan. In fact, their friendship was one of the most beautiful recorded in the Scriptures. Did you know, however, that Jonathan was about 30 years older than David? What, then, was the basis for their friendship? Faith in God, mutual respect, and seeing each other’s courage as they fought God’s enemies. ([1 Sam. 13:3;][14:13;][17:48-50;][18:1]) Like David and Jonathan, we too find “great delight” in loving those who love Jehovah and who show their faith in him. Kiera, who has served God for years, says, “I’ve made friends with people from around the world, people of many different backgrounds and cultures.” When you broaden out in this way, you will see clear evidence of the uniting power of God’s Word and spirit. w18.12 26 ¶11-13

^ (Ps. 16:3) And the holy ones in the earth, The majestic ones, bring me great delight.”

^ (1 Sam. 13:3) Then Jonʹa·than struck down the garrison of the Phi·lisʹtines that was in Geʹba, and the Phi·lisʹtines heard about it. And Saul had the horn blown throughout all the land, saying: “Let the Hebrews hear!”

^ (1 Sam. 14:13) And Jonʹa·than climbed up on his hands and feet, and his armor-bearer was behind him; and the Phi·lisʹtines began to fall before Jonʹa·than, and his armor-bearer was putting them to death behind him.

^ (1 Sam. 17:48-50) Then the Phi·lisʹtine rose and drew steadily closer to meet David, but David ran quickly toward the battle line to meet the Phi·lisʹtine. 49 David thrust his hand into his bag and took a stone from there and slung it. He struck the Phi·lisʹtine in the forehead, and the stone sank into his forehead and he fell facedown on the ground. 50 So David prevailed over the Phi·lisʹtine with a sling and a stone; he struck down the Phi·lisʹtine and put him to death, though there was no sword in David’s hand.

^ (1 Sam. 18:1) As soon as David had finished speaking to Saul, Jonʹa·than and David became bound together in close friendship,* and Jonʹa·than began to love him as himself.*

Or “Jonathan’s soul became bound with David’s soul.”

Or “as his own soul.”

Friday, January 10

Whoever divorces his wife, except on the grounds of sexual immorality, and marries another commits adultery.—[Matt. 19:9].

The expression “sexual immorality” covers a range of sexual sins outside of marriage: adultery, prostitution, sex relations between unmarried individuals, homosexuality, and bestiality. If, for example, a married man engages in sexual immorality, his wife can decide whether to divorce him or not. Significantly, Jesus did not say that a mate’s immorality (por·neiʹa) must absolutely lead to divorce. For example, a wife might choose to maintain the marriage despite her husband’s having been immoral. She might still love him; she might be willing to forgive him and work with him to improve their marriage. Realistically, if she got a divorce but did not remarry, she would face challenges. What of her material and sexual needs? What about loneliness? Are there children to consider? ([1 Cor. 7:14]) Clearly, the divorced innocent one would face serious issues. w18.12 12 ¶10-11

^ (Matt. 19:9) I say to you that whoever divorces his wife, except on the grounds of sexual immorality, and marries another commits adultery.”

^ (1 Cor. 7:14) For the unbelieving husband is sanctified in relation to his wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified in relation to the brother; otherwise, your children would be unclean, but now they are holy.

Saturday, January 11

O you who love Jehovah, hate what is bad.—[Ps. 97:10].

Jehovah hates unrighteousness. ([Isa. 61:8]) While he knows that we have some wrong inclinations because of inherited imperfection, he exhorts us to cultivate similar hatred for unrighteousness. Meditating on why Jehovah detests badness will help us make his view our own, giving us added strength to resist wrongdoing. Cultivating Jehovah’s view of unrighteousness will also help us identify certain practices as wrong, even though they are not specifically mentioned in God’s Word. For example, lap dancing is a form of lewd conduct that is becoming more common in the world. Some might excuse such conduct, reasoning that it is not the same as outright sexual relations. But do such actions reflect the thinking of God, who abhors every kind of badness? Let us stay far from wrongdoing by cultivating self-control as well as an abhorrence for what Jehovah hates.—[Rom. 12:9]. w18.11 25 ¶11-12

^ (Ps. 97:10) O you who love Jehovah, hate what is bad. He is guarding the lives* of his loyal ones; He rescues them from the hand* of the wicked.

Or “souls.”

Or “power.”

^ (Isa. 61:8) For I, Jehovah, love justice; I hate robbery and unrighteousness. I will faithfully give them their wages, And I will make an everlasting covenant with them.

^ (Rom. 12:9) Let your love be without hypocrisy. Abhor what is wicked; cling to what is good.

Sunday, January 12

The righteous one will live by his faithfulness.—[Hab. 2:4].

The apostle Paul saw Jehovah’s assurance as so significant that he quoted this verse three times! ([Rom. 1:17;][Gal. 3:11;][Heb. 10:38]) Whatever difficulties the righteous one may suffer, he will by his faith and trust live to see the fulfillment of God’s purposes. Jehovah tells us to look beyond the present. The book of Habakkuk provides a powerful lesson for all of us living in these last days. Jehovah extends his promise of life to any righteous person who displays faith and trust in Him. Let us continue to strengthen our faith and trust in God, no matter what distress and anxiety we face. Through Habakkuk, Jehovah assures us that He will support and deliver us. He kindly asks us to trust in him and to wait patiently for his appointed time when, under God’s Kingdom, the whole earth will be filled with his happy and mild-tempered worshippers.—[Matt. 5:5;] Heb. 10:36-39. w18.11 16-17 ¶15-17

^ (Hab. 2:4) Look at the one who is proud;* He is not upright within himself. But the righteous one will live by his faithfulness.*

Or “Look! His soul is swelled up.”

Or possibly, “faith; belief.”

^ (Rom. 1:17) For in it God’s righteousness is being revealed by faith and for faith, just as it is written: “But the righteous one will live by reason of faith.”

^ (Gal. 3:11) Moreover, it is evident that by law no one is declared righteous with God, because “the righteous one will live by reason of faith.”

^ (Heb. 10:38) “But my righteous one will live by reason of faith,” and “if he shrinks back, I have* no pleasure in him.”

Or “my soul has.”

^ (Matt. 5:5) “Happy are the mild-tempered, since they will inherit the earth.

^ (Heb. 10:36-39) For you need endurance, so that after you have done the will of God, you may receive the fulfillment of the promise. 37 For yet “a very little while,” and “the one who is coming will arrive and will not delay.” 38 “But my righteous one will live by reason of faith,” and “if he shrinks back, I have* no pleasure in him.” 39 Now we are not the sort who shrink back to destruction, but the sort who have faith for the preserving of our lives.*

Or “my soul has.”

Or “souls.”

Wednesday, January 15

Walk worthily of the calling with which you were called, with all humility.—[Eph. 4:1, 2].

A remarkable example of showing self-control when we are provoked can be found at 2 Samuel 16:5-13. David and his servants endured reproach and physical assault by Shimei, a relative of King Saul’s. David did so despite having the power to put an end to it. How did David muster up the strength to control his spirit? The superscription of Psalm 3 indicates that it was composed when David “was fleeing from his son Absalom.” Verses 1 and 2 fit events described in chapter 16 of Second Samuel. Then [Psalm 3:4] highlights David’s confidence: “I will call aloud to Jehovah, and he will answer me.” We too can pray when under attack. In response, Jehovah provides his holy spirit, which can help us to endure. Can you think of a situation in which you need to exercise self-restraint or freely forgive unwarranted animosity? Are you confident that Jehovah can see your affliction and bestow a blessing? w18.09 6-7 ¶16-17

^ (Eph. 4:1, 2) Therefore I, the prisoner in the Lord, appeal to you to walk worthily of the calling with which you were called, 2 with all humility* and mildness, with patience, putting up with one another in love,

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (2 Sam. 16:5-13) When King David reached Ba·huʹrim, a man of the family of Saul’s house named Shimʹe·i, the son of Geʹra, came out shouting curses as he approached. 6 He was throwing stones at David and at all the servants of King David, as well as at all the people and the mighty men on his right and on his left. 7 Shimʹe·i said as he cursed: “Get out, get out, you bloodguilty man! You worthless man! 8 Jehovah has brought back on you all the bloodguilt for the house of Saul, in whose place you have ruled as king, but Jehovah gives the kingship into the hand of Abʹsa·lom your son. Now calamity has overtaken you because you are a bloodguilty man!” 9 Then A·bishʹai the son of Ze·ruʹiah said to the king: “Why should this dead dog curse my lord the king? Let me go over, please, and take off his head.” 10 But the king said: “What do I have to do with you, you sons of Ze·ruʹiah? Let him curse me, for Jehovah has said to him, ‘Curse David!’ So who should say, ‘Why are you doing this?’” 11 David then said to A·bishʹai and all his servants: “Here my own son, who came from my own body, is seeking my life,* and how much more now a Benʹja·min·ite! Leave him alone so that he may curse me, for Jehovah told him to! 12 Perhaps Jehovah will see my affliction, and Jehovah will restore goodness to me instead of the curses shouted at me this day.” 13 With that David and his men kept going down the road while Shimʹe·i was walking alongside the mountain abreast of him, shouting curses and throwing stones and a lot of dust.

Or “soul.”

^ (Ps. 3:0) A melody of David when he was fleeing from his son Abʹsa·lom.

^ (Ps. 3:1, 2) O Jehovah, why have my adversaries become so numerous? Why are so many rising up against me?  2 Many are saying about me:* “God will not save him.” (Selah)*

Or “my soul.”

See Glossary.

^ (Ps. 3:4) I will call aloud to Jehovah, And he will answer me from his holy mountain. (Selah)

Thursday, January 16

We are God’s fellow workers.—[1 Cor. 3:9].

When witnessing, we should always be considerate and respectful, which includes getting to know the local people well. Remember that when we go from door to door, we are uninvited guests. How important, then, that we call at a time when people might be more inclined to converse! ([Matt. 7:12]) For example, do people in your territory like to sleep longer on weekends? If so, you may be able to start your ministry by doing street work, public witnessing, or return visits on people you know will be up and about. Many people are very busy, so it may be appropriate to keep your visits brief, at least initially. (1 Cor. 9:20-23) When people see that we are aware of their circumstances or busy schedules, they may be more willing to have us call back. Clearly, the fruitage of God’s spirit should be reflected in our ministry. When it is, we truly become “God’s fellow workers”—even a means by which Jehovah may draw someone to the truth.—1 Cor. 3:6, 7. w18.09 32 ¶15-17

^ (1 Cor. 3:9) For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

^ (Matt. 7:12) “All things, therefore, that you want men to do to you, you also must do to them. This, in fact, is what the Law and the Prophets mean.

^ (1 Cor. 9:20-23) To the Jews I became as a Jew in order to gain Jews; to those under law I became as under law, though I myself am not under law, in order to gain those under law. 21 To those without law I became as without law, although I am not without law toward God but under law toward Christ, in order to gain those without law. 22 To the weak I became weak, in order to gain the weak. I have become all things to people of all sorts, so that I might by all possible means save some. 23 But I do all things for the sake of the good news, in order to share it with others.

^ (1 Cor. 3:6, 7) I planted, A·polʹlos watered, but God kept making it grow, 7 so that neither is the one who plants anything nor is the one who waters, but God who makes it grow.

Friday, January 17

Happy are the mild-tempered, since they will inherit the earth.—[Matt. 5:5].

How can being mild-tempered contribute to happiness? After coming to an accurate knowledge of the truth, individuals change. At one time, they may have been harsh, quarrelsome, and aggressive. But now they have clothed themselves with “the new personality” and display “the tender affections of compassion, kindness, humility, mildness, and patience.” ([Col. 3:9-12]) As a result, they now enjoy a peaceful, loving, and happier life. Furthermore, God’s Word promises that such ones will “inherit the earth.” ([Ps. 37:8-10,][29]) In what sense do the mild-tempered “inherit the earth”? Jesus’ spirit-anointed disciples inherit the earth when they rule over it as kings and priests. ([Rev. 20:6]) Millions of others who do not have the heavenly calling, however, will inherit the earth in the sense that they will be allowed to live here forever in perfection, peace, and happiness. w18.09 19 ¶8-9

^ (Matt. 5:5) “Happy are the mild-tempered, since they will inherit the earth.

^ (Col. 3:9-12) Do not lie to one another. Strip off the old personality* with its practices, 10 and clothe yourselves with the new personality, which through accurate knowledge is being made new according to the image of the One who created it, 11 where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, foreigner, Scythʹi·an,* slave, or freeman; but Christ is all things and in all. 12 Accordingly, as God’s chosen ones, holy and loved, clothe yourselves with the tender affections of compassion, kindness, humility,* mildness, and patience.

Lit., “man.”

“Scythian” implied an uncivilized person.

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Ps. 37:8-10) Let go of anger and abandon rage; Do not become upset and turn to doing evil.*  9 For evil men will be done away with, But those hoping in Jehovah will possess the earth. 10 Just a little while longer, and the wicked will be no more; You will look at where they were, And they will not be there.

Or possibly, “Do not become upset, for it can only lead to harm.”

^ (Ps. 37:29) The righteous will possess the earth, And they will live forever on it.

^ (Rev. 20:6) Happy and holy is anyone having part in the first resurrection; over these the second death has no authority, but they will be priests of God and of the Christ, and they will rule as kings with him for the 1,000 years.

Saturday, January 18

Everyone must be quick to listen.—[Jas. 1:19].

Jehovah himself sets the superlative example in this regard. ([Gen. 18:32;][Josh. 10:14]) Consider what we can learn from the interchange recorded at Exodus 32:11-14. Although not needing Moses’ input, Jehovah gave Moses an opportunity to reveal how he felt. What human would listen at length to the reasoning of someone who has displayed faulty thinking and then act on that person’s word? Yet, Jehovah listens patiently to humans who call on him in faith. Each of us does well to ask: ‘If Jehovah can stoop down to deal with people and listen to them as he did with Abraham, Rachel, Moses, Joshua, Manoah, Elijah, and Hezekiah, should I not be better at honoring all my brothers, dignifying them, listening to their ideas, and even acting on their good ideas? Does someone in my congregation or in my family deserve my attention right now? What should I do about that? What will I do about that?’—[Gen. 30:6;][Judg. 13:9;] 1 Ki. 17:22; 2 Chron. 30:20. w18.09 6 ¶14-15

^ (Jas. 1:19) Know this, my beloved brothers: Everyone must be quick to listen, slow to speak, slow to anger,

^ (Gen. 18:32) Finally he said: “Jehovah, please, do not become hot with anger, but let me speak just once more: Suppose only ten are found there.” He answered: “I will not destroy it for the sake of the ten.”

^ (Josh. 10:14) There has never been a day like that one, either before it or after it, when Jehovah listened to the voice of a man, for Jehovah was fighting for Israel.

^ (Ex. 32:11-14) Then Moses appealed to* Jehovah his God and said: “Why, O Jehovah, should you turn your burning anger against your people after bringing them out of the land of Egypt with great power and with a mighty hand? 12 Why should the Egyptians say, ‘He had evil intentions when he led them out. He wanted to kill them in the mountains and exterminate them from the surface of the earth’? Turn from your burning anger and reconsider* your decision to bring this calamity on your people. 13 Remember your servants Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, to whom you swore by yourself and said: ‘I will multiply your offspring* like the stars of the heavens, and I will give all this land that I have designated to your offspring,* so that they may take it as a permanent possession.’” 14 So Jehovah began to reconsider* the calamity that he had spoken of bringing on his people.

Or “softened the face of.”

Or “feel regret over.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “felt regret over.”

^ (Gen. 30:6) Then Rachel said: “God has acted as my judge and has also listened to my voice, so that he gave me a son.” That is why she named him Dan.*

Meaning “Judge.”

^ (Judg. 13:9) So the true God listened to Ma·noʹah, and the angel of the true God came again to the woman while she was sitting in the field; her husband Ma·noʹah was not with her.

^ (1 Ki. 17:22) Jehovah listened to E·liʹjah’s request, and the life* of the child came back into him, and he revived.*

Or “soul.”

Or “came to life.”

^ (2 Chron. 30:20) And Jehovah listened to Hez·e·kiʹah and pardoned* the people.

Lit., “healed.”

Sunday, January 19

The generous person will prosper, and whoever refreshes others will himself be refreshed.—[Prov. 11:25].

It can be a challenge to maintain a generous spirit when we are surrounded by people who put their own interests ahead of those of others. However, Jesus stated that the two greatest commandments are to love Jehovah with our whole heart, soul, mind, and strength and to love our neighbor as ourselves. (Mark 12:28-31) Those who love Jehovah imitate him. Jehovah gives to others, and so does Jesus. And they recommend that we do the same, for it will make us truly happy. If we strive to manifest this generous spirit in our dealings with both God and neighbor, we will bring honor to Jehovah and benefit ourselves and others. No doubt you are already striving to give of yourself to help others, especially fellow believers. ([Gal. 6:10]) If you continue to do so, you will surely be loved and appreciated, and you will be happy as a result. w18.08 22 ¶19-20

^ (Prov. 11:25) The generous person* will prosper,* And whoever refreshes* others will himself be refreshed.

Or “soul.”

Lit., “will be made fat.”

Lit., “freely waters.”

^ (Mark 12:28-31) One of the scribes who had come up and heard them disputing, knowing that he had answered them in a fine way, asked him: “Which commandment is first* of all?” 29 Jesus answered: “The first is, ‘Hear, O Israel, Jehovah our God is one Jehovah, 30 and you must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind and with your whole strength.’ 31 The second is this, ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’ There is no other commandment greater than these.”

Or “most important.”

^ (Gal. 6:10) So, then, as long as we have the opportunity,* let us work what is good toward all, but especially toward those related to us in the faith.

Lit., “appointed time.”

Monday, January 20

Stop judging by the outward appearance.—[John 7:24].

Jehovah places no significance on racial, ethnic, national, tribal, or linguistic differences. Any man or woman who fears God and does what is right is acceptable to him. (Gal. 3:26-28; Rev. 7:9, 10) No doubt, you acknowledge that this is true. But what if you have grown up in a land or in a home filled with prejudice? While you might see yourself as being impartial, deep inside, prejudice may linger. Even Peter, who had the privilege of revealing Jehovah’s impartiality, later manifested prejudice. ([Gal. 2:11-14]) How can we stop judging by the outward appearance? We need to examine ourselves carefully in the light of God’s Word to see if we are holding on to any prejudiced thoughts or feelings. ([Ps. 119:105]) We might also need loving help from others who may see prejudiced attitudes in us, even if we cannot see them in ourselves. ([Gal. 2:11,][14]) It could be that these attitudes are so ingrained in us that we are not conscious of them. w18.08 9 ¶5-6

^ (John 7:24) Stop judging by the outward appearance, but judge with righteous judgment.”

^ (Gal. 3:26-28) You are all, in fact, sons of God through your faith in Christ Jesus. 27 For all of you who were baptized into Christ have put on Christ. 28 There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither slave nor freeman, there is neither male nor female, for you are all one in union with Christ Jesus.

^ (Rev. 7:9, 10) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands. 10 And they keep shouting with a loud voice, saying: “Salvation we owe to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb.”

Or “languages.”

^ (Gal. 2:11-14) However, when Ceʹphas* came to Antioch, I resisted* him face-to-face, because he was clearly in the wrong.* 12 For before certain men from James arrived, he used to eat with people of the nations; but when they arrived, he stopped doing this and separated himself, fearing those of the circumcised class. 13 The rest of the Jews also joined him in putting on this pretense,* so that even Barʹna·bas was led along with them in their pretense.* 14 But when I saw that they were not walking in step with the truth of the good news, I said to Ceʹphas* before them all: “If you, though you are a Jew, live as the nations do and not as Jews do, how can you compel people of the nations to live according to Jewish practice?”

Also called Peter.

Or “confronted.”

Or “he stood condemned.”

Or “hypocrisy.”

Or “hypocrisy.”

Also called Peter.

^ (Ps. 119:105) Your word is a lamp to my foot, And a light for my path.

^ (Gal. 2:11) However, when Ceʹphas* came to Antioch, I resisted* him face-to-face, because he was clearly in the wrong.*

Also called Peter.

Or “confronted.”

Or “he stood condemned.”

^ (Gal. 2:14) But when I saw that they were not walking in step with the truth of the good news, I said to Ceʹphas* before them all: “If you, though you are a Jew, live as the nations do and not as Jews do, how can you compel people of the nations to live according to Jewish practice?”

Also called Peter.

Tuesday, January 21

Let your light shine before men.—[Matt. 5:16].

Ask yourself: ‘Is my complete allegiance to Jehovah evident to others? Do I look for opportunities to identify myself as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses?’ Jehovah would be deeply saddened if after he has selected us as his people, we were to hesitate to let others know that we belong to him. ([Ps. 119:46;][Mark 8:38]) Sad to say, some individuals have blurred the distinction between their serving God and their not serving him by imitating “the spirit of the world.” ([1 Cor. 2:12]) That is a spirit that caters to ‘the desires of one’s flesh.’ ([Eph. 2:3]) For example, despite all the counsel that has been given on the subject, some still prefer styles of dress and grooming that are immodest. They wear tight-fitting and revealing clothing, even to Christian gatherings. Or they have adopted extreme haircuts and hairdos. (1 Tim. 2:9, 10) As a result, when they are in a crowd, it may be difficult to tell who belongs to Jehovah and who is “a friend of the world.”—[Jas. 4:4]. w18.07 24-25 ¶11-12

^ (Matt. 5:16) Likewise, let your light shine before men, so that they may see your fine works and give glory to your Father who is in the heavens.

^ (Ps. 119:46) I will speak about your reminders in front of kings, And I will not be ashamed.

^ (Mark 8:38) For whoever becomes ashamed of me and my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, the Son of man will also be ashamed of him when he comes in the glory of his Father with the holy angels.”

^ (1 Cor. 2:12) Now we received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit that is from God, so that we might know the things that have been kindly given us by God.

^ (Eph. 2:3) Yes, among them we all at one time conducted ourselves in harmony with the desires of our flesh, carrying out the will of the flesh and of our thoughts, and we were naturally children of wrath just as the rest.

^ (1 Tim. 2:9, 10) Likewise, the women should adorn themselves in appropriate* dress, with modesty and soundness of mind,* not with styles of hair braiding and gold or pearls or very expensive clothing, 10 but in the way that is proper for women professing devotion to God, namely, through good works.

Or “respectable.”

Or “good judgment; sensibleness.”

^ (Jas. 4:4) Adulteresses,* do you not know that friendship with the world is enmity with God? Whoever, therefore, wants to be a friend of the world is making himself an enemy of God.

Or “You unfaithful ones.”

Wednesday, January 22

All of you are brothers.—[Matt. 23:8].

One sense in which we are “brothers” is that all of us have descended from Adam. ([Acts 17:26]) But there is more. Jesus explained that his disciples were brothers and sisters because they recognized Jehovah as their heavenly Father. ([Matt. 12:50]) In addition, they had become members of one large spiritual family, united by love and faith. Thus in their letters, the apostles often referred to fellow disciples as ‘brothers and sisters.’ ([Rom. 1:13;] 1 Pet. 2:17;[1 John 3:13]) After making it clear that we should view one another as brothers and sisters, Jesus stressed the need for humility. (Matt. 23:11, 12) Undue pride among his apostles had led to some disunity. And pride of race could also have been a problem. Did the Jews have reason to be proud because they were descendants of Abraham? Many Jews had that deep-seated conviction. But John the Baptist told them: “God is able to raise up children for Abraham from these stones.”—[Luke 3:8]. w18.06 9-10 ¶8-9

^ (Matt. 23:8) But you, do not you be called Rabbi, for one is your Teacher, and all of you are brothers.

^ (Acts 17:26) And he made out of one man every nation of men to dwell on the entire surface of the earth, and he decreed the appointed times and the set limits of where men would dwell,

^ (Matt. 12:50) For whoever does the will of my Father who is in heaven, that one is my brother and sister and mother.”

^ (Rom. 1:13) But I do not want you to be unaware, brothers, that many times I have intended to come to you—but I have been prevented until now—in order that I might acquire some fruitage also among you just as among the rest of the nations.

^ (1 Pet. 2:17) Honor men of all sorts, have love for the whole association of brothers,* be in fear of God, honor the king.

Lit., “the brotherhood.”

^ (1 John 3:13) Do not be surprised, brothers, that the world hates you.

^ (Matt. 23:11, 12) But the greatest one among you must be your minister. 12 Whoever exalts himself will be humbled, and whoever humbles himself will be exalted.

^ (Luke 3:8) Therefore, produce fruits that befit repentance. Do not start saying to yourselves, ‘We have Abraham as our father.’ For I say to you that God is able to raise up children for Abraham from these stones.

Thursday, January 23

A man of knowledge restrains his words.—[Prov. 17:27].

When faced with frustrating situations or recurring personality conflicts, do we control our lips and our temper? ([Prov. 10:19;][Matt. 5:22]) When provoked by others, we need to learn to “yield place to the wrath.” Whose wrath? Jehovah’s wrath. (Rom. 12:17-21) If we keep looking to Jehovah, we will show him due respect by yielding to his wrath, patiently waiting for him to take action when he deems it necessary. To do otherwise and avenge ourselves in some way would be tantamount to disrespecting Jehovah. Do we faithfully follow the latest directions that Jehovah has given us? If so, we will not rely on always doing things the way we have done them in the past. Rather, we will be quick to follow any new direction that Jehovah provides through his organization. ([Heb. 13:17]) At the same time, we will be careful that we “do not go beyond the things that are written.” ([1 Cor. 4:6]) In so doing, we keep our eyes fixed on Jehovah. w18.07 15-16 ¶17-18

^ (Prov. 17:27) A man of knowledge restrains his words, And a discerning man will remain calm.*

Lit., “cool of spirit.”

^ (Prov. 10:19) When words are many, transgression cannot be avoided, But whoever controls his lips acts discreetly.

^ (Matt. 5:22) However, I say to you that everyone who continues wrathful with his brother will be accountable to the court of justice; and whoever addresses his brother with an unspeakable word of contempt will be accountable to the Supreme Court; whereas whoever says, ‘You despicable fool!’ will be liable to the fiery Ge·henʹna.

^ (Rom. 12:17-21) Return evil for evil to no one. Take into consideration what is fine from the viewpoint of all men. 18 If possible, as far as it depends on you, be peaceable with all men. 19 Do not avenge yourselves, beloved, but yield place to the wrath; for it is written: “‘Vengeance is mine; I will repay,’ says Jehovah.” 20 But “if your enemy is hungry, feed him; if he is thirsty, give him something to drink; for by doing this you will heap fiery coals on his head.” 21 Do not let yourself be conquered by the evil, but keep conquering the evil with the good.

^ (Heb. 13:17) Be obedient to those who are taking the lead among you and be submissive, for they are keeping watch over you* as those who will render an account, so that they may do this with joy and not with sighing, for this would be damaging to you.

Or “your souls.”

^ (1 Cor. 4:6) Now, brothers, these things I have applied* to myself and A·polʹlos for your good, that through us you may learn the rule: “Do not go beyond the things that are written,” so that you may not be puffed up with pride, favoring one against the other.

Or “transferred.”

Friday, January 24

Press on to maturity.—[Heb. 6:1].

As you advance toward Christian maturity, you will find that principles become more important to you. That is because laws may apply to a specific situation, whereas principles are far broader in application. For example, a young child does not understand the dangers of bad associations, so a discerning parent will set rules to protect him. ([1 Cor. 15:33]) But as the child matures, his thinking ability develops, and he is able to reason on Bible-based principles. Thus, he can increasingly make wise decisions in choosing his associates. (1 Cor. 13:11;[14:20]) When we reason on godly principles, our conscience increasingly becomes a more reliable guide, attuned to God’s thinking. Do we have everything we need to make wise decisions that please Jehovah? Yes. By making skilled use of the laws and principles found in God’s Word, we will be “fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.”—2 Tim. 3:16, 17. w18.06 19 ¶14; 20 ¶16-17

^ (Heb. 6:1) Therefore, now that we have moved beyond the primary doctrine about the Christ, let us press on to maturity, not laying a foundation again, namely, repentance from dead works and faith in God,

^ (1 Cor. 15:33) Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.*

Or “corrupt good morals.”

^ (1 Cor. 13:11) When I was a child, I used to speak as a child, to think as a child, to reason as a child; but now that I have become a man, I have done away with the traits of a child.

^ (1 Cor. 14:20) Brothers, do not become young children in your understanding, but be young children as to badness; and become full-grown in your understanding.

^ (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

Saturday, January 25

Who really is my neighbor?—[Luke 10:29].

Jesus’ story showed that a Samaritan could teach the Jews the meaning of true neighborly love. (Luke 10:25-37) To fulfill their commission, Jesus’ disciples needed to conquer the pride and prejudice they had. Before ascending to heaven, he assigned them to bear witness to “all Judea and Samaria, and to the most distant part of the earth.” ([Acts 1:8]) Jesus had earlier prepared them for such an extensive assignment by drawing their attention to good qualities in foreigners. He praised a foreign army officer for his outstanding faith. ([Matt. 8:5-10]) In his hometown of Nazareth, Jesus spoke of how Jehovah had favored foreigners, such as the Phoenician widow from Zarephath and the Syrian leper Naaman. ([Luke 4:25-27]) And Jesus not only preached to a Samaritan woman but he spent two days in a Samaritan town because of the people’s interest in his message.—John 4:21-24,[40]. w18.06 10 ¶10-11

^ (Luke 10:29) But wanting to prove himself righteous, the man said to Jesus: “Who really is my neighbor?”

^ (Acts 1:8) But you will receive power when the holy spirit comes upon you, and you will be witnesses of me in Jerusalem, in all Ju·deʹa and Sa·marʹi·a, and to the most distant part of the earth.”

^ (Matt. 8:5-10) When he entered Ca·perʹna·um, an army officer came to him, pleading with him 6 and saying: “Sir, my servant is laid up in the house with paralysis, and he is suffering terribly.”* 7 He said to him: “When I get there, I will cure him.” 8 The army officer replied: “Sir, I am not worthy to have you come under my roof, but just say the word and my servant will be healed. 9 For I too am a man under authority, having soldiers under me, and I say to this one, ‘Go!’ and he goes, and to another, ‘Come!’ and he comes, and to my slave, ‘Do this!’ and he does it.” 10 When Jesus heard that, he was amazed and said to those following him: “I tell you the truth, with no one in Israel have I found so great a faith.

Or “is terribly afflicted.”

^ (Luke 4:25-27) For instance, I tell you in truth: There were many widows in Israel in the days of E·liʹjah when heaven was shut up for three years and six months, and a great famine came on all the land. 26 Yet E·liʹjah was sent to none of those women, but only to a widow in Zarʹe·phath in the land of Siʹdon. 27 Also, there were many lepers in Israel in the time of E·liʹsha the prophet; yet not one of them was cleansed, only Naʹa·man the Syrian.”

^ (John 4:21-24) Jesus said to her: “Believe me, woman, the hour is coming when neither on this mountain nor in Jerusalem will you worship the Father. 22 You worship what you do not know; we worship what we know, because salvation begins with the Jews. 23 Nevertheless, the hour is coming, and it is now, when the true worshippers will worship the Father with spirit and truth, for indeed, the Father is looking for ones like these to worship him. 24 God is a Spirit, and those worshipping him must worship with spirit and truth.”

^ (John 4:40) So when the Sa·marʹi·tans came to him, they asked him to stay with them, and he stayed there two days.

Sunday, January 26

Put on the complete suit of armor from God so that you may be able to stand firm against the crafty acts of the Devil.—[Eph. 6:11].

The apostle Paul likened our life as Christians to that of soldiers engaged in hand-to-hand combat. Of course, the war we fight is spiritual, not literal. Even so, our enemies are real. Satan and the demons are skilled warriors with vast experience. At first glance, our prospects may seem bleak. Young Christians in particular may appear to be vulnerable. How can they hope to win against superhuman, wicked spirit forces? The fact is, young ones can win, and they are winning! Why? Because they “go on acquiring power in the Lord.” But they do more than draw on God’s power. They are dressed for battle. Like well-trained soldiers, they have “put on the complete suit of armor from God.” ([Eph. 6:10-12]) When developing his illustration, Paul perhaps had in mind the armor worn by Roman legionnaires.—[Acts 28:16]. w18.05 27 ¶1-2

^ (Eph. 6:11) Put on the complete suit of armor from God so that you may be able to stand firm against the crafty acts* of the Devil;

Or “the schemes.”

^ (Eph. 6:10-12) Finally, go on acquiring power in the Lord and in the mightiness of his strength. 11 Put on the complete suit of armor from God so that you may be able to stand firm against the crafty acts* of the Devil; 12 because we have a struggle,* not against blood and flesh, but against the governments, against the authorities, against the world rulers of this darkness, against the wicked spirit forces in the heavenly places.

Or “the schemes.”

Lit., “wrestling.”

^ (Acts 28:16) When finally we entered Rome, Paul was permitted to stay by himself with the soldier guarding him.

Monday, January 27

Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.—[Matt. 6:9].

The foremost reason why we share in the preaching work is to glorify Jehovah and sanctify his name before mankind. ([John 15:1,][8]) Yet, we cannot make God’s name more sacred. It is already sacred, or holy, in the absolute sense. But note what the prophet Isaiah stated: “Jehovah of armies—he is the One you should regard as holy.” ([Isa. 8:13]) We sanctify God’s name, among other ways, by regarding it as separate from all other names and by helping others to regard it as holy. For instance, by proclaiming the truth about Jehovah’s wonderful qualities and his unchangeable purpose for mankind, we defend God’s name against Satan’s lies and slander. ([Gen. 3:1-5]) Also, when we strive to help people in our territory to see that Jehovah is worthy “to receive the glory and the honor and the power,” we sanctify God’s name.—[Rev. 4:11]. w18.05 18 ¶3-4

^ (Matt. 6:9) “You must pray, then, this way: “‘Our Father in the heavens, let your name be sanctified.

^ (John 15:1) “I am the true vine, and my Father is the cultivator.

^ (John 15:8) My Father is glorified in this, that you keep bearing much fruit and prove yourselves my disciples.

^ (Isa. 8:13) Jehovah of armies—he is the One you should regard as holy, He is the One you should fear, And he is the One who should cause you to tremble.”

^ (Gen. 3:1-5) Now the serpent was the most cautious* of all the wild animals of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it said to the woman: “Did God really say that you must not eat from every tree of the garden?” 2 At this the woman said to the serpent: “We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden. 3 But God has said about the fruit of the tree that is in the middle of the garden: ‘You must not eat from it, no, you must not touch it; otherwise you will die.’” 4 At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die. 5 For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.”

Or “shrewdest; craftiest.”

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

Tuesday, January 28

It is good to give thanks to Jehovah . . . For you have made me rejoice, O Jehovah, because of your deeds; because of the works of your hands I shout joyfully.—[Ps. 92:1,][4].

The primary reason for setting spiritual goals is to show Jehovah how grateful we are for his love and for what he has done for us. As a young person, think of all you owe to Jehovah. Your life, your faith, the Bible, the congregation, and your wonderful hope for the future. Giving priority to spiritual matters is a way of showing gratitude to God for these blessings, and that brings you closer to him. Once you start working toward spiritual goals, you begin building a record of good works in Jehovah’s eyes. This brings you even closer to him. The apostle Paul promised: “God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name.” ([Heb. 6:10]) You are never too young to set goals. Why not consider which goals are important to you and then start working toward them?—Phil. 1:10, 11. w18.04 26 ¶5-6

^ (Ps. 92:1) It is good to give thanks to Jehovah And to sing praises* to your name, O Most High,

Or “make music.”

^ (Ps. 92:4) For you have made me rejoice, O Jehovah, because of your deeds; Because of the works of your hands I shout joyfully.

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (Phil. 1:10, 11) that you may make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others up to the day of Christ; 11 and that you may be filled with righteous fruit, which is through Jesus Christ, to God’s glory and praise.

Wednesday, January 29

Where the spirit of Jehovah is, there is freedom.—[2 Cor. 3:17].

People of the Roman world, among whom the early Christians lived, prided themselves on being champions of law, justice, and freedom. Yet, much of the power and glory of the Roman Empire was built on the backs of slaves. At one point, some 30 percent of the population were slaves. Undoubtedly, slavery and freedom were topics on the minds of the common people, including Christians. The letters of the apostle Paul have much to say about freedom. However, the objective of his ministry was not social or political reform, the very thing people of that day were seeking. Rather than looking to any human ruler or agency for freedom, Paul and his fellow Christians worked hard to help others learn the good news of God’s Kingdom and the incomparable value of the ransom sacrifice of Christ Jesus. Paul directed his fellow believers to the Source of true freedom. w18.04 8 ¶1-2

^ (2 Cor. 3:17) Now Jehovah* is the Spirit, and where the spirit of Jehovah* is, there is freedom.

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

Thursday, January 30

Simon, Simon, look! Satan has demanded to have all of you to sift you as wheat. But I have made supplication for you that your faith may not give out; and you, once you have returned, strengthen your brothers.—Luke 22:31, 32.

On the night before his death, Jesus told the apostle Peter the above. Peter proved to be a pillar in the early Christian congregation. ([Gal. 2:9]) He encouraged his brothers by his courageous example at Pentecost and thereafter. Toward the end of his long ministry, he wrote to fellow Christians. Explaining why, he stated: “I have written you in few words in order to encourage you and to give an earnest witness that this is the true undeserved kindness of God. Stand firm in it.” ([1 Pet. 5:12]) Peter’s inspired letters have continued to be a source of encouragement to Christians throughout the ages and up to this day. How we need this encouragement as we await the fulfillment of Jehovah’s promises!—[2 Pet. 3:13]. w18.04 17 ¶12-13

^ (Luke 22:31, 32) “Simon, Simon, look! Satan has demanded to have all of you to sift you as wheat. 32 But I have made supplication for you that your faith may not give out; and you, once you have returned, strengthen your brothers.”

^ (Gal. 2:9) and when they recognized the undeserved kindness that was given me, James and Ceʹphas* and John, the ones who seemed to be pillars, gave Barʹna·bas and me the right hand of fellowship,* so that we should go to the nations but they to those who are circumcised.

Also called Peter.

Or “partnership.”

^ (1 Pet. 5:12) Through Sil·vaʹnus,* whom I regard as a faithful brother, I have written you in few words in order to encourage you and to give an earnest witness that this is the true undeserved kindness of God. Stand firm in it.

Also called Silas.

^ (2 Pet. 3:13) But there are new heavens and a new earth that we are awaiting according to his promise, and in these righteousness is to dwell.

Friday, January 31

The one who peers into the perfect law that belongs to freedom and continues in it . . . will be happy in what he does.—[Jas. 1:25].

To be able to do what one wants to do or to live the way one wants to live seems to be much desired by people everywhere. How to satisfy those desires, however, is quite another matter. On the social or political level, many resort to protests, demonstrations, revolts, even revolutions. But do such confrontations achieve the desired results? On the contrary, they often lead to tragedies and loss of life. All of this once again testifies to the truthfulness of King Solomon’s inspired observation: “Man has dominated man to his harm.” ([Eccl. 8:9]) In today’s text, James pointed out the key to finding true happiness and satisfaction. Jehovah, who gave that perfect law, knows best the things humans need in order to be completely happy and satisfied. He gave the first human couple everything that they needed to be happy—including true freedom. w18.04 3 ¶1-3

^ (Jas. 1:25) But the one who peers into the perfect law that belongs to freedom and continues in it has become, not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work; and he will be happy in what he does.

^ (Eccl. 8:9) All of this I have seen, and I applied my heart to every work that has been done under the sun, during the time that man has dominated man to his harm.*

Or “injury; detriment.”

February

Saturday, February 1

Fully accomplish your ministry.—[2 Tim. 4:5].

Jesus had tender feelings for others. People sensed his love for them and responded favorably to the Kingdom message. The more we develop similar tender feelings for people, the more effective we will be in accomplishing our ministry. What can help us show fellow feeling to those to whom we preach? We want to put ourselves in the place of those we meet in the ministry and treat them as we would like to be treated. ([Matt. 7:12]) Consider the needs of each individual. Do not try to use the same approach with everyone we meet in our ministry. Rather, take into consideration the specific circumstances and viewpoints of each individual. Draw the person out with tactful questions. ([Prov. 20:5]) When we draw others out, we in effect allow them to tell us why they need the good news. Once we know that, we can show fellow feeling for their specific needs and respond accordingly, just as Jesus did.—Compare 1 Corinthians 9:19-23. w19.03 20 ¶2; 22 ¶8-9

^ (2 Tim. 4:5) You, though, keep your senses in all things, endure hardship, do the work of an evangelizer,* fully accomplish your ministry.

Or “keep preaching the good news.”

^ (Matt. 7:12) “All things, therefore, that you want men to do to you, you also must do to them. This, in fact, is what the Law and the Prophets mean.

^ (Prov. 20:5) The thoughts* of a man’s heart are like deep waters, But the discerning man draws them out.

Or “intentions.” Lit., “counsel.”

^ (1 Cor. 9:19-23) For though I am free from all people, I have made myself the slave to all, so that I may gain as many people as possible. 20 To the Jews I became as a Jew in order to gain Jews; to those under law I became as under law, though I myself am not under law, in order to gain those under law. 21 To those without law I became as without law, although I am not without law toward God but under law toward Christ, in order to gain those without law. 22 To the weak I became weak, in order to gain the weak. I have become all things to people of all sorts, so that I might by all possible means save some. 23 But I do all things for the sake of the good news, in order to share it with others.

Sunday, February 2

Commit to Jehovah whatever you do, and your plans will succeed.—[Prov. 16:3].

Adam and Eve displayed a callous lack of appreciation for all the good that Jehovah had done for them. We all have the opportunity to show just how much we disagree with the decision that they made. By getting baptized, we show Jehovah that we believe that he has the authority to set the standard of what is right and what is wrong for us. We prove that we love our Father and trust in him. The challenge we face after baptism is to live each day by Jehovah’s standards, not our own. Millions of people are living that way each year. You can be like them if you continue to deepen your understanding of God’s Word, the Bible; associate regularly with your brothers and sisters; and zealously share what you have learned about your loving Father. (Heb. 10:24, 25) When you make decisions, listen to the advice Jehovah gives you through his Word and his organization. ([Isa. 30:21]) Then all you do will be successful.—[Prov. 16:20]. w19.03 7 ¶17-18

^ (Prov. 16:3) Commit to Jehovah whatever you do,* And your plans will succeed.

Lit., “Roll to Jehovah your works.”

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Isa. 30:21) And your own ears will hear a word behind you saying, “This is the way. Walk in it,” in case you should go to the right or in case you should go to the left.

^ (Prov. 16:20) The one who shows insight in a matter will find success,* And happy is the one trusting in Jehovah.

Lit., “good.”

Monday, February 3

Every good gift and every perfect present is from above, coming down from the Father of the celestial lights.—[Jas. 1:17].

Jehovah has given us an abundance of spiritual food. For example, we receive helpful instruction through our meetings, our magazines, and our websites. Have you ever heard a talk, read an article, or watched a broadcast and thought, ‘That is just what I needed’? How can we show our appreciation to Jehovah? ([Col. 3:15]) One way is by regularly thanking him in our prayers for these good gifts. We also express appreciation to Jehovah when we keep our place of worship clean and tidy. We share regularly in cleaning and maintaining our Kingdom Halls, and those who handle electronic equipment used by the congregation do so carefully. When we maintain our Kingdom Halls properly, they will last longer and will need fewer major repairs. That way, we make more money available to build and renovate other Kingdom Halls around the world. w19.02 18 ¶17-18

^ (Jas. 1:17) Every good gift and every perfect present is from above, coming down from the Father of the celestial lights, who does not vary or change like the shifting shadows.*

Or “with whom there is not a variation of the turning of the shadow.”

^ (Col. 3:15) Also, let the peace of the Christ rule in your hearts,* for you were called to that peace in one body. And show yourselves thankful.

Or “control your hearts.”

Tuesday, February 4

These are just the fringes of his ways; only a faint whisper has been heard of him!—[Job 26:14].

Job spent time contemplating the marvels of Jehovah’s creation. ([Job 26:7, 8]) He was awestruck when he thought about the earth, the sky, the clouds, and the thunder, yet he recognized that he knew very little about the vastness of creation. He also felt awe for Jehovah’s expressions. “I have treasured up his sayings,” Job said of God’s words. ([Job 23:12]) Job’s awe and respect for Jehovah moved him. He loved his Father and wanted to please him. Job’s determination to keep his integrity thus grew stronger. We need to do as Job did. We know far more about the marvels of creation than did people of Job’s time. And we have the entire inspired Bible to help us to know Jehovah as he really is. All that we learn can help to fill our heart with awe. Our awe and respect for Jehovah will, in turn, move us to love and obey him and to build up our deep desire to keep our integrity.—[Job 28:28]. w19.02 5 ¶12

^ (Job 26:14) Look! These are just the fringes of his ways; Only a faint whisper has been heard of him! So who can understand his mighty thunder?”

^ (Job 26:7, 8) He stretches out the northern sky* over empty space,* Suspending the earth upon nothing;  8 He wraps up the waters in his clouds, So that the clouds do not burst under their weight;

Lit., “the north.”

Lit., “emptiness.”

^ (Job 23:12) I have not departed from the commandment of his lips. I have treasured up his sayings even more than what was required of me.*

Or “prescribed for me.”

^ (Job 28:28) And he said to man: ‘Look! The fear of Jehovah—that is wisdom, And to turn away from bad is understanding.’”

Wednesday, February 5

I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?—[Ps. 118:6].

Throughout history, human rulers have persecuted Jehovah’s people. They may charge us with various “crimes,” but the real issue is that we choose to “obey God as ruler rather than men.” ([Acts 5:29]) We might be ridiculed, imprisoned, or even physically mistreated. With Jehovah’s help, however, we will not retaliate but will remain mild throughout the test. Consider the example that three Hebrew exiles—Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah—set for us. Mildly, they explained to the king why they would not worship the image he had made. They were willing to accept whatever outcome Jehovah would permit. ([Dan. 3:1,] 8-28) When our loyalty to God is tested, how can we imitate the three Hebrews? We humbly trust that Jehovah will care for us. ([Ps. 118:7]) We answer those who accuse us of wrongdoing in a mild, respectful manner. ([1 Pet. 3:15]) And we absolutely refuse to compromise our friendship with our loving Father. w19.02 10-11 ¶11-13

^ (Ps. 118:6) Jehovah is on my side; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?

^ (Acts 5:29) In answer Peter and the other apostles said: “We must obey God as ruler rather than men.

^ (Dan. 3:1) Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar the king made an image* of gold that was 60 cubits* high and 6 cubits* wide. He set it up on the plain of Duʹra in the province* of Babylon.

Or “statue.”

About 27 m (88 ft). See App. B14.

About 2.7 m (8.8 ft). See App. B14.

Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ (Ps. 118:7) Jehovah is on my side as my helper;* I will look in triumph on those who hate me.

Or possibly, “along with those helping me.”

^ (1 Pet. 3:15) But sanctify the Christ as Lord in your hearts, always ready to make a defense before everyone who demands of you a reason for the hope you have, but doing so with a mild temper and deep respect.

Thursday, February 6

Take courage!—[John 16:33].

We can strengthen our courage by thinking about the hope that the ransom sacrifice of Christ makes possible for us. ([John 3:16;][Eph. 1:7]) In the weeks leading up to the Memorial, we have a special opportunity to build our appreciation for the ransom. During that time, keep up with the Memorial Bible reading and prayerfully meditate on the events surrounding Jesus’ death. Then when we gather for the Lord’s Evening Meal, we will understand more fully the significance of the Memorial emblems and the matchless sacrifice that they represent. When we appreciate what Jesus and Jehovah have done for us and understand how it benefits us and our loved ones, our hope grows stronger, and we are motivated to endure courageously to the end. ([Heb. 12:3]) How grateful we can be that Jesus continues to display humility and courage as our heavenly High Priest, who pleads in our behalf! (Heb. 7:24, 25) To show our appreciation, we must loyally commemorate Jesus’ death, just as he commanded.—Luke 22:19, 20. w19.01 22 ¶8; 23-24 ¶10-11

^ (John 16:33) I have said these things to you so that by means of me you may have peace. In the world you will have tribulation, but take courage! I have conquered the world.”

^ (John 3:16) “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.

^ (Eph. 1:7) By means of him we have the release by ransom through the blood of that one, yes, the forgiveness of our trespasses, according to the riches of his undeserved kindness.

^ (Heb. 12:3) Indeed, consider closely the one who has endured such hostile speech from sinners against their own interests, so that you may not get tired and give up.*

Or “give out in your souls.”

^ (Heb. 7:24, 25) but because he continues alive forever, his priesthood has no successors. 25 So he is able also to save completely those who are approaching God through him, because he is always alive to plead for them.

^ (Luke 22:19, 20) Also, he took a loaf, gave thanks, broke it, and gave it to them, saying: “This means my body, which is to be given in your behalf. Keep doing this in remembrance of me.” 20 Also, he did the same with the cup after they had the evening meal, saying: “This cup means the new covenant by virtue of my blood, which is to be poured out in your behalf.

Friday, February 7

Please take pleasure in my voluntary offerings of praise, O Jehovah.—[Ps. 119:108].

Jehovah has given all of us the privilege to praise him. Our comments at meetings are part of our “sacrifice of praise,” and no one can offer that sacrifice for us. ([Heb. 13:15]) Does Jehovah demand the same type of sacrifice, or comment, from each of us? No, he does not! View the congregation meetings like a meal shared with good friends. Imagine that some friends in the congregation planned a barbecue and asked you to prepare some small item of food. How would you respond? You might feel a little anxious, but you would likely do your best to bring something that everyone could enjoy. Jehovah, our Host, has provided a table full of good things for us at our meetings. ([Ps. 23:5;][Matt. 24:45]) And he is pleased when we bring a simple gift, the best that we can give. So prepare well and participate as freely as you can. Then you will not only feed at Jehovah’s table but also bring a gift to share with the congregation. w19.01 8 ¶3; 13 ¶20

^ (Ps. 119:108) Please take pleasure in my voluntary offerings of praise,* O Jehovah, And teach me your judgments.

Lit., “the voluntary offerings of my mouth.”

^ (Heb. 13:15) Through him let us always offer to God a sacrifice of praise, that is, the fruit of our lips that make public declaration to his name.

^ (Ps. 23:5) You prepare a table for me before my enemies. You refresh* my head with oil; My cup is well-filled.

Or “grease.”

^ (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

Saturday, February 8

Those who pursue other gods multiply their sorrows.—[Ps. 16:4].

In Bible times, false worship often included gross sexual immorality. (Hos. 4:13, 14) To be sure, that form of worship appealed to the sinful flesh. But it did not bring lasting happiness. To the contrary! ‘Those who pursued other gods multiplied their sorrows,’ said David. They also brought untold suffering to countless children. ([Isa. 57:5]) Jehovah detested such cruelty! ([Jer. 7:31]) Today, too, false worship often condones sexual immorality, even homosexuality. But the end results of reveling in so-called moral freedom have not really changed since Bible times. (1 Cor. 6:18, 19) People “multiply their sorrows,” as you may have observed. So young ones, listen to your heavenly Father. Be fully convinced that obedience to him is in your best interests. Impress on your heart that the harm caused by wrongdoing far outweighs any temporary pleasure.—[Gal. 6:8]. w18.12 27-28 ¶16-18

^ (Ps. 16:4) Those who pursue other gods multiply their sorrows. I will never pour out their drink offerings of blood, Nor will my lips mention their names.

^ (Hos. 4:13, 14) On the tops of the mountains they sacrifice, And on the hills they make sacrifices smoke, Under oak trees and storax trees and every big tree, Because their shade is good. That is why your daughters commit prostitution* And your daughters-in-law commit adultery. 14 I will not hold an accounting against your daughters because of their prostitution,* And against your daughters-in-law because of their adultery. For the men go off with the harlots And sacrifice with the temple prostitutes; Such a people without understanding will come to ruin.

Or “immorality; promiscuity.”

Or “immorality; promiscuity.”

^ (Isa. 57:5) Those who are inflamed with passion among big trees, Under every luxuriant tree, Who slaughter the children in the valleys,* Under the clefts of the crags?

Or “wadis.”

^ (Jer. 7:31) They have built the high places of Toʹpheth, which is in the Valley of the Son of Hinʹnom,* in order to burn their sons and their daughters in the fire, something that I had not commanded and that had never even come into my heart.’*

See Glossary, “Gehenna.”

Or “had never entered my thoughts.”

^ (1 Cor. 6:18, 19) Flee from sexual immorality!* Every other sin that a man may commit is outside his body, but whoever practices sexual immorality is sinning against his own body. 19 Do you not know that your body is the temple of the holy spirit within you, which you have from God? Also, you do not belong to yourselves,

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ (Gal. 6:8) because the one sowing with a view to his flesh will reap corruption from his flesh, but the one sowing with a view to the spirit will reap everlasting life from the spirit.

Sunday, February 9

I will behave the same way toward you.—[Hos. 3:3].

If a Christian’s mate committed immorality, the innocent Christian would face a decision. Jesus said that the innocent one would have a basis for getting a divorce and then be free to remarry. ([Matt. 19:9]) On the other hand, the innocent mate could extend forgiveness. That would not be wrong. Hosea took back Gomer. Once Gomer was back with Hosea, she was not to have relations with any other man. Hosea did “not have relations” with Gomer for a while. ([Hos. 3:1-3], ftn.) In time, though, Hosea must have resumed marital relations with her, thereby reflecting God’s willingness to accept his people back and resume his dealings with them. ([Hos. 1:11;][3:4, 5]) What bearing does that have on a marriage today? If an innocent mate decided to maintain the marriage, resuming marital relations would show forgiveness. ([1 Cor. 7:3,][5]) That course would cancel what had been grounds for divorce. Thereafter as a couple, they should work to reflect God’s view of marriage. w18.12 13 ¶13

^ (Hos. 3:3) Then I said to her: “You will remain mine for many days. You must not commit prostitution,* and you must not have relations with another man, and I will behave the same way toward you.”*

Or “engage in immorality (promiscuity).”

Or “I will not have relations with you.”

^ (Matt. 19:9) I say to you that whoever divorces his wife, except on the grounds of sexual immorality, and marries another commits adultery.”

^ (Hos. 3:1-3) Then Jehovah said to me: “Go once again, love the woman who is loved by another man and is committing adultery, just as Jehovah loves the people of Israel while they turn to other gods and love raisin cakes.”* 2 So I purchased her for myself for 15 silver pieces and a hoʹmer measure* and a half of barley. 3 Then I said to her: “You will remain mine for many days. You must not commit prostitution,* and you must not have relations with another man, and I will behave the same way toward you.”*

That is, those used in false worship.

A homer equaled 220 L (200 dry qt). See App. B14.

Or “engage in immorality (promiscuity).”

Or “I will not have relations with you.”

^ (Hos. 1:11) And the people of Judah and of Israel will be gathered together into unity and will choose for themselves one head and go up out of the land, for great will be the day of Jezʹre·el.

^ (Hos. 3:4, 5) It is because for a long time* the people of Israel will dwell without a king, without a prince, without a sacrifice, without a pillar, and without an ephʹod and teraphim statues.* 5 Afterward the people of Israel will come back and look for Jehovah their God and for David their king, and they will come trembling to Jehovah and to his goodness in the final part of the days.

Lit., “many days.”

Or “household gods; idols.”

^ (1 Cor. 7:3) Let the husband give to his wife her due, and let the wife also do likewise to her husband.

^ (1 Cor. 7:5) Do not deprive each other except by mutual consent for an appointed time, so that you may devote time to prayer and may come together again, in order that Satan may not keep tempting you for your lack of self-control.

Monday, February 10

The shrewd one sees the danger and conceals himself.—[Prov. 22:3].

When studying, we do well to consider what bearing Jehovah’s thoughts may have on situations we might face in the future. That way, should we be in a situation requiring an immediate decision, we will not be caught completely off guard. By immediately rejecting the attempted seductions of Potiphar’s wife, Joseph showed that he had given thought to Jehovah’s view of marital faithfulness. ([Gen. 39:8, 9]) Furthermore, his reply to Potiphar’s wife: “How could I commit this great badness and actually sin against God?” indicates that he had made God’s view his own. What about us? Suppose a coworker began manifesting flirtatious behavior. Or what if a sexually explicit message or image was sent to your mobile phone? It is far easier to take a stand if we have already sought out and adopted Jehovah’s view on such matters and have determined in advance what we will do. w18.11 25 ¶13-14

^ (Prov. 22:3) The shrewd one sees the danger and conceals himself, But the inexperienced keep right on going and suffer the consequences.*

Or “penalty.”

^ (Gen. 39:8, 9) But he refused and said to his master’s wife: “Here my master does not know what is with me in the house, and he has entrusted everything he has into my care. 9 There is no one greater in this house than I am, and he has not withheld from me anything at all except you, because you are his wife. So how could I commit this great badness and actually sin against God?”

Tuesday, February 11

I will exult in Jehovah.—[Hab. 3:18].

Some scholars think that this verse literally means “I will jump for joy in the Lord; I will spin round for delight in God.” What a powerful assurance for all of us! Not only has Jehovah given us wonderful promises but he has assured us that he is swiftly working out his great purpose. No doubt, the vital message of Habakkuk is to trust in Jehovah. ([Hab. 2:4]) We can acquire and maintain such trust if we strengthen our relationship with Jehovah by (1) persevering in prayer, telling Jehovah all about our anxieties and concerns; (2) paying careful attention to Jehovah’s Word and any direction we receive through his organization; and (3) faithfully and patiently waiting on Jehovah. That is what Habakkuk did. Though he began his book with grief, he ended with a confident and joyful exclamation. May we follow this inspiring example so that we too can feel Jehovah’s fatherly embrace! What greater comfort could we find in this darkening world? w18.11 17 ¶18-19

^ (Hab. 3:18) Yet, as for me, I will exult in Jehovah; I will be joyful in the God of my salvation.

^ (Hab. 2:4) Look at the one who is proud;* He is not upright within himself. But the righteous one will live by his faithfulness.*

Or “Look! His soul is swelled up.”

Or possibly, “faith; belief.”

Wednesday, February 12

[Christ] died for all so that those who live should live no longer for themselves, but for him who died for them and was raised up.—[2 Cor. 5:15].

True Christians also have this reason to be drawn to God’s love: He “loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.” ([John 3:16]) What love Jesus also showed in giving his life for us! And what a powerful motivation that love is for us! God’s Word promises that not even “tribulation or distress” can “separate us from the love of the Christ.” ([Rom. 8:35,][38, 39]) When we grapple with trials that are physically, emotionally, or spiritually draining, the compelling force of Christ’s love can give us the strength to endure. ([2 Cor. 5:14]) Jesus’ love has the power to sustain us and to motivate us not to give up, even in the face of such trials as disasters, persecution, personal disappointments, or gnawing anxiety. w18.09 14 ¶8-9

^ (2 Cor. 5:15) And he died for all so that those who live should live no longer for themselves, but for him who died for them and was raised up.

^ (John 3:16) “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.

^ (Rom. 8:35) Who will separate us from the love of the Christ? Will tribulation or distress or persecution or hunger or nakedness or danger or sword?

^ (Rom. 8:38, 39) For I am convinced that neither death nor life nor angels nor governments nor things now here nor things to come nor powers 39 nor height nor depth nor any other creation will be able to separate us from God’s love that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

^ (2 Cor. 5:14) For the love the Christ has compels us, because this is what we have concluded, that one man died for all; so, then, all had died.

Thursday, February 13

I will walk in your truth.—[Ps. 86:11].

To walk in the truth, we must accept and obey all of Jehovah’s sayings. We must give the truth priority in our lives and live according to Bible principles. Like David, we must be firmly resolved to keep walking in God’s truth. If we are not, we could have second thoughts about what we paid for the truth and perhaps be tempted to begin taking back part of the payment. Rather, we carefully hold on to the complete truth. We recognize that we cannot pick which truths to accept and which to ignore. After all, we must walk in “all the truth.” ([John 16:13]) To avoid drifting away from the truth, we must make wise use of our time. If we are not careful, we might start to spend excessive amounts of time on recreation, hobbies, browsing the Internet, or watching television. Although these things are not wrong in themselves, the time we spend on them can begin to encroach on time previously spent in personal study and other spiritual activities. w18.11 10 ¶7-8

^ (Ps. 86:11) Instruct me, O Jehovah, about your way. I will walk in your truth. Unify my heart* to fear your name.

Or “Give me an undivided heart.”

^ (John 16:13) However, when that one comes, the spirit of the truth, he will guide you into all the truth, for he will not speak of his own initiative, but what he hears he will speak, and he will declare to you the things to come.

Friday, February 14

I have calmed and quieted my soul.—[Ps. 131:2].

When our life takes an unexpected turn, the changes that we have to face may cause us apprehension and emotional stress. ([Prov. 12:25]) We may even find it hard to accept those changes. In such circumstances, how can we ‘calm and quiet’ our soul? ([Ps. 131:1-3]) Despite adverse circumstances, we today can experience firsthand the soothing effect of “the peace of God” that guards our mental powers. ([Phil. 4:6, 7]) Thus, if we turn to Jehovah when we feel overwhelmed by anxiety, God’s peace can strengthen our determination to reach spiritual goals and guard us against any tendency to give up. In addition to calming us down, God’s spirit can draw our attention to key scriptures that will help us to keep our spiritual priorities.—John 14:26, 27. w18.10 27 ¶2; 28 ¶5, 8

^ (Ps. 131:2) No, but I have calmed and quieted my soul* Like a weaned child with its mother; I am* contented like a weaned child.

Or “myself.” See Glossary.

Or “My soul is.”

^ (Prov. 12:25) Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down,* But a good word cheers it up.

Or “depresses him.”

^ (Ps. 131:1-3) O Jehovah, my heart is not haughty, Nor are my eyes lofty; Nor do I aspire to things too great, Or to things that are beyond me.  2 No, but I have calmed and quieted my soul* Like a weaned child with its mother; I am* contented like a weaned child.  3 Let Israel wait for Jehovah From now on and forever.

Or “myself.” See Glossary.

Or “My soul is.”

^ (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

^ (John 14:26, 27) But the helper, the holy spirit, which the Father will send in my name, that one will teach you all things and bring back to your minds all the things I told you. 27 I leave you peace; I give you my peace. I do not give it to you the way that the world gives it. Do not let your hearts be troubled nor let them shrink out of fear.

Saturday, February 15

Speak the truth with one another.—[Zech. 8:16].

What device has had the worst possible effect on humankind? The lie! That is, saying something that one knows is not true in order to deceive someone else. And who devised the first lie? Jesus Christ identified “the Devil” as “the father of the lie.” ([John 8:44]) When did he utter the first lie? It happened thousands of years ago in the garden of Eden. The first human couple, Adam and Eve, were enjoying life in the Paradise that their Creator had provided for them. Then, the Devil entered the scene. He knew that God had commanded the couple not to eat from “the tree of the knowledge of good and bad,” lest they die for their disobedience. Even so, through a serpent, Satan told Eve: “You certainly will not die [the first lie ever told]. For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.”—Gen. 2:15-17;[3:1-5]. w18.10 6 ¶1-2

^ (Zech. 8:16) “‘These are the things you should do: Speak the truth with one another, and the judgments in your gates must promote truth and peace.

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

^ (Gen. 2:15-17) Jehovah God took the man and settled him in the garden of Eʹden to cultivate it and to take care of it. 16 Jehovah God also gave this command to the man: “From every tree of the garden you may eat to satisfaction. 17 But as for the tree of the knowledge of good and bad, you must not eat from it, for in the day you eat from it you will certainly die.”

^ (Gen. 3:1-5) Now the serpent was the most cautious* of all the wild animals of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it said to the woman: “Did God really say that you must not eat from every tree of the garden?” 2 At this the woman said to the serpent: “We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden. 3 But God has said about the fruit of the tree that is in the middle of the garden: ‘You must not eat from it, no, you must not touch it; otherwise you will die.’” 4 At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die. 5 For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.”

Or “shrewdest; craftiest.”

Monday, February 17

Wisdom is the most important thing, so acquire wisdom.—[Prov. 4:7].

Doing what we know to be right brings rich blessings. Although wisdom is based on knowledge, it particularly has to do with the decisions we make rather than just the facts we understand. Even ants reveal wisdom. Ants demonstrate instinctive wisdom by preparing their food in the summer. (Prov. 30:24, 25) Christ, “the wisdom of God,” always does the things pleasing to the Father. ([1 Cor. 1:24;][John 8:29]) God knows the difference between making the right choice and acting on that choice. And he rewards those who demonstrate humility with endurance and who practice what they know to be true. (Matt. 7:21-23) Therefore, work to preserve the spiritual environment in which genuine humility can flourish. Applying what we know to be true takes time and requires patience, but it is a mark of humility that leads to happiness now and forever. w18.09 7 ¶18

^ (Prov. 4:7) Wisdom is the most important* thing, so acquire wisdom, And with all you acquire, acquire understanding.

Or “the prime.”

^ (Prov. 30:24, 25) Four things on earth are among the smallest, But they are instinctively wise:* 25 The ants are not strong creatures,* Yet they prepare their food in the summer.

Or “exceedingly wise.”

Lit., “a people not strong.”

^ (1 Cor. 1:24) However, to those who are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ is the power of God and the wisdom of God.

^ (John 8:29) And the One who sent me is with me; he did not abandon me to myself, because I always do the things pleasing to him.”

^ (Matt. 7:21-23) “Not everyone saying to me, ‘Lord, Lord,’ will enter into the Kingdom of the heavens, but only the one doing the will of my Father who is in the heavens will. 22 Many will say to me in that day: ‘Lord, Lord, did we not prophesy in your name, and expel demons in your name, and perform many powerful works* in your name?’ 23 And then I will declare to them: ‘I never knew* you! Get away from me, you workers of lawlessness!’

Or “many miracles.”

Or “recognized.”

Tuesday, February 18

Let each one examine his own actions, . . . and not in comparison with the other person.—[Gal. 6:4].

The Creator envisioned that perfect humans would cooperate with him to accomplish his purposes. Despite mankind’s current imperfect state, faithful people can still work with Jehovah each day. For example, we become “God’s fellow workers” by preaching the good news of his Kingdom and making disciples. ([1 Cor. 3:5-9]) Just think what a privilege we have to be counted worthy of cooperating with the almighty Creator of the universe in a work that he considers important! Yet, preaching and making disciples are not the only ways that we work with Jehovah. Other ways we can do so are by assisting our family and fellow worshippers, by being hospitable, by volunteering for theocratic projects, and by expanding our sacred service. ([Col. 3:23]) However, do not compare what you can do for Jehovah with what others can do. Remember that age, health, circumstances, and abilities vary from one person to another. w18.08 23 ¶1-2

^ (Gal. 6:4) But let each one examine his own actions, and then he will have cause for rejoicing in regard to himself alone, and not in comparison with the other person.

^ (1 Cor. 3:5-9) What, then, is A·polʹlos? Yes, what is Paul? Ministers through whom you became believers, just as the Lord granted each one. 6 I planted, A·polʹlos watered, but God kept making it grow, 7 so that neither is the one who plants anything nor is the one who waters, but God who makes it grow. 8 Now the one who plants and the one who waters are one,* but each person will receive his own reward according to his own work. 9 For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

Or “have one purpose.”

^ (Col. 3:23) Whatever you are doing, work at it whole-souled* as for Jehovah,* and not for men,

See Glossary, “Soul.”

See App. A5.

Wednesday, February 19

Keep in expectation of it! For it will without fail come true.—[Hab. 2:3].

Jehovah assured Habakkuk that he would receive answers to his sincere questions. Relief for all his worries would come before too long. God, in effect, told the prophet: “Be patient, trust in me. My answer will come despite the apparent delay!” Jehovah reminded him that He had an appointed time for fulfilling His promises. He counseled Habakkuk to wait for the accomplishment of His purposes. Ultimately, the prophet would not be disappointed. Patiently waiting on Jehovah and paying close attention to what he tells us will give us confidence and will help us to acquire a calm heart despite adversities and hardships. Jesus confirmed that we can trust in Jehovah as the Great Timekeeper, not focusing on “times or seasons” that God has not yet revealed. ([Acts 1:7]) Therefore, may we not give up but wait in humility, faith, and patience, making good use of the time we have to serve Jehovah to the best of our abilities.—Mark 13:35-37;[Gal. 6:9]. w18.11 16 ¶13-14

^ (Hab. 2:3) For the vision is yet for its appointed time, And it is rushing toward its end,* and it will not lie. Even if it should delay,* keep in expectation of it!* For it will without fail come true. It will not be late!

Or “fulfillment.”

Or “if it seems to delay.”

Or “wait eagerly for it!”

^ (Acts 1:7) He said to them: “It does not belong to you to know the times or seasons that the Father has placed in his own jurisdiction.

^ (Mark 13:35-37) Keep on the watch, therefore, for you do not know when the master of the house is coming, whether late in the day or at midnight or before dawn or early in the morning, 36 in order that when he comes suddenly, he does not find you sleeping. 37 But what I say to you, I say to all: Keep on the watch.”

^ (Gal. 6:9) So let us not give up in doing what is fine, for in due time we will reap if we do not tire out.*

Or “give up.”

Thursday, February 20

God has shown me that I should call no man defiled or unclean.—[Acts 10:28].

Like other Jews of his time, Peter grew up believing that Gentiles were unclean. Yet, Peter had experienced events that caused him to reevaluate that position. For example, Peter had a miraculous vision. ([Acts 10:9-16]) Like Peter, we must examine ourselves carefully and be willing to receive help so that we can identify any remaining traces of prejudice in our hearts. What else can we do? If we open our heart wide, we will allow love to replace prejudice. (2 Cor. 6:11-13) Are you in the habit of having close association only with those of your own race, ethnicity, nationality, tribe, or language group? If so, widen out. Why not invite those of a different background to work with you in the field ministry or invite them to your home for a meal or a gathering? (Acts 16:14, 15) If you do so, you will fill your heart with so much love that there will be no room for prejudice. w18.08 9 ¶3, 6; 10 ¶7

^ (Acts 10:28) He said to them: “You well know how unlawful it is for a Jew to associate with or approach a man of another race, and yet God has shown me that I should call no man defiled or unclean.

^ (Acts 10:9-16) The next day as they were continuing on their journey and were approaching the city, Peter went up to the housetop about the sixth hour to pray. 10 But he became very hungry and wanted to eat. While they were preparing the meal, he fell into a trance 11 and saw heaven opened and something* descending like a great linen sheet being let down by its four corners on the earth; 12 and in it were all sorts of four-footed animals and reptiles* of the earth and birds of heaven. 13 Then a voice said to him: “Get up, Peter, slaughter* and eat!” 14 But Peter said: “Not at all, Lord, because I have never eaten anything defiled and unclean.” 15 And the voice spoke again to him, the second time: “Stop calling defiled the things God has cleansed.” 16 This happened a third time, and immediately it* was taken up into heaven.

Lit., “some sort of object (vessel).”

Or “creeping things.”

Or “sacrifice.”

Lit., “the object (vessel).”

^ (2 Cor. 6:11-13) We have opened our mouth to speak* to you, Corinthians, and we have opened wide our heart. 12 We are not restricted in* our affections for you, but you are restricted in your own tender affections for us. 13 So in response—I speak as to my children—you too open your hearts wide.*

Or “have spoken openly.”

Or “cramped for room in.”

Or “you too widen out.”

^ (Acts 16:14, 15) And a woman named Lydʹi·a, a seller of purple from the city of Thy·a·tiʹra and a worshipper of God, was listening, and Jehovah opened her heart wide to pay attention to the things Paul was saying. 15 Now when she and her household got baptized, she urged us: “If you have considered me to be faithful to Jehovah, come and stay at my house.” And she just made us come.

Friday, February 21

Keep from becoming causes for stumbling.—[1 Cor. 10:32].

Some Witnesses have not firmly rejected worldly conduct. Their dancing and actions at parties go beyond what is acceptable for Christians. They post on social media photos of themselves and comments that are unbecoming to spiritual people. Therefore, they can be a negative influence on their peers who are striving to maintain fine conduct among Jehovah’s people. (1 Pet. 2:11, 12) The world aggressively promotes “the desire of the flesh and the desire of the eyes and the showy display of one’s means of life.” ([1 John 2:16]) Yet, because we belong to Jehovah, we are admonished to “reject ungodliness and worldly desires and to live with soundness of mind and righteousness and godly devotion amid this present system of things.” ([Titus 2:12]) Our speech, our eating and drinking habits, our dress and grooming, our work ethic—everything we do—should tell onlookers that we are exclusively devoted to Jehovah. w18.07 25 ¶13-14

^ (1 Cor. 10:32) Keep from becoming causes for stumbling to Jews as well as Greeks and to the congregation of God,

^ (1 Pet. 2:11, 12) Beloved, I urge you as foreigners and temporary residents to keep abstaining from fleshly desires, which wage war against you.* 12 Maintain your conduct fine among the nations, so that when they accuse you of being wrongdoers, they may be eyewitnesses of your fine works and, as a result, glorify God in the day of his inspection.

Or “the soul.”

^ (1 John 2:16) because everything in the world—the desire of the flesh and the desire of the eyes and the showy display of one’s means of life*—does not originate with the Father, but originates with the world.

Or “the bragging about one’s possessions.”

^ (Titus 2:12) It trains us to reject ungodliness and worldly desires and to live with soundness of mind and righteousness and godly devotion amid this present system of things,*

Or “this present age.” See Glossary.

Saturday, February 22

Our eyes look to Jehovah our God until he shows us favor.—[Ps. 123:2].

If we keep our figurative eyes focused on Jehovah, we will not allow the actions of others to embitter us or damage our relationship with him. This is especially important if, like Moses, we have a measure of responsibility in God’s organization. While it is true that each of us needs to ‘keep working out his own salvation with fear and trembling,’ we must remember that Jehovah does not have one rigid, inflexible standard by which he judges us. ([Phil. 2:12]) Rather, the more responsibility we have, the greater our accountability. ([Luke 12:48]) But if we truly love Jehovah, nothing will stumble us or separate us from his love. ([Ps. 119:165;] Rom. 8:37-39) In these challenging times, may our eyes be raised continually to the One who is “enthroned in the heavens,” so that we can perceive his will. ([Ps. 123:1]) May we never allow our relationship with Jehovah to be negatively affected by the actions of others. w18.07 16 ¶19-20

^ (Ps. 123:2) As the eyes of servants look to the hand of their master, And the eyes of a servant girl to the hand of her mistress, So our eyes look to Jehovah our God Until he shows us favor.

^ (Phil. 2:12) Consequently, my beloved ones, just as you have always obeyed, not only during my presence but now much more readily during my absence, keep working out your own salvation with fear and trembling.

^ (Luke 12:48) But the one who did not understand and yet did things deserving of strokes will be beaten with few. Indeed, everyone to whom much was given, much will be demanded of him, and the one who was put in charge of much will have more than usual demanded of him.

^ (Ps. 119:165) Abundant peace belongs to those who love your law; Nothing can make them stumble.*

Or “For them there is no stumbling block.”

^ (Rom. 8:37-39) On the contrary, in all these things we are coming off completely victorious through the one who loved us. 38 For I am convinced that neither death nor life nor angels nor governments nor things now here nor things to come nor powers 39 nor height nor depth nor any other creation will be able to separate us from God’s love that is in Christ Jesus our Lord.

^ (Ps. 123:1) To you I raise my eyes, You who are enthroned in the heavens.

Sunday, February 23

Let your light shine before men, so that they may . . . give glory to your Father.—[Matt. 5:16].

How thrilling it is to hear of increases that Jehovah’s people are experiencing! In 2017 we regularly conducted over 10,000,000 Bible studies. This certainly indicates that God’s servants are letting their light shine! And think of the millions of interested ones whom we welcomed at the Memorial. They could thus learn of the love that God expressed when he provided the ransom. ([1 John 4:9]) Worldwide, Jehovah’s people speak many different languages. However, this does not prevent us from offering united praise to our Father, Jehovah. ([Rev. 7:9]) No matter what our mother tongue is or where we live, we can shine “as illuminators in the world.” ([Phil. 2:15]) The increase we observe, the unity we enjoy, and the watchful attitude that we strive to maintain all contribute to our bringing glory to Jehovah. w18.06 21 ¶1-3

^ (Matt. 5:16) Likewise, let your light shine before men, so that they may see your fine works and give glory to your Father who is in the heavens.

^ (1 John 4:9) By this the love of God was revealed in our case, that God sent his only-begotten Son into the world so that we might gain life through him.

^ (Rev. 7:9) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands.

Or “languages.”

^ (Phil. 2:15) so that you may come to be blameless and innocent, children of God without a blemish in the midst of a crooked and twisted generation, among whom you are shining as illuminators in the world,

Monday, February 24

Rabbi, eat.—[John 4:31].

Jesus’ reply indicated that he was so absorbed in the spiritual discussion that his hunger could be ignored. Preaching—even to a Samaritan woman—was the will of his Father, and it was like food for him. ([John 4:32-34]) James and John did not grasp this lesson. When journeying with Jesus through Samaria, the disciples sought overnight lodging in a Samaritan village. The Samaritans refused to receive them, so James and John angrily suggested calling down fire from heaven to destroy the entire village. Jesus firmly rebuked them. ([Luke 9:51-56]) We may wonder if James and John would have reacted the same way if the inhospitable village had been in their home region of Galilee. It seems likely that prejudice had kindled their animosity. It could be that the apostle John felt embarrassed about his rash outburst when he later enjoyed a successful preaching campaign among the Samaritans.—[Acts 8:14,][25]. w18.06 10-11 ¶12-13

^ (John 4:31) Meanwhile, the disciples were urging him: “Rabbi, eat.”

^ (John 4:32-34) But he said to them: “I have food to eat that you do not know about.” 33 So the disciples said to one another: “No one brought him anything to eat, did he?” 34 Jesus said to them: “My food is to do the will of him who sent me and to finish his work.

^ (Luke 9:51-56) As the days were drawing near* for him to be taken up, he resolutely set his face to go to Jerusalem. 52 So he sent messengers ahead of him. And they went and entered a village of Sa·marʹi·tans to make preparations for him. 53 But they did not receive him, because he was determined to go to Jerusalem. 54 When the disciples James and John saw this, they said: “Lord,* do you want us to call fire down from heaven and annihilate them?” 55 But he turned and rebuked them. 56 So they went to a different village.

Lit., “were coming to the full; were being fulfilled.”

Or “Master.”

^ (Acts 8:14) When the apostles in Jerusalem heard that Sa·marʹi·a had accepted the word of God, they sent Peter and John to them;

^ (Acts 8:25) Therefore, when they had given the witness thoroughly and had spoken the word of Jehovah, they started back toward Jerusalem, and they went declaring the good news to many villages of the Sa·marʹi·tans.

Tuesday, February 25

Stand firm . . . with the belt of truth fastened around your waist.—[Eph. 6:14].

When Bible truth is wrapped around us tightly, as it were, we will be moved to live in harmony with it and to speak the truth at all times. Why will we avoid telling lies? Because lies have been one of Satan’s most effective weapons. Lies damage both the one telling them and the one believing them. ([John 8:44]) So to the best of our imperfect ability, we avoid telling lies. ([Eph. 4:25]) But it can be a challenge. Eighteen-year-old Abigail says: “Speaking the truth may not always seem worth it, especially when telling a lie can get you out of a difficult situation.” Why, then, tell the truth? Victoria, 23, says: “When you tell the truth and stand up for your beliefs, you might get bullied. But you always get outstanding benefits: You gain confidence, you feel closer to Jehovah, and you earn the respect of those who love you.” Certainly, it is worth keeping “the belt of truth fastened around your waist” at all times. w18.05 28 ¶3, 5

^ (Eph. 6:14) Stand firm, therefore, with the belt of truth fastened around your waist, wearing the breastplate of righteousness,

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

^ (Eph. 4:25) Therefore, now that you have put away deceit, each one of you speak truth with his neighbor, because we are members belonging to one another.

Wednesday, February 26

Keep on the watch.—[Matt. 24:42].

As these critical times worsen, all of us need to keep on the watch. When Jehovah acts, it will be at the right time. (Matt. 24:42-44) Meanwhile, exercise patience, being ever watchful. Read God’s Word each day, and be vigilant with a view to prayers. ([1 Pet. 4:7]) Take note of sterling examples of brothers and sisters whose lives reflect their joy in keeping on the watch as well as letting their light shine. Fill your life with upbuilding activity and association. That will bring you great joy, and it will seem to you that time is passing quickly. ([Eph. 5:16]) It is faith-strengthening to know that our imperfection does not stop us from serving Jehovah acceptably. Consequently, appreciate Jehovah’s provision of “gifts in men,” congregation elders. ([Eph. 4:8,][11, 12]) The next time an elder visits you, take advantage of the opportunity to draw on his wisdom and benefit from his advice. w18.06 24-25 ¶15-18

^ (Matt. 24:42) Keep on the watch, therefore, because you do not know on what day your Lord is coming.

^ (Matt. 24:42-44) Keep on the watch, therefore, because you do not know on what day your Lord is coming. 43 “But know one thing: If the householder had known in what watch* the thief was coming, he would have kept awake and not allowed his house to be broken into. 44 On this account, you too prove yourselves ready, because the Son of man is coming at an hour that you do not think to be it.

Or “at what time of night.”

^ (1 Pet. 4:7) But the end of all things has drawn close. Therefore, be sound in mind, and be vigilant* with a view to prayers.

Or “alert; awake.”

^ (Eph. 5:16) making the best use of your time,* because the days are wicked.

Lit., “buying out the appointed time.”

^ (Eph. 4:8) For it says: “When he ascended on high he carried away captives; he gave gifts in men.”

^ (Eph. 4:11, 12) And he gave some as apostles, some as prophets, some as evangelizers,* some as shepherds and teachers, 12 with a view to the readjustment* of the holy ones, for ministerial work, to build up the body of the Christ,

Or “proclaimers of the good news.”

Or “training.”

Thursday, February 27

If you observe my commandments, you will remain in my love.—[John 15:10].

Jesus told his disciples not only to be in his love but to “remain in [his] love.” Why? Because living as a true disciple of Christ year after year calls for endurance. Jesus stressed the need for endurance by using forms of the word “remain” over and over in the brief passage recorded at [John 15:4-10]. How do we show that we want to remain in Christ’s love and keep his approval? By observing Jesus’ commandments. Simply put, Jesus tells us, ‘Be obedient to me.’ Yet, Jesus only asked us to do what he himself did, for he added: “Just as I have observed the commandments of the Father and remain in his love.” Jesus sets the example. ([John 13:15]) By carrying out Jesus’ command to go and preach, we too show our love for God because Jesus’ commandments reflect his Father’s thinking. ([Matt. 17:5;][John 8:28]) In response to our expression of love, Jehovah and Jesus keep us in their love. w18.05 18 ¶5-7

^ (John 15:10) If you observe my commandments, you will remain in my love, just as I have observed the commandments of the Father and remain in his love.

^ (John 15:4-10) Remain in union with me, and I will remain in union with you. Just as the branch cannot bear fruit by itself unless it remains in the vine, neither can you unless you remain in union with me. 5 I am the vine; you are the branches. Whoever remains in union with me and I in union with him, this one bears much fruit; for apart from me you can do* nothing at all. 6 If anyone does not remain in union with me, he is thrown out like a branch and dries up. And men gather those branches and throw them into the fire, and they are burned. 7 If you remain in union with me and my sayings remain in you, ask whatever you wish and it will take place for you. 8 My Father is glorified in this, that you keep bearing much fruit and prove yourselves my disciples. 9 Just as the Father has loved me, so I have loved you; remain in my love. 10 If you observe my commandments, you will remain in my love, just as I have observed the commandments of the Father and remain in his love.

Or “produce.”

^ (John 13:15) For I set the pattern for you, that just as I did to you, you should also do.

^ (Matt. 17:5) While he was still speaking, look! a bright cloud overshadowed them, and look! a voice out of the cloud said: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved. Listen to him.”

^ (John 8:28) Jesus then said: “After you have lifted up the Son of man, then you will know that I am he and that I do nothing of my own initiative; but just as the Father taught me, I speak these things.

Friday, February 28

The plans of the diligent surely lead to success.—[Prov. 21:5].

Adolescents have to make decisions about education, employment, and other matters. If you know what your goals are, making good decisions becomes easier. The earlier you make plans by setting good goals, the sooner you will have success. Thousands of young ones in congregations all over the world deserve warm praise. They commit themselves to Jehovah and focus their lives on theocratic goals. Such young people enjoy life to the full while at the same time learning to follow Jehovah’s guidance in all endeavors. This also includes family life. “Trust in Jehovah with all your heart,” wrote Solomon. “In all your ways take notice of him, and he will make your paths straight.” ([Prov. 3:5, 6]) Youths in the Christian congregation are precious in the eyes of Jehovah, who loves them dearly and gives them his protection, guidance, and blessing. w18.04 26 ¶7; 27 ¶9

^ (Prov. 21:5) The plans of the diligent surely lead to success,* But all who are hasty surely head for poverty.

Or “advantage.”

^ (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

Saturday, February 29

Love one another; just as I have loved you, you also love one another.—[John 13:34].

The apostle John was a pillar in the early Christian congregation. His riveting Gospel account of Jesus’ ministry has been a source of encouragement to Christians throughout the centuries—and still is. His Gospel alone preserves Jesus’ statement that love is the identifying mark of his true disciples. ([John 13:35]) John’s three letters contain further gems of truth. When we are weighed down with the burden of sin, are we not relieved to read that “the blood of Jesus . . . cleanses us from all sin”? ([1 John 1:7]) And if our heart continues to condemn us, do we not get a lump in our throat and tears of gratitude in our eyes when we read that “God is greater than our hearts”? ([1 John 3:20]) John alone wrote that “God is love.” ([1 John 4:8,][16]) His second and third letters commend Christians who continue “walking in the truth.”—[2 John 4;][3 John 3, 4]. w18.04 18 ¶14-15

^ (John 13:34) I am giving you a new commandment, that you love one another; just as I have loved you, you also love one another.

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (1 John 1:7) However, if we are walking in the light as he himself is in the light, we do have fellowship with one another, and the blood of Jesus his Son cleanses us from all sin.

^ (1 John 3:20) regarding whatever our hearts may condemn us in, because God is greater than our hearts and knows all things.

^ (1 John 4:8) Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.

^ (1 John 4:16) And we have come to know and believe the love that God has for us. God is love, and the one who remains in love remains in union with God and God remains in union with him.

^ (2 John 4) I rejoice very much because I have found some of your children walking in the truth, just as we received commandment from the Father.

^ (3 John 3, 4) For I rejoiced very much when brothers came and bore witness about the truth you hold, as you go on walking in the truth. 4 No greater joy* do I have than this: that I should hear that my children go on walking in the truth.

Or possibly, “cause for thankfulness.”

March

Sunday, March 1

You rule over everything.—1 Chron. 29:12.

When reading the first two chapters of Genesis, we can easily see that Adam and Eve enjoyed the kind of freedom that people today can only hope for—freedom from want, from fear, and from oppression. The first couple’s life was completely free from worries about food, work, sickness, and death. (Gen. 1:27-29;[2:8, 9,][15]) When it comes to freedom, though, a key point for us to bear in mind is that Jehovah God alone has what can be called absolute and unlimited freedom. Why? Because he is the Creator of all things and the almighty Sovereign of the universe. ([1 Tim. 1:17;][Rev. 4:11]) Accordingly, all creatures in heaven and on earth have freedom in only a relative sense. They must recognize that Jehovah God has the ultimate authority to impose what he determines to be just, necessary, and reasonable limits. That, in fact, was what Jehovah God did with his human creation right from the beginning. w18.04 4 ¶4, 6

^ (1 Chron. 29:12) The riches and the glory are from you, and you rule over everything, and in your hand there are power and mightiness, and your hand is able to make great and to give strength to all.

^ (Gen. 1:27-29) And God went on to create the man in his image, in God’s image he created him; male and female he created them. 28 Further, God blessed them, and God said to them: “Be fruitful and become many, fill the earth and subdue it, and have in subjection the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and every living creature that is moving on the earth.” 29 Then God said: “Here I have given to you every seed-bearing plant that is on the entire earth and every tree with seed-bearing fruit. Let them serve as food for you.

^ (Gen. 2:8, 9) Further, Jehovah God planted a garden in Eʹden, toward the east; and there he put the man whom he had formed. 9 Thus Jehovah God made to grow out of the ground every tree that was pleasing to look at and good for food and also the tree of life in the middle of the garden and the tree of the knowledge of good and bad.

^ (Gen. 2:15) Jehovah God took the man and settled him in the garden of Eʹden to cultivate it and to take care of it.

^ (1 Tim. 1:17) Now to the King of eternity, incorruptible, invisible, the only God, be honor and glory forever and ever. Amen.

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

Monday, March 2

How beautiful . . . are the feet of the one bringing good news.—[Isa. 52:7].

In this present system, we endure only with Jehovah’s help. (2 Cor. 4:7, 8) But think of those who struggle to survive in this world without a close friendship with Jehovah. Like Jesus, we feel pity for them, and we are moved to bring them “good news of something better.” So be patient with those whom you teach. Remember, they may never have considered some of the Bible truths we know very well. And many have a strong emotional connection to their current beliefs. They may see their religious views as uniting them with their family, their culture, and their community. Before we ask people to give up their cherished “old” beliefs, we may first need to help them build a strong appreciation for “new” truths—Bible teachings that at the outset are unfamiliar to them. Only then will they be ready to abandon their former viewpoint. It may take time to help people make such changes.—[Rom. 12:2]. w19.03 23 ¶10, 12; 24 ¶13

^ (Isa. 52:7) How beautiful on the mountains are the feet of the one bringing good news, The one proclaiming peace, The one bringing good news of something better, The one proclaiming salvation, The one saying to Zion: “Your God has become King!”

^ (2 Cor. 4:7, 8) However, we have this treasure in earthen vessels,* so that the power beyond what is normal may be God’s and not from us. 8 We are hard-pressed in every way, but not cramped beyond movement; we are perplexed, but not absolutely with no way out;*

Or “in jars of clay.”

Or possibly, “not left in despair.”

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

Tuesday, March 3

I have approved you.—[Mark 1:11].

Jehovah’s example in expressing love and approval reminds us to look for opportunities to encourage others. ([John 5:20]) We blossom when someone we care about shows love to us and commends us for the good we do. Likewise, our brothers and sisters in the congregation and our family members need our love and encouragement. When we commend others, we strengthen their faith and help them to serve Jehovah loyally. Parents especially need to encourage their children. When parents commend their children sincerely and show them affection, they help their children to flourish. The words: “I have approved you” show that Jehovah was confident that Jesus would faithfully carry out his Father’s will. Jehovah has such confidence in his Son, so we can likewise be completely confident that Jesus will faithfully carry out all of Jehovah’s promises. ([2 Cor. 1:20]) When we consider Jesus’ example, we are even more determined to learn from him and to follow in his footsteps.—[1 Pet. 2:21]. w19.03 8 ¶3; 9 ¶5-6

^ (Mark 1:11) And a voice came out of the heavens: “You are my Son, the beloved; I have approved you.”

^ (John 5:20) For the Father has affection for the Son and shows him all the things he himself does, and he will show him works greater than these, so that you may marvel.

^ (2 Cor. 1:20) For no matter how many the promises of God are, they have become “yes” by means of him. Therefore, also through him is the “Amen” said to God, which brings him glory through us.

^ (1 Pet. 2:21) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

Wednesday, March 4

The law of the spirit that gives life in union with Christ Jesus has set you free from the law of sin and of death.—[Rom. 8:2].

When we realize the true value of a costly gift, we are moved to show our gratitude to the giver. The Israelites did not appreciate the freedom that Jehovah bestowed upon them when he delivered them from slavery in Egypt. Within a few months of their deliverance, they began to long for the food and drink they once had in Egypt and complained about Jehovah’s provisions, even wanting to return to Egypt. Just imagine, they put ‘fish, cucumbers, watermelons, leeks, onions, and garlic’ above their God-given freedom to worship the true God, Jehovah. Is it any wonder that Jehovah became very angry with his people? (Num. 11:5, 6,[10;][14:3, 4]) What a lesson for us! The apostle Paul urged all Christians not to take for granted the freedom that Jehovah has kindly given us through his Son, Jesus Christ.—[2 Cor. 6:1]. w18.04 9-10 ¶6-7

^ (Rom. 8:2) For the law of the spirit that gives life in union with Christ Jesus has set you free from the law of sin and of death.

^ (Num. 11:5, 6) How fondly we remember the fish that we used to eat without cost in Egypt, also the cucumbers, the watermelons, the leeks, the onions, and the garlic! 6 But now we* are withering away. We see nothing at all except this manna.”

Or “our souls.”

^ (Num. 11:10) Moses heard the people weeping, family after family, each man at the entrance of his tent. And Jehovah became very angry, and Moses was also very displeased.

^ (Num. 14:3, 4) Why is Jehovah bringing us to this land to fall by the sword? Our wives and children will become plunder. Is it not better for us to return to Egypt?” 4 They were even saying to one another: “Let us appoint a leader and return to Egypt!”

^ (2 Cor. 6:1) Working together with him, we also urge you not to accept the undeserved kindness of God and miss its purpose.

Thursday, March 5

He loves righteousness and justice. The earth is filled with Jehovah’s loyal love.—[Ps. 33:5].

All of us want to be loved. And all of us want to be treated fairly. If we are repeatedly denied love and justice, we may feel worthless and hopeless. Jehovah knows that we long for love and yearn for justice. ([Ps. 33:5]) We can be sure that our God loves us dearly and wants us to be treated fairly. This becomes evident when we look closely at the Law that Jehovah gave to the nation of Israel through Moses. As we study the Mosaic Law, we discover the warm feelings of our loving God, Jehovah. ([Rom. 13:8-10]) We can note that the Mosaic Law was built on love because love motivates all that Jehovah does. ([1 John 4:8]) Jehovah founded that entire code of laws on two basic commands—love God, and love your neighbor. ([Lev. 19:18;][Deut. 6:5;] Matt. 22:36-40) Each of the 600 and more commandments that make up the Law reveals a facet of Jehovah’s love. w19.02 20-21 ¶1-4

^ (Ps. 33:5) He loves righteousness and justice. The earth is filled with Jehovah’s loyal love.

^ (Ps. 33:5) He loves righteousness and justice. The earth is filled with Jehovah’s loyal love.

^ (Rom. 13:8-10) Do not owe anything to anyone except to love one another; for whoever loves his fellow man has fulfilled the law. 9 For the law code, “You must not commit adultery, you must not murder, you must not steal, you must not covet,” and whatever other commandment there is, is summed up in this saying: “You must love your neighbor as yourself.” 10 Love does not work evil to one’s neighbor; therefore, love is the law’s fulfillment.

^ (1 John 4:8) Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.

^ (Lev. 19:18) “‘You must not take vengeance nor hold a grudge against the sons of your people, and you must love your fellow man as yourself. I am Jehovah.

^ (Deut. 6:5) You must love Jehovah your God with all your heart and all your soul* and all your strength.*

See Glossary.

Or “vital force; resources.”

^ (Matt. 22:36-40) “Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the Law?” 37 He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind.’ 38 This is the greatest and first commandment. 39 The second, like it, is this: ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’ 40 On these two commandments the whole Law hangs, and the Prophets.”

Friday, March 6

Where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.—[Matt. 6:21].

Job was careful about his behavior with those of the opposite sex. ([Job 31:1]) He knew that it was improper to pay romantic attention to any woman other than his wife. Today, we live in a world that bombards us with sexual temptation. Like Job, will we refuse to pay improper attention to anyone to whom we are not married? Will we also refuse to look at lewd or pornographic images in any form? ([Matt. 5:28]) If we exert such self-control daily, we will strengthen ourselves to keep our integrity. Job also obeyed Jehovah in the way he viewed material things. Job saw that if he put his trust in his possessions, he would commit a grave error deserving of punishment. (Job 31:24, 25,[28]) Today, we live in a very materialistic world. If we develop a balanced view of money and possessions, as the Bible admonishes us to do, we will strengthen our determination to keep our integrity.—Prov. 30:8, 9; Matt. 6:19, 20. w19.02 6 ¶13-14

^ (Matt. 6:21) For where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.

^ (Job 31:1) “I have made a covenant with my eyes. So how could I show improper attention to a virgin?

^ (Matt. 5:28) But I say to you that everyone who keeps on looking at a woman so as to have a passion for her has already committed adultery with her in his heart.

^ (Job 31:24, 25) If I put my confidence in gold Or said to fine gold, ‘You are my security!’ 25 If I found my joy in my great wealth Because of the many possessions I acquired;

^ (Job 31:28) Then that would be an error deserving punishment by the judges, For I would have denied the true God above.

^ (Prov. 30:8, 9) Remove untruth and lies far from me. Give me neither poverty nor riches. Just let me consume my portion of food,  9 So that I do not become satisfied and deny you and say, “Who is Jehovah?” Nor let me become poor and steal and dishonor* the name of my God.

Or “assail.”

^ (Matt. 6:19, 20) “Stop storing up for yourselves treasures on the earth, where moth and rust consume and where thieves break in and steal. 20 Rather, store up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust consumes, and where thieves do not break in and steal.

Saturday, March 7

Just as the Father has loved me, so I have loved you.—[John 15:9].

Jesus perfectly reflected Jehovah’s intense love for us in everything that he did. (1 John 4:8-10) Above all, Jesus was moved from the heart to give his life in our behalf. Whether we are of the anointed or of the “other sheep,” we benefit from the love that Jehovah and his Son have shown to us by means of that sacrifice. ([John 10:16;][1 John 2:2]) Think, too, about the very nature of the Memorial meal; it reveals Jesus’ love and consideration for his disciples. How so? Jesus showed love for his spirit-begotten followers by instituting, not a complicated ritual, but a simple meal for them to observe. As time passed, those anointed disciples needed to observe the Memorial each year, doing so under various circumstances, including imprisonment. ([Rev. 2:10]) Were they able to obey Jesus? Yes, they were! Down to modern times, true Christians have sought to commemorate Jesus’ death. w19.01 24 ¶13-15

^ (John 15:9) Just as the Father has loved me, so I have loved you; remain in my love.

^ (1 John 4:8-10) Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love. 9 By this the love of God was revealed in our case, that God sent his only-begotten Son into the world so that we might gain life through him. 10 The love is in this respect, not that we have loved God, but that he loved us and sent his Son as a propitiatory sacrifice* for our sins.

Or “an atoning sacrifice; a means of appeasement.”

^ (John 10:16) “And I have other sheep, which are not of this fold; those too I must bring in, and they will listen to my voice, and they will become one flock, one shepherd.

^ (1 John 2:2) And he is a propitiatory sacrifice* for our sins, yet not for ours only but also for the whole world’s.

Or “an atoning sacrifice; a means of appeasement.”

^ (Rev. 2:10) Do not be afraid of the things you are about to suffer. Look! The Devil will keep on throwing some of you into prison so that you may be fully put to the test, and you will have tribulation for ten days. Prove yourself faithful even to death, and I will give you the crown of life.

Monday, March 9

A husband should not leave his wife.—[1 Cor. 7:11].

All Christians should strive to show regard for marriage, even as Jesus and Jehovah do. However, some may fail to do so, for humans are imperfect. ([Rom. 7:18-23]) Thus, it should not shock us that some Christians in the first century had troubled marriages. Paul wrote that “a wife should not separate from her husband”; yet, in some cases that did occur. ([1 Cor. 7:10]) Paul did not explain what led to such a separation. The problem was not, for example, that the husband had been immoral, giving the wife a basis for divorce and remarriage. Paul wrote that a wife who was separated from her husband should “remain unmarried or else be reconciled with her husband.” So the two were still united in God’s eyes. Paul advised that whatever the underlying problems, if sexual immorality is not involved, the goal should be reconciliation. The two could seek Bible-based help from congregation elders. w18.12 13 ¶14-15

^ (1 Cor. 7:11) But if she does separate, let her remain unmarried or else be reconciled with her husband; and a husband should not leave his wife.

^ (Rom. 7:18-23) For I know that in me, that is, in my flesh, there dwells nothing good; for I have the desire to do what is fine but not the ability to carry it out. 19 For I do not do the good that I wish, but the bad that I do not wish is what I practice. 20 If, then, I do what I do not wish, I am no longer the one carrying it out, but it is the sin dwelling in me. 21 I find, then, this law in my case: When I wish to do what is right, what is bad is present with me. 22 I really delight in the law of God according to the man I am within, 23 but I see in my body another law warring against the law of my mind and leading me captive to sin’s law that is in my body.

^ (1 Cor. 7:10) To the married people I give instructions, not I but the Lord, that a wife should not separate from her husband.

Tuesday, March 10

Keep on . . . seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness.—[Matt. 6:33].

Today, God’s will for his people is to develop a friendship with him and have as full a share as possible in his work. (Matt. 28:19, 20;[Jas. 4:8]) Well-meaning people might try to sway us from that course. For example, what if your employer offered you a promotion with a substantial increase in salary but the position would interfere with your spiritual activities? Or if you are in school, suppose you were offered an opportunity to move away from home to receive additional education. At that moment, would you need to do prayerful research, consult with others, and then make a decision? Why not learn Jehovah’s thinking on such matters now and endeavor to make his thoughts your own? Then, if you are ever presented with such an offer, you may find that it hardly amounts to a temptation. Your spiritual goals are set, your heart is resolved, and all that remains for you is to carry out a decision that you have already made. w18.11 27 ¶18

^ (Matt. 6:33) “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

Wednesday, March 11

Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart.—[Prov. 4:23].

Solomon became king of Israel when he was just a young man. In the early part of his reign, Jehovah appeared to him in a dream and said: “Ask what you would like me to give you.” Solomon replied: “I am just a youth and I am inexperienced. . . . So grant your servant an obedient heart to judge your people.” ([1 Ki. 3:5-10]) “An obedient heart”—what a modest request that was! No wonder Jehovah loved Solomon! ([2 Sam. 12:24]) Our God was so pleased with the young king’s answer that he gave Solomon “a wise and understanding heart.” ([1 Ki. 3:12]) As long as he was faithful, Solomon enjoyed many blessings. He had the honor of building a temple “for the name of Jehovah the God of Israel.” ([1 Ki. 8:20]) He became famous for his God-given wisdom. And the things he said when he was inspired by God are recorded in three books of the Bible. One of these is the book of Proverbs. w19.01 14 ¶1-2

^ (Prov. 4:23) Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart, For out of it are the sources of life.

^ (1 Ki. 3:5-10) In Gibʹe·on Jehovah appeared to Solʹo·mon in a dream by night, and God said: “Ask what you would like me to give you.” 6 At this Solʹo·mon said: “You have shown great loyal love toward your servant David my father as he walked before you in faithfulness and in righteousness and in uprightness of heart. You have continued to show him this great loyal love down to this day by giving him a son to sit on his throne. 7 And now, Jehovah my God, you have made your servant king in the place of David my father, though I am just a youth* and I am inexperienced.* 8 Your servant is among your people whom you have chosen, a people so vast that they cannot be numbered or counted. 9 So grant your servant an obedient heart to judge your people, to discern between good and bad, for who is able to judge this numerous* people of yours?” 10 It was pleasing to Jehovah that Solʹo·mon had requested this.

Or “little boy.”

Lit., “and I do not know going out and coming in.”

Or possibly, “difficult.” Lit., “heavy.”

^ (2 Sam. 12:24) Then David comforted his wife Bath-sheʹba. He went in to her and lay down with her. In time she bore a son, and he was named Solʹo·mon.* And Jehovah loved him,

From a Hebrew word meaning “Peace.”

^ (1 Ki. 3:12) I will do what you asked. I will give you a wise and understanding heart, so that just as there has never been anyone like you before, there will never be anyone like you again.

^ (1 Ki. 8:20) Jehovah has carried out the promise that he made, for I have succeeded my father David and I sit on the throne of Israel, just as Jehovah promised. I have also built the house for the name of Jehovah the God of Israel

Thursday, March 12

Stop being molded by this system of things.—[Rom. 12:2].

Some people resist the idea of having anyone mold or influence their thoughts. “I think for myself,” they say. They probably mean that they make their own decisions and that it is proper to do so. They do not wish to be controlled, nor do they want to surrender their individuality. We can be assured, however, that bringing our thinking into harmony with Jehovah’s does not mean giving up all individual thought or expression. As stated at 2 Corinthians 3:17, “where the spirit of Jehovah is, there is freedom.” We are free to develop our own distinct personalities. We can have our personal preferences and choose our fields of interest. Indeed, Jehovah designed us to do so. However, we cannot use our freedom without restraint. ([1 Pet. 2:16]) When it comes to issues of right and wrong, Jehovah wants us to be guided by his thinking as revealed in his Word. w18.11 19 ¶5-6

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

^ (2 Cor. 3:17) Now Jehovah* is the Spirit, and where the spirit of Jehovah* is, there is freedom.

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ (1 Pet. 2:16) Be as free people, using your freedom, not as a cover* for doing wrong, but as slaves of God.

Or “an excuse.”

Friday, March 13

Demas has forsaken me because he loved the present system of things.—[2 Tim. 4:10].

When we learned the truth, our interest in material things became secondary to our spiritual pursuits. We were happy to make material sacrifices in order to walk in the truth. Over time, however, we may see others buying the latest electronic devices or enjoying other material advantages. We could begin to feel that we are losing out. No longer content with the necessities, we might put spiritual pursuits aside in favor of accumulating material possessions. Such a course reminds us of Demas. His love for “the present system of things” led him to abandon a life of service with the apostle Paul. Why did Demas leave Paul? Whether he loved material things more than spiritual activities or he was no longer willing to make personal sacrifices in order to serve with Paul, the Bible does not say. We surely do not want to rekindle a desire for material things and let those attractions crowd out our love for the truth. w18.11 10 ¶9

^ (2 Tim. 4:10) For Deʹmas has forsaken me because he loved the present system of things,* and he has gone to Thes·sa·lo·niʹca, Cresʹcens to Ga·laʹti·a, Titus to Dal·maʹtia.

Or “present age.” See Glossary.

Saturday, March 14

You certainly will not die.—[Gen. 3:4].

Satan’s lie was malicious because he knew full well that if Eve believed him and ate the fruit, she would die. Eve and Adam both disobeyed Jehovah’s command and eventually died. ([Gen. 3:6;][5:5]) More than that, through such sin, “death spread to all men.” In fact, “death ruled as king . . . , even over those who had not sinned in the same way that Adam transgressed.” ([Rom. 5:12,][14]) Now, instead of being able to enjoy perfect, endless life as God had originally intended, humans are doing well if they live “70 years, or 80 if one is especially strong.” Even then, life is often “filled with trouble and sorrow.” ([Ps. 90:10]) How tragic—all resulting from Satan’s lie! In explaining the Devil’s actions, Jesus stated: “He did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him.” ([John 8:44]) Truth is still not in Satan, for he continues “misleading the entire inhabited earth” with his lies. ([Rev. 12:9]) We do not want to be misled by the Devil. w18.10 6-7 ¶1-4

^ (Gen. 3:4) At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die.

^ (Gen. 3:6) Consequently, the woman saw that the tree was good for food and that it was something desirable to the eyes, yes, the tree was pleasing to look at. So she began taking of its fruit and eating it. Afterward, she also gave some to her husband when he was with her, and he began eating it.

^ (Gen. 5:5) So all the days of Adam’s life amounted to 930 years, and then he died.

^ (Rom. 5:12) That is why, just as through one man sin entered into the world and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because they had all sinned—.

^ (Rom. 5:14) Nevertheless, death ruled as king from Adam down to Moses, even over those who had not sinned in the same way that Adam transgressed, who bears a resemblance to the one who was to come.

^ (Ps. 90:10) The span of our life is 70 years, Or 80 if one is especially strong.* But they are filled with trouble and sorrow; They quickly pass by, and away we fly.

Or “because of special mightiness.”

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

^ (Rev. 12:9) So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.

Sunday, March 15

Happy are the peacemakers, since they will be called sons of God.—[Matt. 5:9].

Those who take the initiative to make peace have good reason to be happy. The disciple James wrote: “The fruit of righteousness is sown in peaceful conditions for those who are making peace.” ([Jas. 3:18]) When we have a strained relationship with someone either in the congregation or in the family, we can plead for God’s help to be peacemakers. Thus, Jehovah’s holy spirit, righteous conduct, and happiness can predominate. Jesus emphasized the importance of taking the initiative to make peace when he said: “If, then, you are bringing your gift to the altar and there you remember that your brother has something against you, leave your gift there in front of the altar, and go away. First make your peace with your brother, and then come back and offer your gift.”—Matt. 5:23, 24. w18.09 21 ¶17

^ (Matt. 5:9) “Happy are the peacemakers, since they will be called sons of God.

^ (Jas. 3:18) Moreover, the fruit of righteousness is sown in peaceful conditions for* those who are making peace.

Or possibly, “by.”

^ (Matt. 5:23, 24) “If, then, you are bringing your gift to the altar and there you remember that your brother has something against you, 24 leave your gift there in front of the altar, and go away. First make your peace with your brother, and then come back and offer your gift.

Monday, March 16

I am giving you a new commandment, that you love one another; just as I have loved you, you also love one another.—[John 13:34].

On his final night with his disciples, Jesus mentioned love nearly 30 times. He specifically indicated that his disciples should “love one another.” ([John 15:12,][17]) Their love for one another would be so outstanding that it would clearly distinguish them as his true followers. ([John 13:35]) This love is not mere sentimentality. Jesus was referring to a most noble quality—self-sacrificing love. He said: “No one has love greater than this, that someone should surrender his life in behalf of his friends. You are my friends if you do what I am commanding you.” (John 15:13, 14) The genuine, self-sacrificing love and unbreakable unity of Jehovah’s servants today identify them as God’s people. (1 John 3:10, 11) How grateful we are that Christlike love prevails among Jehovah’s servants regardless of their nationality, tribe, language, or background! w18.09 12 ¶1-2

^ (John 13:34) I am giving you a new commandment, that you love one another; just as I have loved you, you also love one another.

^ (John 15:12) This is my commandment, that you love one another just as I have loved you.

^ (John 15:17) “These things I command you, that you love one another.

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (John 15:13, 14) No one has love greater than this, that someone should surrender his life in behalf of his friends. 14 You are my friends if you do what I am commanding you.

^ (1 John 3:10, 11) The children of God and the children of the Devil are evident by this fact: Whoever does not practice righteousness does not originate with God, nor does the one who does not love his brother. 11 For this is the message that you have heard from the beginning, that we should love one another;

Tuesday, March 17

If anyone does not provide for those who are his own, and especially for those who are members of his household, he has disowned the faith.—[1 Tim. 5:8].

Jehovah expects his servants to care for their families. For example, you may have to work to provide financially for your loved ones. Many mothers stay at home to look after their infants. And some adult children may have to care for infirm parents. These are necessary activities. If you have such responsibilities, you likely cannot set aside as much time for theocratic activities as you would like to. But take heart! Jehovah is pleased when you provide for your family. ([1 Cor. 10:31]) If you do not have pressing family responsibilities, could you assist fellow worshippers who are caregivers and those who are infirm, elderly, or otherwise in need? Why not look around in your congregation and take note of who needs help? In doing so, you might be working with Jehovah to answer a prayer.—[1 Cor. 10:24]. w18.08 24 ¶3, 5

^ (1 Tim. 5:8) Certainly if anyone does not provide for those who are his own, and especially for those who are members of his household, he has disowned the faith and is worse than a person without faith.

^ (1 Cor. 10:31) Therefore, whether you are eating or drinking or doing anything else, do all things for God’s glory.

^ (1 Cor. 10:24) Let each one keep seeking, not his own advantage, but that of the other person.

Wednesday, March 18

God was with him, and he rescued him out of all his tribulations.—[Acts 7:9, 10].

Joseph was about 17 years old when his own brothers out of jealousy sold him as a slave. Prior to this, Joseph had been his father’s favorite. ([Gen. 37:2-4,][23-28]) For about 13 years, Joseph had to endure slavery and imprisonment in Egypt, far away from his beloved father, Jacob. What helped Joseph not to give in to despair and bitterness? While suffering in prison, Joseph must have focused his mind on evidence of Jehovah’s blessing. ([Gen. 39:21;] Ps. 105:17-19) The prophetic dreams that Joseph had when he was younger would also have given him confidence that he had Jehovah’s favor. ([Gen. 37:5-11]) He likely poured out his anguish to Jehovah on more than one occasion. ([Ps. 145:18]) In response to Joseph’s heartfelt prayers, Jehovah gave him the inner conviction that He would be “with him” in all his trials. w18.10 28 ¶3-4

^ (Acts 7:9, 10) And the family heads became jealous of Joseph and sold him into Egypt. But God was with him, 10 and he rescued him out of all his tribulations and gave him favor and wisdom before Pharʹaoh king of Egypt. And he appointed him to govern Egypt and his whole house.

^ (Gen. 37:2-4) This is the history of Jacob. When Joseph was 17 years old, the young man was tending the flock with the sons of Bilʹhah and the sons of Zilʹpah, the wives of his father. And Joseph brought a bad report about them to their father. 3 Now Israel loved Joseph more than all his other sons because he was the son of his old age, and he had a special robe* made for him. 4 When his brothers saw that their father loved him more than all his brothers, they began to hate him, and they could not speak peaceably to him.

Or “a beautiful long garment.”

^ (Gen. 37:23-28) So as soon as Joseph came to his brothers, they stripped Joseph of his robe, the special robe that he wore, 24 and they took him and threw him into the waterpit. At the time the pit was empty; there was no water in it. 25 Then they sat down to eat. When they looked up, there was a caravan of Ishʹma·el·ites coming from Gilʹe·ad. Their camels were carrying labdanum gum, balsam, and resinous bark, and they were on their way down to Egypt. 26 At this Judah said to his brothers: “What profit would there be if we killed our brother and covered over his blood? 27 Come, now, let us sell him to the Ishʹma·el·ites, and do not let our hand be upon him. After all, he is our brother, our flesh.” So they listened to their brother. 28 And when the Midʹi·an·ite merchants were passing by, they lifted Joseph up out of the waterpit and sold him to the Ishʹma·el·ites for 20 pieces of silver. These men took Joseph into Egypt.

^ (Gen. 39:21) But Jehovah continued with Joseph and kept showing loyal love to him and granting him favor in the eyes of the chief officer of the prison.

^ (Ps. 105:17-19) He sent ahead of them a man Who was sold to be a slave, Joseph. 18 With fetters they bound* his feet, His neck was put in irons;* 19 Until the time that his word proved true, The saying of Jehovah is what refined him.

Lit., “afflicted.”

Or “His soul came into iron.”

^ (Gen. 37:5-11) Later Joseph had a dream and told it to his brothers, and they found further reason to hate him. 6 He said to them: “Please listen to this dream that I had. 7 There we were binding sheaves in the middle of the field when my sheaf got up and stood erect and your sheaves encircled and bowed down to my sheaf.” 8 His brothers said to him: “Are you really going to make yourself king over us and dominate us?” So they found another reason to hate him, because of his dreams and what he said. 9 After that he had still another dream, and he related it to his brothers: “I have had another dream. This time the sun and the moon and 11 stars were bowing down to me.” 10 Then he related it to his father as well as his brothers, and his father rebuked him and said to him: “What is the meaning of this dream of yours? Am I as well as your mother and your brothers really going to come and bow down to the earth to you?” 11 And his brothers grew jealous of him, but his father kept the saying in mind.

^ (Ps. 145:18) Jehovah is near to all those calling on him, To all who call on him in truth.*

Or “in sincerity.”

Thursday, March 19

The poor man is hated even by his neighbors, but many are the friends of the rich person.—[Prov. 14:20].

Material wealth is a factor that can affect our view of others. But how could a person’s wealth or his poverty affect the way we view him? Holy spirit moved Solomon to record a sad truth about imperfect humans as shown in today’s text. What does this proverb teach us? If we are not careful, we could desire the friendship of brothers who are wealthy while shunning brothers who are poor. Why is it so dangerous to measure the value of others solely on the basis of their material wealth? Because doing so could create class distinctions in the congregation. The disciple James warned that this problem was dividing some congregations in the first century. ([Jas. 2:1-4]) We must be on guard not to allow this thinking to affect our congregation today and make sure that we fight against making judgments that are based on the outward appearance. w18.08 10 ¶8-10

^ (Prov. 14:20) The poor man is hated even by his neighbors, But many are the friends of the rich person.

^ (Jas. 2:1-4) My brothers, you are not holding to the faith of our glorious Lord Jesus Christ while showing favoritism, are you? 2 For if a man with gold rings on his fingers and in splendid clothing comes into your meeting, but a poor man in filthy clothing also enters, 3 do you look with favor on the one wearing the splendid clothing and say, “You take this seat here in a fine place,” and do you say to the poor one, “You keep standing” or, “Take that seat there under my footstool”? 4 If so, do you not have class distinctions among yourselves, and have you not become judges rendering wicked decisions?

Friday, March 20

Have intense love for one another.—[1 Pet. 4:8].

Our appreciation for Jehovah’s special friendship is shown in how we treat fellow worshippers. They too belong to Jehovah. If we never lose sight of that fact, we will always treat our brothers and sisters with kindness and love. (1 Thess. 5:15) Jesus said to his followers: “By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.” ([John 13:35]) Interestingly, Malachi depicted Jehovah as “paying attention and listening” as His people interact with one another. ([Mal. 3:16]) Jehovah indeed “knows those who belong to him.” ([2 Tim. 2:19]) He is keenly aware of every single thing we do and say. ([Heb. 4:13]) When we are less than kind to our fellow worshippers, Jehovah is “paying attention and listening.” When we are hospitable, generous, forgiving, and kind to one another, we can be sure that Jehovah takes notice of that as well.—[Heb. 13:16]. w18.07 26 ¶15, 17

^ (1 Pet. 4:8) Above all things, have intense love for one another, because love covers a multitude of sins.

^ (1 Thess. 5:15) See that no one repays injury for injury to anyone, but always pursue what is good toward one another and to all others.

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (Mal. 3:16) At that time those who fear Jehovah spoke with one another, each one with his companion, and Jehovah kept paying attention and listening. And a book of remembrance was written before him for those fearing Jehovah and for those meditating on* his name.

Or “thinking on.” Or possibly, “treasuring.”

^ (2 Tim. 2:19) Despite that, the solid foundation of God remains standing, having this seal, “Jehovah* knows those who belong to him,” and, “Let everyone calling on the name of Jehovah* renounce unrighteousness.”

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ (Heb. 4:13) And there is not a creation that is hidden from his sight, but all things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes of the one to whom we must give an account.

^ (Heb. 13:16) Moreover, do not forget to do good and to share what you have with others, for God is well-pleased with such sacrifices.

Saturday, March 21

To [Jehovah] you should cling.—[Deut. 10:20].

It makes sense to cling to Jehovah. No one is more powerful, wise, or loving than our God! Who of us would not want to be on his side? ([Ps. 96:4-6]) Still, some of God’s worshippers have wavered when a situation called for them to take sides with Jehovah. Consider the case of Cain. He did not profess to worship any other god but Jehovah. Cain’s worship, however, was not acceptable to God. There were seeds of wickedness growing deep within his heart. ([1 John 3:12]) Jehovah reached out to Cain and told him: “If you turn to doing good, will you not be restored to favor? But if you do not turn to doing good, sin is crouching at the door, and its craving is to dominate you; but will you get the mastery over it?” ([Gen. 4:6, 7]) Jehovah was, in effect, telling Cain, “If you repent and take a firm stand on my side, I will, in turn, be on your side.” But Cain did not listen to the counsel. w18.07 17 ¶1, 3; 18 ¶4

^ (Deut. 10:20) “Jehovah your God you should fear, him you should serve, to him you should cling, and by his name you should swear.

^ (Ps. 96:4-6) Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise. He is more awe-inspiring than all other gods.  5 All the gods of the peoples are worthless gods, But Jehovah is the one who made the heavens.  6 In his presence are majesty* and splendor; Strength and beauty are in his sanctuary.

Or “dignity.”

^ (1 John 3:12) not like Cain, who originated with the wicked one and slaughtered his brother. And for what reason did he slaughter him? Because his own works were wicked, but those of his brother were righteous.

^ (Gen. 4:6, 7) Then Jehovah said to Cain: “Why are you so angry and dejected? 7 If you turn to doing good, will you not be restored to favor?* But if you do not turn to doing good, sin is crouching at the door, and its craving is to dominate you; but will you get the mastery over it?”

Or “will there not be an exaltation?”

Sunday, March 22

Let your light shine before men.—[Matt. 5:16].

One way we let our light shine is by preaching the good news and making disciples. (Matt. 28:19, 20) In addition, we can glorify Jehovah by our Christian conduct. Householders and passersby observe our behavior. Our friendly smile and warm greeting say much about who we are and what kind of God we worship. “When you enter the house,” Jesus told his disciples, “greet the household.” ([Matt. 10:12]) In the area where Jesus and the apostles often preached, it was not unusual for people to invite strangers into their homes. Today, this is not the custom in many places. Still, your positive, friendly manner as you explain why you are there can often allay a householder’s concern or ease his irritation. A pleasant smile is often the best introduction. That has also proved true when brothers and sisters engage in public witnessing using a literature cart. You may find that people often react favorably to a pleasant smile and greeting. w18.06 22 ¶4-5

^ (Matt. 5:16) Likewise, let your light shine before men, so that they may see your fine works and give glory to your Father who is in the heavens.

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Matt. 10:12) When you enter the house, greet the household.

Monday, March 23

God is not partial.—[Acts 10:34].

The apostle Peter had a custom of associating only with Jews. But after God made it clear that Christians should not be partial, Peter preached to Cornelius, a Roman soldier. ([Acts 10:28,][35]) Thereafter, Peter enjoyed food and association with Gentile believers. Years later, though, Peter stopped eating with non-Jewish Christians in the city of Antioch. ([Gal. 2:11-14]) In that case, Paul gave Peter a fitting reproof, which he evidently accepted. When Peter wrote his first letter to Jewish and Gentile Christians in Asia Minor, he spoke warmly about the whole association of brothers. ([1 Pet. 1:1;][2:17]) Clearly, the apostles did learn from Jesus’ example to love “all sorts of men.” ([John 12:32;][1 Tim. 4:10]) Although it took time, they adjusted their way of thinking. Putting on “the new personality,” the early Christians came to view all people as equal in the sight of God.—Col. 3:10, 11. w18.06 11 ¶15-16

^ (Acts 10:34) At this Peter began to speak, and he said: “Now I truly understand that God is not partial,

^ (Acts 10:28) He said to them: “You well know how unlawful it is for a Jew to associate with or approach a man of another race, and yet God has shown me that I should call no man defiled or unclean.

^ (Acts 10:35) but in every nation the man who fears him and does what is right is acceptable to him.

^ (Gal. 2:11-14) However, when Ceʹphas* came to Antioch, I resisted* him face-to-face, because he was clearly in the wrong.* 12 For before certain men from James arrived, he used to eat with people of the nations; but when they arrived, he stopped doing this and separated himself, fearing those of the circumcised class. 13 The rest of the Jews also joined him in putting on this pretense,* so that even Barʹna·bas was led along with them in their pretense.* 14 But when I saw that they were not walking in step with the truth of the good news, I said to Ceʹphas* before them all: “If you, though you are a Jew, live as the nations do and not as Jews do, how can you compel people of the nations to live according to Jewish practice?”

Also called Peter.

Or “confronted.”

Or “he stood condemned.”

Or “hypocrisy.”

Or “hypocrisy.”

Also called Peter.

^ (1 Pet. 1:1) Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the temporary residents scattered about in Ponʹtus, Ga·laʹti·a, Cap·pa·doʹci·a, Asia, and Bi·thynʹi·a, to those chosen

^ (1 Pet. 2:17) Honor men of all sorts, have love for the whole association of brothers,* be in fear of God, honor the king.

Lit., “the brotherhood.”

^ (John 12:32) And yet I, if I am lifted up from the earth, will draw all sorts of men to myself.”

^ (1 Tim. 4:10) This is why we are working hard and exerting ourselves, because we have rested our hope on a living God, who is a Savior of all sorts of men, especially of faithful ones.

^ (Col. 3:10, 11) and clothe yourselves with the new personality, which through accurate knowledge is being made new according to the image of the One who created it, 11 where there is neither Greek nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, foreigner, Scythʹi·an,* slave, or freeman; but Christ is all things and in all.

“Scythian” implied an uncivilized person.

Tuesday, March 24

Stand firm . . . wearing the breastplate of righteousness.—[Eph. 6:14].

One type of breastplate worn by a Roman soldier in the first century consisted of overlapping horizontal strips of iron. This type of garment required that he regularly check that the plates were firmly fixed in place in order to protect his heart and other vital organs. What an appropriate symbol of how Jehovah’s righteous standards can protect our figurative heart! ([Prov. 4:23]) Just as a soldier would not swap a breastplate of iron for one made of an inferior metal, we would never want to exchange Jehovah’s standards of what is right for our own. Our judgment is just too flawed to offer us the protection that we need. ([Prov. 3:5, 6]) Instead, we regularly check that the ‘iron plates’ Jehovah has given us are firmly fixed over our heart. And the more we love divine truths, the easier it is to carry our “breastplate,” that is, to live by God’s righteous standards.—Ps. 111:7, 8;[1 John 5:3]. w18.05 28 ¶3-4, 6-7

^ (Eph. 6:14) Stand firm, therefore, with the belt of truth fastened around your waist, wearing the breastplate of righteousness,

^ (Prov. 4:23) Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart, For out of it are the sources of life.

^ (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

^ (Ps. 111:7, 8) The works of his hands are truth and justice; Trustworthy are all his orders.  8 They are always reliable,* now and forever; They are made in truth and righteousness.

Or “well-founded.”

^ (1 John 5:3) For this is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments; and yet his commandments are not burdensome,

Wednesday, March 25

The people were quarreling with Moses.—[Num. 20:3].

Despite Moses’ long record of unselfish leadership, the people complained not only about the lack of water but also about Moses, as if it were his fault that they were thirsty. ([Num. 20:1-5,][9-11]) In the heat of anger, Moses lost his mild disposition. Rather than speak in faith to the rock, as Jehovah had commanded, Moses spoke in bitterness to the people and gave credit to himself. Then, he struck the rock twice and much water gushed out. Pride and anger caused him to make a painful mistake. (Ps. 106:32, 33) For his temporary lack of meekness, Moses was not allowed to enter the Promised Land. ([Num. 20:12]) From this incident, we learn valuable lessons. First, we must constantly work at maintaining our meek attitude. If we neglect it for a moment, pride may reassert itself and cause us to speak and act foolishly. Second, stress can weaken us, so we must strive to be meek, even when we are under pressure. w19.02 12-13 ¶19-21

^ (Num. 20:3) The people were quarreling with Moses, saying: “If only we had died when our brothers died before Jehovah!

^ (Num. 20:1-5) In the first month, the entire assembly of the Israelites came into the wilderness of Zin, and the people began dwelling in Kaʹdesh. It was there that Mirʹi·am died and was buried. 2 Now there was no water for the assembly, and they gathered together against Moses and Aaron. 3 The people were quarreling with Moses, saying: “If only we had died when our brothers died before Jehovah! 4 Why have you brought Jehovah’s congregation into this wilderness for us and our livestock to die here? 5 And why have you led us up out of Egypt to bring us into this evil place? It is no place for seed and figs and vines and pomegranates, and there is no water to drink.”

^ (Num. 20:9-11) So Moses took the rod from before Jehovah, just as He had commanded him. 10 Then Moses and Aaron called the congregation together before the crag, and he said to them: “Hear, now, you rebels! Must we bring out water for you from this crag?” 11 With that Moses lifted his hand up and struck the crag twice with his rod, and much water began to pour out, and the assembly and their livestock began to drink.

^ (Ps. 106:32, 33) They provoked Him at the waters of Merʹi·bah,* And it went badly for Moses because of them. 33 They embittered his spirit, And he spoke rashly with his lips.

Meaning “Quarreling.”

^ (Num. 20:12) Jehovah later said to Moses and Aaron: “Because you did not show faith in me and sanctify me before the eyes of the people of Israel, you will not bring this congregation into the land that I will give them.”

Thursday, March 26

This good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth.—[Matt. 24:14].

Will obeying Jesus’ command to preach become burdensome? On the contrary. After relating his illustration of the vine, Jesus said that as Kingdom preachers, we will experience joy. ([John 15:11]) In fact, he assured us that his joy will become ours. How? Jesus compared himself to a vine and his disciples to branches. ([John 15:5]) A vine supports the branches. As long as the branches are attached to it, they receive water and nourishment that flows from the vine. Similarly, as long as we remain in union with Christ by closely following in his steps, we experience the same joy that he has in doing his Father’s will. ([John 4:34;][17:13;][1 Pet. 2:21]) Notes Hanne, a pioneer for over 40 years, “The joy I always feel after I have been in the ministry stimulates me to continue in Jehovah’s service.” Indeed, deep-seated joy gives us the strength to keep on preaching even in challenging territories.—Matt. 5:10-12. w18.05 17 ¶2; 20 ¶14

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (John 15:11) “These things I have spoken to you, so that my joy may be in you and your joy may be made full.

^ (John 15:5) I am the vine; you are the branches. Whoever remains in union with me and I in union with him, this one bears much fruit; for apart from me you can do* nothing at all.

Or “produce.”

^ (John 4:34) Jesus said to them: “My food is to do the will of him who sent me and to finish his work.

^ (John 17:13) But now I am coming to you, and I am saying these things in the world, so that they may have my joy made complete in themselves.

^ (1 Pet. 2:21) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

^ (Matt. 5:10-12) “Happy are those who have been persecuted for righteousness’ sake, since the Kingdom of the heavens belongs to them. 11 “Happy are you when people reproach* you and persecute you and lyingly say every sort of wicked thing against you for my sake. 12 Rejoice and be overjoyed, since your reward is great in the heavens, for in that way they persecuted the prophets prior to you.

Or “insult.”

Friday, March 27

I was appointed . . . a teacher of nations in the matter of faith and truth.—[1 Tim. 2:7].

In the first century, perhaps the apostle who did the most to encourage his brothers was the apostle Paul. He was sent by the holy spirit to preach to the people of the nations of the Greco-Roman world, who worshipped many gods. ([Gal. 2:7-9]) Paul traveled far and wide in what is now Turkey, as well as in Greece and Italy, establishing Christian congregations among non-Jews. These newly converted Christians “suffered at the hands of [their] own countrymen” and needed encouragement. (1 Thess. 2:14) About the year 50 C.E., Paul wrote to the young congregation in Thessalonica: “We always thank God when we mention all of you in our prayers, for we continually remember your faithful work, your loving labor, and your endurance.” (1 Thess. 1:2, 3) He also exhorted them to strengthen one another, saying: “Keep encouraging one another and building one another up.”—1 Thess. 5:11. w18.04 18-19 ¶16-17

^ (1 Tim. 2:7) For the purpose of this witness I was appointed a preacher and an apostle—I am telling the truth, I am not lying—a teacher of nations in the matter of faith and truth.

^ (Gal. 2:7-9) On the contrary, when they saw that I had been entrusted with the good news for those who are uncircumcised, just as Peter had been for those who are circumcised— 8 for the one who empowered Peter for an apostleship to those who are circumcised also empowered me for those who are of the nations— 9 and when they recognized the undeserved kindness that was given me, James and Ceʹphas* and John, the ones who seemed to be pillars, gave Barʹna·bas and me the right hand of fellowship,* so that we should go to the nations but they to those who are circumcised.

Also called Peter.

Or “partnership.”

^ (1 Thess. 2:14) For you, brothers, became imitators of the congregations of God in union with Christ Jesus that are in Ju·deʹa, because you suffered at the hands of your own countrymen the same things that they also are suffering at the hands of the Jews,

^ (1 Thess. 1:2, 3) We always thank God when we mention all of you in our prayers, 3 for we continually remember your faithful work, your loving labor, and your endurance because of your hope in our Lord Jesus Christ in the presence of our God and Father.

^ (1 Thess. 5:11) Therefore, keep encouraging* one another and building one another up, just as you are in fact doing.

Or “comforting.”

Saturday, March 28

The good news has to be preached first.—[Mark 13:10].

A young person who focuses his life on the desire to please Jehovah gives special attention to the ministry. Because the preaching work is so urgent, it should be high on our list of priorities. Could you set the goal of sharing in the ministry more often? Could you pioneer? But what if you find little joy in preaching? And how can you be more effective at giving a witness? Two basic steps will help: Prepare well, and do not give up sharing what you know with others. It might surprise you how much joy you will then find when preaching. You could start by working out an answer to a question commonly raised by schoolmates, such as “Why do you believe in God?” Our jw.org website contains articles designed to help young people work out for themselves how to answer that question. There you will find a worksheet entitled “Why Do I Believe in God?” The worksheet will guide you in preparing your own answer. w18.04 27 ¶10-11

^ (Mark 13:10) Also, in all the nations, the good news has to be preached first.

Sunday, March 29

Be fruitful and become many.—[Gen. 1:28].

Even though Adam and Eve initially enjoyed freedom in many ways, there were limits imposed on them. Some of them were instinctive, but they were limits nonetheless. For example, our first parents knew that to keep on living, they had to breathe, eat, sleep, and so on. Would they feel a loss of freedom for having to do these things? No, for Jehovah saw to it that even in doing such routine things, they could find enjoyment and contentment. (Ps. 104:14, 15; Eccl. 3:12, 13) Jehovah specifically commanded Adam and Eve to populate the earth and to take care of it. Did this command in some way deprive them of their freedom? Of course not! It was given to enable humans to participate in their Creator’s purpose—to make the earth into a global paradise home for a race of perfect humans forever. ([Ps. 127:3;][Isa. 45:18]) Enjoying their marriage and family for all eternity could have been Adam and Eve’s happy lot in life. w18.04 4-5 ¶7-8

^ (Gen. 1:28) Further, God blessed them, and God said to them: “Be fruitful and become many, fill the earth and subdue it, and have in subjection the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and every living creature that is moving on the earth.”

^ (Ps. 104:14, 15) He is making grass grow for the cattle And vegetation for mankind’s use, To grow food from the land 15 And wine that makes man’s heart rejoice, Oil that makes the face shine, And bread that sustains the heart of mortal man.

^ (Eccl. 3:12, 13) I have concluded that there is nothing better for them than to rejoice and to do good during their life, 13 also that everyone should eat and drink and find enjoyment for all his hard work. It is the gift of God.

^ (Ps. 127:3) Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.

Or “Children.”

^ (Isa. 45:18) For this is what Jehovah says, The Creator of the heavens, the true God, The One who formed the earth, its Maker who firmly established it, Who did not create it simply for nothing,* but formed it to be inhabited: “I am Jehovah, and there is no one else.

Or possibly, “to be empty.”

Monday, March 30

All those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.—[Acts 13:48].

If we are patient with people in the ministry, we will not expect them to understand or accept Bible truth the first time they hear it. As an example, consider how we might reason with someone about the hope of everlasting life on a paradise earth. Many believe that death is the end of it all or that all good people go to heaven. One brother relates an approach that he finds effective. First, he reads [Genesis 1:28]. Then, he asks the householder where and in what conditions God wanted the human family to live. Most people answer, “On earth, in good conditions.” Next, the brother reads [Isaiah 55:11] and asks whether God’s purpose has changed. Often, the householder will answer no. Finally, the brother reads Psalm 37:10, 11 and asks what mankind’s future will be like. Using this Scriptural reasoning, he has helped a number of people to understand that God still wants good people to live forever in Paradise on earth. w19.03 24 ¶14-15; 25 ¶19

^ (Acts 13:48) When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.

^ (Gen. 1:28) Further, God blessed them, and God said to them: “Be fruitful and become many, fill the earth and subdue it, and have in subjection the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and every living creature that is moving on the earth.”

^ (Isa. 55:11) So my word that goes out of my mouth will be.* It will not return to me without results, But it will certainly accomplish whatever is my delight,* And it will have sure success in what I send it to do.

Or “will prove to be.”

Or “my will.”

^ (Ps. 37:10, 11) Just a little while longer, and the wicked will be no more; You will look at where they were, And they will not be there. 11 But the meek will possess the earth, And they will find exquisite delight in the abundance of peace.

Tuesday, March 31

Listen to him.—[Matt. 17:5].

Jehovah made it clear that he wants us to listen to his Son’s words and obey them. Jesus lovingly taught his followers how to preach the good news, and he repeatedly reminded them to keep on the watch. ([Matt. 24:42;][28:19, 20]) He also urged them to exert themselves vigorously, and he encouraged them not to give up. ([Luke 13:24]) Jesus stressed the need for his followers to love one another, to remain united, and to observe his commandments. ([John 15:10,][12, 13]) That counsel is just as valid today as it was when Jesus gave it. Jesus said: “Everyone who is on the side of the truth listens to my voice.” ([John 18:37]) We show that we are listening to his voice when we “continue putting up with one another and forgiving one another freely.” ([Col. 3:13;] Luke 17:3, 4) We further show that we are listening to his voice by zealously preaching the good news “in favorable times and difficult times.”—[2 Tim. 4:2]. w19.03 10 ¶9-10

^ (Matt. 17:5) While he was still speaking, look! a bright cloud overshadowed them, and look! a voice out of the cloud said: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved. Listen to him.”

^ (Matt. 24:42) Keep on the watch, therefore, because you do not know on what day your Lord is coming.

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (Luke 13:24) “Exert yourselves vigorously to get in through the narrow door, because many, I tell you, will seek to get in but will not be able.

^ (John 15:10) If you observe my commandments, you will remain in my love, just as I have observed the commandments of the Father and remain in his love.

^ (John 15:12, 13) This is my commandment, that you love one another just as I have loved you. 13 No one has love greater than this, that someone should surrender his life in behalf of his friends.

^ (John 18:37) So Pilate said to him: “Well, then, are you a king?” Jesus answered: “You yourself are saying that I am a king. For this I have been born, and for this I have come into the world, that I should bear witness to the truth. Everyone who is on the side of the truth listens to my voice.”

^ (Col. 3:13) Continue putting up with one another and forgiving one another freely even if anyone has a cause for complaint against another. Just as Jehovah* freely forgave you, you must also do the same.

See App. A5.

^ (Luke 17:3, 4) Pay attention to yourselves. If your brother commits a sin, rebuke him, and if he repents, forgive him. 4 Even if he sins seven times a day against you and he comes back to you seven times, saying, ‘I repent,’ you must forgive him.”

^ (2 Tim. 4:2) Preach the word; be at it urgently in favorable times and difficult times; reprove, reprimand, exhort, with all patience and art of teaching.

April

Wednesday, April 1

[Jesus] said to Peter: “Get behind me, Satan! . . . You think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.”—[Matt. 16:23].

What about us? Do we think God’s thoughts or those of this world? Granted, we have likely conformed our conduct to God’s requirements. But what about our thinking? Are we bringing our thoughts and viewpoints into alignment with Jehovah’s? Doing so requires a deliberate effort. On the other hand, little or no effort is needed to absorb the world’s thinking. That is because the spirit of the world is all around us. ([Eph. 2:2]) Furthermore, because it often appeals to self-interest, the world’s way of thinking can be enticing. Yes, it is challenging to think like Jehovah but all too easy to think like the world. However, if we allow the world to mold our thinking, we will be inclined toward selfishness and a desire for moral independence. (Mark 7:21, 22) It is therefore vital that we cultivate “God’s thoughts,” not “those of men.” w18.11 18 ¶1; 19 ¶3-4

^ (Matt. 16:23) But turning his back,* he said to Peter: “Get behind me, Satan! You are a stumbling block to me, because you think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.”*

Or “turning around.”

Or “you have, not God’s mind, but that of humans.”

^ (Eph. 2:2) in which you at one time walked according to the system of things* of this world, according to the ruler of the authority of the air, the spirit that is now at work in the sons of disobedience.

Or “the course.”

^ (Mark 7:21, 22) For from inside, out of the heart of men, come injurious reasonings: sexual immorality, thefts, murders, 22 acts of adultery, greed, acts of wickedness, deceit, brazen conduct, an envious eye, blasphemy, haughtiness, and unreasonableness.

Thursday, April 2

This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved.—[Matt. 3:17].

How encouraged Jesus must have been when Jehovah acknowledged him on three separate occasions by speaking directly from heaven. Just after Jesus’ baptism in the Jordan River, Jehovah said the above. Evidently, John the Baptist was the only other person who heard those words. Then, about a year before Jesus’ death, three of his apostles heard Jehovah say about Jesus: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved. Listen to him.” ([Matt. 17:5]) Finally, just a few days before Jesus’ death, Jehovah again spoke to his Son from heaven. ([John 12:28]) Even though Jesus knew that he would experience a shameful death, falsely branded as a blasphemer, he prayed that Jehovah’s will be done and not his. ([Matt. 26:39,][42]) “He endured a torture stake, despising shame,” not seeking recognition from the world, but only from his Father.—[Heb. 12:2]. w18.07 10-11 ¶15-16

Memorial Bible reading: (Events after sunset: Nisan 9) [Mark 14:3-9]

^ (Matt. 3:17) Look! Also, a voice from the heavens said: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved.”

^ (Matt. 17:5) While he was still speaking, look! a bright cloud overshadowed them, and look! a voice out of the cloud said: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved. Listen to him.”

^ (John 12:28) Father, glorify your name.” Then a voice came out of heaven: “I have glorified it and will glorify it again.”

^ (Matt. 26:39) And going a little way forward, he fell facedown, praying: “My Father, if it is possible, let this cup pass away from me. Yet, not as I will, but as you will.”

^ (Matt. 26:42) Again, a second time, he went off and prayed: “My Father, if it is not possible for this to pass away unless I drink it, let your will take place.”

^ (Heb. 12:2) as we look intently at the Chief Agent and Perfecter of our faith, Jesus. For the joy that was set before him he endured a torture stake,* despising shame, and has sat down at the right hand of the throne of God.

See Glossary.

^ (Mark 14:3-9) And while he was at Bethʹa·ny dining* in the house of Simon the leper, a woman came with an alabaster jar of perfumed oil, genuine nard, very expensive. She broke open the alabaster jar and began pouring it on his head. 4 At this some said to one another indignantly: “Why has this perfumed oil been wasted? 5 For this perfumed oil could have been sold for more than 300 de·narʹi·i and the money given to the poor!” And they were greatly annoyed with* her. 6 But Jesus said: “Let her alone. Why do you try to make trouble for her? She did a fine deed toward me. 7 For you always have the poor with you, and you can do them good whenever you want to, but you will not always have me. 8 She did what she could; she poured perfumed oil on my body beforehand, in view of the burial. 9 Truly I say to you, wherever the good news is preached in all the world, what this woman did will also be told in memory of her.”

Or “reclining at the table.”

Or “they spoke angrily to; they scolded.”

Friday, April 3

Father, if you want to, remove this cup from me.—[Luke 22:42].

Just after Jesus introduced the Lord’s Evening Meal, he demonstrated tremendous courage. How so? Jesus accepted his Father’s will for him, even though he knew that doing so meant that he would be executed for the shameful crime of blasphemy. (Matt. 26:65, 66) Jesus maintained perfect integrity so as to honor Jehovah’s name, uphold God’s sovereignty, and open the way to endless life for repentant humans. At the same time, Jesus prepared his followers for what they would soon face. Jesus also showed courage by setting aside any anxiety he may have had and by focusing attention on the needs of his faithful apostles. The simple meal, which he introduced after dismissing Judas, would remind those who would become his anointed followers of the benefits of Jesus’ shed blood and of sharing in the new covenant.—1 Cor. 10:16, 17. w19.01 22 ¶7-8

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 9) Mark 11:1-11

^ (Luke 22:42) saying: “Father, if you want to, remove this cup from me. Nevertheless, let, not my will, but yours take place.”

^ (Matt. 26:65, 66) Then the high priest ripped his outer garments, saying: “He has blasphemed! What further need do we have of witnesses? See! Now you have heard the blasphemy. 66 What is your opinion?” They answered: “He deserves to die.”

^ (1 Cor. 10:16, 17) The cup of blessing that we bless, is it not a sharing in the blood of the Christ? The loaf that we break, is it not a sharing in the body of the Christ? 17 Because there is one loaf, we, although many, are one body, for we are all partaking of that one loaf.

Saturday, April 4

Father, glorify your name.—[John 12:28].

In response, Jesus’ Father spoke from heaven: “I have glorified it and will glorify it again.” Jesus was troubled because of the great responsibility he had to remain faithful to Jehovah. Jesus was aware that he was going to suffer a brutal scourging and a cruel death. ([Matt. 26:38]) More than all else, Jesus wanted to glorify his Father’s name. Jesus was charged with blasphemy, and he was concerned that his death would bring reproach on God. Like Jesus, we too may be concerned about reproach brought on Jehovah’s name. Perhaps like Jesus, we are victims of unjust treatment. Or we may be disturbed by false stories that opposers spread about us. We may think about the reproach these reports bring on Jehovah’s name. At such times, Jehovah’s words are of great comfort to us. Jehovah will never fail to glorify his name.—Ps. 94:22, 23;[Isa. 65:17]. w19.03 11-12 ¶14-16

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 10) Mark 11:12-19

^ (John 12:28) Father, glorify your name.” Then a voice came out of heaven: “I have glorified it and will glorify it again.”

^ (Matt. 26:38) Then he said to them: “I am deeply grieved, even to death. Stay here and keep on the watch with me.”

^ (Ps. 94:22, 23) But Jehovah will become a secure refuge* for me, My God is my rock of refuge. 23 He will make their wicked deeds come back upon them. He will do away with* them by means of their own evil. Jehovah our God will do away with* them.

Or “secure height.”

Lit., “will silence.”

Lit., “will silence.”

^ (Isa. 65:17) For look! I am creating new heavens and a new earth; And the former things will not be called to mind,* Nor will they come up into the heart.

Or “be remembered.”

^ (Mark 11:12-19) The next day when they were leaving Bethʹa·ny, he felt hungry. 13 From a distance he caught sight of a fig tree that had leaves, and he went to see whether he could find something on it. But on coming to it, he found nothing but leaves, for it was not the season for figs. 14 So he said to it: “Let no one eat fruit from you ever again.” And his disciples were listening. 15 They now came to Jerusalem. There he entered the temple and started to throw out those selling and buying in the temple, and he overturned the tables of the money changers and the benches of those selling doves, 16 and he would not let anyone carry a utensil through the temple. 17 He was teaching and saying to them: “Is it not written, ‘My house will be called a house of prayer for all the nations’? But you have made it a cave of robbers.” 18 And the chief priests and the scribes heard it, and they began to seek how to kill him; for they were in fear of him, because all the crowd was astounded at his teaching. 19 When it became late in the day, they went out of the city.

Sunday, April 5

Jesus began explaining to his disciples that he must . . . suffer many things . . . and be killed.—[Matt. 16:21].

Jesus’ disciples could not believe what they were hearing. Jesus, the one they expected to restore Israel’s kingdom, said that he would soon suffer and die. It was the apostle Peter who spoke up. “Be kind to yourself, Lord,” he said. “You will not have this happen to you at all.” Jesus countered: “Get behind me, Satan! You are a stumbling block to me, because you think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.” (Matt. 16:22, 23;[Acts 1:6]) With those words, Jesus made a distinction between thoughts that originate with God and thoughts that originate with this world under Satan’s control. ([1 John 5:19]) Peter echoed the self-sparing attitude of the world. But Jesus knew that his Father’s thinking was different. In his reply to Peter, Jesus clearly rejected the world’s thinking in favor of Jehovah’s. w18.11 18 ¶1-2

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 11) Mark 11:20–12:27,[41-44]

^ (Matt. 16:21) From that time forward, Jesus began explaining to his disciples that he must go to Jerusalem and suffer many things from the elders and chief priests and scribes and be killed, and on the third day be raised up.

^ (Matt. 16:22, 23) At this Peter took him aside and began to rebuke him, saying: “Be kind to yourself, Lord; you will not have this happen to you at all.” 23 But turning his back,* he said to Peter: “Get behind me, Satan! You are a stumbling block to me, because you think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.”*

Or “turning around.”

Or “you have, not God’s mind, but that of humans.”

^ (Acts 1:6) So when they had assembled, they asked him: “Lord, are you restoring the kingdom to Israel at this time?”

^ (1 John 5:19) We know that we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.

^ (Mark 12:41-44) And he sat down with the treasury chests in view and began observing how the crowd was dropping money into the treasury chests, and many rich people were dropping in many coins. 42 Now a poor widow came and dropped in two small coins of very little value. 43 So he called his disciples to him and said to them: “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than all the others who put money into the treasury chests. 44 For they all put in out of their surplus, but she, out of her want,* put in everything she had, all she had to live on.”

Or “poverty.”

Monday, April 6

Keep proclaiming the death of the Lord, until he comes.—[1 Cor. 11:26].

Imagine what Jehovah sees when millions around the world gather for the Lord’s Evening Meal. He looks at more than just the large number of people; he notices each individual who is present. For instance, he sees those who faithfully come every year. Among them may be individuals who come despite facing severe persecution. Others do not come regularly to other meetings, but they view attending the Memorial as a solemn duty. Jehovah also notices those who may be at the Memorial for the first time, perhaps out of curiosity. Certainly, Jehovah is pleased to see that so many attend the Memorial. ([Luke 22:19]) However, he is more interested in the reason for their coming; motive matters to Jehovah. Are we eager to be instructed by Jehovah and the organization that he is using?—[Isa. 30:20;][John 6:45]. w19.01 26 ¶1-3

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 12) Mark 14:1, 2,[10, 11;] Matthew 26:1-5,[14-16]

^ (1 Cor. 11:26) For whenever you eat this loaf and drink this cup, you keep proclaiming the death of the Lord, until he comes.

^ (Luke 22:19) Also, he took a loaf, gave thanks, broke it, and gave it to them, saying: “This means my body, which is to be given in your behalf. Keep doing this in remembrance of me.”

^ (Isa. 30:20) Though Jehovah will give you bread in the form of distress and water in the form of oppression, your Grand Instructor will no longer hide himself, and you will see your Grand Instructor with your own eyes.

^ (John 6:45) It is written in the Prophets: ‘They will all be taught* by Jehovah.’ Everyone who has listened to the Father and has learned comes to me.

Or “be those taught.”

^ (Mark 14:1, 2) Now the Passover and the Festival of Unleavened Bread was two days later. And the chief priests and the scribes were looking for a way to seize* him by cunning* and kill him; 2 for they were saying: “Not at the festival; perhaps there might be an uproar of the people.”

Or “arrest.”

Or “deceit; craftiness.”

^ (Mark 14:10, 11) And Judas Is·carʹi·ot, one of the Twelve, went off to the chief priests in order to betray him to them. 11 When they heard it, they were delighted and promised to give him silver money. So he began seeking an opportunity to betray him.

^ (Matt. 26:1-5) Now when Jesus had finished saying all these things, he said to his disciples: 2 “You know that two days from now the Passover takes place, and the Son of man will be handed over to be executed on the stake.” 3 Then the chief priests and the elders of the people gathered in the courtyard of the high priest, who was named Caʹia·phas, 4 and they conspired together to seize* Jesus by cunning* and to kill him. 5 However, they were saying: “Not at the festival, so that there may not be an uproar among the people.”

Or “arrest.”

Or “deceit; craftiness.”

^ (Matt. 26:14-16) Then one of the Twelve, the one called Judas Is·carʹi·ot, went to the chief priests 15 and said: “What will you give me to betray him to you?” They stipulated to him 30 silver pieces. 16 So from then on, he kept looking for a good opportunity to betray him.

Memorial Date
After Sundown
Tuesday, April 7

Christ died for us.—[Rom. 5:8].

Jesus was willing not only to die for his disciples but also to live each day in a way that put their interests ahead of his own. For instance, he met with his followers even when he was physically tired or emotionally distressed. (Luke 22:39-46) And he focused on what he could give to others, not on what he could get from them. ([Matt. 20:28]) We belong to the only true Christian brotherhood, and we enjoy spending as much time as possible inviting new ones to join us. However, we are particularly interested in helping those who are “related to us in the faith” but who have become inactive. ([Gal. 6:10]) We prove our love for them by encouraging them to attend our meetings, especially the Memorial. Like Jehovah and Jesus, we are deeply moved when an inactive one returns to Jehovah.—[Matt. 18:14]. w19.01 29 ¶12, 14; 30 ¶15

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 13) Mark 14:12-16; Matthew 26:17-19 (Events after sunset: Nisan 14) Mark 14:17-72

^ (Rom. 5:8) But God recommends his own love to us* in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.

Or “demonstrates (shows) his own love for us.”

^ (Luke 22:39-46) On leaving, he went as was his custom to the Mount of Olives, and the disciples also followed him. 40 On arriving at the place, he said to them: “Carry on prayer so that you do not enter into temptation.” 41 And he withdrew from them about a stone’s throw away, and he bent his knees and began to pray, 42 saying: “Father, if you want to, remove this cup from me. Nevertheless, let, not my will, but yours take place.” 43 Then an angel from heaven appeared to him and strengthened him. 44 But he was in such agony that he kept praying more earnestly; and his sweat became as drops of blood falling to the ground. 45 When he rose from prayer and went to the disciples, he found them slumbering, exhausted from grief. 46 He said to them: “Why are you sleeping? Get up and keep praying, so that you do not enter into temptation.”

^ (Matt. 20:28) Just as the Son of man came, not to be ministered to, but to minister and to give his life as a ransom in exchange for many.”

^ (Gal. 6:10) So, then, as long as we have the opportunity,* let us work what is good toward all, but especially toward those related to us in the faith.

Lit., “appointed time.”

^ (Matt. 18:14) Likewise, it is not a desirable thing to my Father who is in heaven for even one of these little ones to perish.

^ (Mark 14:12-16) Now on the first day of the Unleavened Bread, when they customarily offered up the Passover sacrifice, his disciples said to him: “Where do you want us to go and prepare for you to eat the Passover?” 13 With that he sent two of his disciples and said to them: “Go into the city, and a man carrying an earthenware water jar will meet you. Follow him, 14 and wherever he goes inside, say to the master of the house, ‘The Teacher says: “Where is the guest room where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?”’ 15 And he will show you a large upper room, furnished and ready. Prepare it for us there.” 16 So the disciples went out, and they entered the city and found it just as he said to them, and they prepared for the Passover.

^ (Matt. 26:17-19) On the first day of the Unleavened Bread, the disciples came to Jesus, saying: “Where do you want us to prepare for you to eat the Passover?” 18 He said: “Go into the city to So-and-so and say to him, ‘The Teacher says: “My appointed time is near; I will celebrate the Passover with my disciples at your home.”’” 19 So the disciples did as Jesus instructed them and prepared for the Passover.

Wednesday, April 8

This means my body. . . . This means my “blood of the covenant.”—Matt. 26:26-28.

In introducing the Memorial of his death, Jesus used only the Passover bread and the wine that were already on hand. Jesus told his apostles that those two basic items symbolized his perfect body and blood, which he would soon offer up in their behalf. The apostles may not have been surprised at the simplicity of this important new meal. Why not? Months earlier, at the home of his close friends—Lazarus, Martha, and Mary—Jesus began teaching. Martha was present, but she was distracted with preparing a large meal for her honored guest. Observing this, Jesus kindly corrected Martha, helping her to see that an elaborate meal was not always necessary. (Luke 10:40-42) Later, with just hours remaining before his sacrificial death, Jesus applied his own counsel. He kept the Memorial meal simple. w19.01 20-21 ¶3-4

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 14) Mark 15:1-47

^ (Matt. 26:26-28) As they continued eating, Jesus took a loaf, and after saying a blessing, he broke it, and giving it to the disciples, he said: “Take, eat. This means my body.” 27 And taking a cup, he offered thanks and gave it to them, saying: “Drink out of it, all of you, 28 for this means my ‘blood of the covenant,’ which is to be poured out in behalf of many for forgiveness of sins.

^ (Luke 10:40-42) Martha, on the other hand, was distracted with attending to many duties. So she came to him and said: “Lord, does it not matter to you that my sister has left me alone to attend to things? Tell her to come and help me.” 41 In answer the Lord said to her: “Martha, Martha, you are anxious and disturbed about many things. 42 A few things, though, are needed, or just one. For her part, Mary chose the good portion, and it will not be taken away from her.”

Thursday, April 9

Father, glorify me at your side with the glory that I had.—[John 17:5].

Jehovah honored Jesus in an unexpected way by resurrecting him to “a superior position” and giving him what no one else had received up until that time—immortal spirit life! ([Phil. 2:9;][1 Tim. 6:16]) What an outstanding acknowledgment of Jesus’ faithful course! What will help us to avoid seeking approval from this world? Keep close in mind that Jehovah always gives recognition to his faithful servants and that he often rewards them in unexpected ways. Who knows what unexpected blessings await us in the future? But for now, as we endure the hardships and trials of this wicked world, let us always remember that this world, is passing away. ([1 John 2:17]) Our loving Father, Jehovah, ‘is not unrighteous so as to forget our work and the love we show for his name.’—[Heb. 6:10]. w18.07 11 ¶17-18

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 15) Matthew 27:62-66 (Events after sunset: Nisan 16) [Mark 16:1]

^ (John 17:5) So now, Father, glorify me at your side with the glory that I had alongside you before the world was.

^ (Phil. 2:9) For this very reason, God exalted him to a superior position and kindly gave him the name that is above every other name,

^ (1 Tim. 6:16) the one alone having immortality, who dwells in unapproachable light, whom no man has seen or can see. To him be honor and eternal might. Amen.

^ (1 John 2:17) Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire, but the one who does the will of God remains forever.

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (Matt. 27:62-66) The next day, which was after the Preparation, the chief priests and the Pharisees gathered together before Pilate, 63 saying: “Sir, we recall what that impostor said while he was still alive, ‘After three days I am to be raised up.’ 64 Therefore, command that the grave be made secure until the third day, so that his disciples may not come and steal him and say to the people, ‘He was raised up from the dead!’ Then this last deception will be worse than the first.” 65 Pilate said to them: “You may have a guard. Go make it as secure as you know how.” 66 So they went and made the grave secure by sealing the stone and posting a guard.

^ (Mark 16:1) So when the Sabbath was over, Mary Magʹda·lene, Mary the mother of James, and Sa·loʹme bought spices in order to come and apply them to his body.

Friday, April 10

I make request . . . that they may all be one.—John 17:20, 21.

Jesus was concerned about unity during his final supper with his apostles. When praying with them, he spoke of his desire that all his disciples be one, just as he and his Father are one. Their unity would give a powerful witness, offering clear evidence that Jehovah had sent Jesus to the earth to do God’s will. Love would be a mark of Jesus’ true disciples that would contribute to their unity. (John 13:34, 35) Jesus’ emphasis on unity is understandable. He had noticed a lack of unity or harmony among the apostles, such as during his final meal with them. As had happened before, a dispute arose over “which one of them was considered to be the greatest.” (Luke 22:24-27; Mark 9:33, 34) Another time, James and John requested that Jesus give them prominent places alongside him in his Kingdom.—Mark 10:35-40. w18.06 8 ¶1-2

Memorial Bible reading: (Daytime events: Nisan 16) [Mark 16:2-8]

^ (John 17:20, 21) “I make request, not concerning these only, but also concerning those putting faith in me through their word, 21 so that they may all be one, just as you, Father, are in union with me and I am in union with you, that they also may be in union with us, so that the world may believe that you sent me.

^ (John 13:34, 35) I am giving you a new commandment, that you love one another; just as I have loved you, you also love one another. 35 By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (Luke 22:24-27) However, there also arose a heated dispute among them over which one of them was considered to be the greatest. 25 But he said to them: “The kings of the nations lord it over them, and those having authority over them are called Benefactors. 26 You, though, are not to be that way. But let the one who is the greatest among you become as the youngest, and the one taking the lead as the one ministering. 27 For which one is greater, the one dining* or the one serving? Is it not the one dining?* But I am among you as the one serving.

Or “reclining at the table.”

Or “reclining at the table.”

^ (Mark 9:33, 34) And they came into Ca·perʹna·um. Now when he was inside the house, he put the question to them: “What were you arguing about on the road?” 34 They kept silent, for on the road they had been arguing among themselves about who is greater.

^ (Mark 10:35-40) James and John, the sons of Zebʹe·dee, approached him and said to him: “Teacher, we want you to do for us whatever we ask of you.” 36 He said to them: “What do you want me to do for you?” 37 They replied: “Grant us to sit down, one at your right hand and one at your left, in your glory.” 38 But Jesus said to them: “You do not know what you are asking for. Can you drink the cup that I am drinking or be baptized with the baptism with which I am being baptized?” 39 They said to him: “We can.” At that Jesus said to them: “The cup I am drinking, you will drink, and with the baptism with which I am being baptized, you will be baptized. 40 However, to sit down at my right hand or at my left is not mine to give, but it belongs to those for whom it has been prepared.”

^ (Mark 16:2-8) And very early on the first day of the week when the sun had risen, they came to the tomb. 3 They were saying to one another: “Who will roll the stone away from the entrance of the tomb for us?” 4 But when they looked up, they saw that the stone had been rolled away, although it was very large. 5 When they entered into the tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the right side, clothed in a white robe, and they were stunned. 6 He said to them: “Do not be stunned. You are looking for Jesus the Naz·a·reneʹ who was executed on the stake. He was raised up. He is not here. Look, here is the place where they laid him. 7 But go, tell his disciples and Peter, ‘He is going ahead of you into Galʹi·lee. You will see him there, just as he told you.’” 8 So when they came out, they fled from the tomb, trembling and overwhelmed with emotion. And they said nothing to anyone, for they were in fear.

Saturday, April 11

A man will leave his father and his mother and he will stick to his wife, and they will become one flesh.—[Gen. 2:24].

Jehovah wants married couples to develop a love so strong that it lasts for life. ([Matt. 19:3-6]) Adultery is one of the most unloving crimes a person can commit. With good reason, the seventh of the Ten Commandments prohibited adultery. ([Deut. 5:18]) It is a sin “against God” and a cruel blow to a marriage mate. ([Gen. 39:7-9]) A victim of adultery might feel the pain of betrayal for decades. Jehovah also cares deeply about the welfare of children. Jehovah commanded parents to provide not only for their children’s physical needs but also for their spiritual needs. Parents were to take every opportunity to help their children appreciate Jehovah’s Law and learn to love him. ([Deut. 6:6-9;][7:13]) Parents were to view their children, not as mere property that they could neglect or mistreat, but as an inheritance, a gift from Jehovah to be cherished.—[Ps. 127:3]. w19.02 21 ¶5, 7

^ (Gen. 2:24) That is why a man will leave his father and his mother and he will stick to* his wife, and they will become one flesh.

Or “remain with.”

^ (Matt. 19:3-6) And Pharisees came to him intent on testing him, and they asked: “Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife on every sort of grounds?” 4 In reply he said: “Have you not read that the one who created them from the beginning made them male and female 5 and said: ‘For this reason a man will leave his father and his mother and will stick to his wife, and the two will be one flesh’? 6 So that they are no longer two, but one flesh. Therefore, what God has yoked together, let no man put apart.”

^ (Deut. 5:18) “‘Neither must you commit adultery.

^ (Gen. 39:7-9) Now after these things, the wife of his master began to cast her eyes on Joseph and say: “Lie down with me.” 8 But he refused and said to his master’s wife: “Here my master does not know what is with me in the house, and he has entrusted everything he has into my care. 9 There is no one greater in this house than I am, and he has not withheld from me anything at all except you, because you are his wife. So how could I commit this great badness and actually sin against God?”

^ (Deut. 6:6-9) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up. 8 Tie them as a reminder on your hand, and they must be like a headband on your forehead.* 9 Write them on the doorposts of your house and on your gates.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

Lit., “between your eyes.”

^ (Deut. 7:13) He will love you and bless you and multiply you. Yes, he will bless you with many children* and with the produce of your soil, your grain, your new wine, your oil, the calves of your herds and the lambs of your flocks, in the land that he swore to your forefathers to give to you.

Lit., “bless the fruit of your womb.”

^ (Ps. 127:3) Look! Sons* are an inheritance from Jehovah; The fruit of the womb is a reward.

Or “Children.”

Sunday, April 12

God . . . will recognize my integrity.—[Job 31:6].

Job kept his integrity by focusing on the hope that God would reward him. He believed that God did care about his integrity. Despite his trials, Job was confident that Jehovah would finally reward him. This confidence surely helped him cling to his integrity. Jehovah was so delighted with Job’s integrity that He rewarded him richly while he was still an imperfect man! (Job 42:12-17;[Jas. 5:11]) And even greater rewards lie ahead for Job. Our God has not changed. ([Mal. 3:6]) If we remember that he values our integrity, we can keep our hope for a bright future alive in our heart. (1 Thess. 5:8, 9) At times, you may feel lonely in such a course, but you will never be alone. You will be among millions of faithful integrity-keepers around the world. You will also join the ranks of men and women of faith who kept their integrity in the past, even under the threat of death.—Heb. 11:36-38;[12:1]. w19.02 7 ¶15-16

^ (Job 31:6) Let God weigh me with accurate scales; Then he will recognize my integrity.

^ (Job 42:12-17) So Jehovah blessed the last part of Job’s life more than the beginning, and Job came to have 14,000 sheep, 6,000 camels, 1,000 pairs of cattle, and 1,000 female donkeys. 13 He also came to have seven more sons and three more daughters. 14 He named the first daughter Je·miʹmah, the second Ke·ziʹah, and the third Kerʹen-hapʹpuch. 15 No women in all the land were as beautiful as Job’s daughters, and their father gave them an inheritance along with their brothers. 16 After this Job lived for 140 years, and he saw his children and his grandchildren—four generations. 17 Finally Job died, after a long and satisfying life.*

Lit., “old and full of days.”

^ (Jas. 5:11) Look! We consider happy* those who have endured. You have heard of the endurance of Job and have seen the outcome Jehovah* gave, that Jehovah* is very tender in affection* and merciful.

Or “blessed.”

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

Or “very compassionate.”

^ (Mal. 3:6) “For I am Jehovah; I do not change.* And you are sons of Jacob; you have not yet come to your finish.

Or “I have not changed.”

^ (1 Thess. 5:8, 9) But as for us who belong to the day, let us keep our senses and put on the breastplate of faith and love and the hope of salvation as a helmet 9 because God assigned us, not to wrath, but to the acquiring of salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ.

^ (Heb. 11:36-38) Yes, others received their trial by mockings and scourgings, indeed, more than that, by chains and prisons. 37 They were stoned, they were tried, they were sawn in two,* they were slaughtered by the sword, they went about in sheepskins, in goatskins, while they were in need, in tribulation, mistreated; 38 and the world was not worthy of them. They wandered about in deserts and mountains and caves and dens of the earth.

Or “sawn apart.”

^ (Heb. 12:1) So, then, because we have such a great cloud of witnesses surrounding us, let us also throw off every weight and the sin that easily entangles us, and let us run with endurance the race that is set before us,

Monday, April 13

Have unity of mind, fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.—[1 Pet. 3:8].

As the Memorial season passes, we do well to ask ourselves the following questions: ‘How can I imitate Jesus more closely in showing love? Do I think more about the needs of my fellow worshippers than about my own? Do I expect more from my brothers and sisters than they can give, or am I aware of their limitations?’ May we always imitate Jesus and show “fellow feeling.” The requirement to observe the Memorial of Christ’s death will not last much longer. When Jesus “comes” during the great tribulation, he will gather his remaining “chosen ones” to heaven, and the Memorial will cease to be commemorated. (1 Cor. 11:26;[Matt. 24:31]) Even after the Memorial meal is no longer observed, we can be sure that Jehovah’s people will fondly remember this simple meal as a symbol of the greatest humility, courage, and love ever shown by a human. w19.01 25 ¶17-19

^ (1 Pet. 3:8) Finally, all of you have unity of mind,* fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.

Or “think in agreement.”

^ (1 Cor. 11:26) For whenever you eat this loaf and drink this cup, you keep proclaiming the death of the Lord, until he comes.

^ (Matt. 24:31) And he will send out his angels with a great trumpet sound, and they will gather his chosen ones together from the four winds, from one extremity of the heavens to their other extremity.

Tuesday, April 14

You find pleasure in truth in the inner person; teach my innermost self true wisdom.—[Ps. 51:6].

Consider how our physical health illustrates the importance of who we are on the inside. First, to keep ourselves in good condition on the inside, we must choose a healthy diet, and we need to exercise regularly. Likewise, to keep ourselves in good spiritual condition, we must choose a healthy diet of spiritual food and regularly exercise our faith in Jehovah. That form of exercise involves applying what we learn and speaking about our faith. (Rom. 10:8-10;[Jas. 2:26]) Second, based on outward appearance, we might think that we are healthy even though we are actually diseased on the inside. In a similar way, based on our theocratic routine, we may think that our faith is strong, but wrong desires could be growing in us. (1 Cor. 10:12; Jas. 1:14, 15) We must remember that Satan would like to infect us with his thinking. w19.01 15 ¶4-5

^ (Ps. 51:6) Look! You find pleasure in truth in the inner person; Teach my innermost self* true wisdom.

Or “my secret self.”

^ (Rom. 10:8-10) But what does it say? “The word is near you, in your own mouth and in your own heart”; that is, “the word” of faith, which we are preaching. 9 For if you publicly declare with your mouth that Jesus is Lord, and exercise faith in your heart that God raised him up from the dead, you will be saved. 10 For with the heart one exercises faith for righteousness, but with the mouth one makes public declaration for salvation.

^ (Jas. 2:26) Indeed, just as the body without spirit* is dead, so also faith without works is dead.

Or “breath.”

^ (1 Cor. 10:12) So let the one who thinks he is standing beware that he does not fall.

^ (Jas. 1:14, 15) But each one is tried by being drawn out and enticed* by his own desire. 15 Then the desire, when it has become fertile,* gives birth to sin; in turn sin, when it has been carried out, brings forth death.

Or “caught as by bait.”

Lit., “has conceived.”

Wednesday, April 15

Go and do the same yourself.—[Luke 10:37].

We might ask ourselves: ‘Am I doing the same? Am I doing what the compassionate Samaritan did?’ (Luke 10:30-35) ‘Could I more actively display mercy and engage in positive deeds of kindness toward those who are suffering? For instance, could I offer practical help to older fellow Christians, widows, and those who are spiritually fatherless children? Can I take the initiative to “speak consolingly to those who are depressed”?’ (1 Thess. 5:14;[Jas. 1:27]) When we display mercy toward others, we enjoy the happiness that results from giving. Moreover, we know that we are pleasing Jehovah. ([Acts 20:35;][Heb. 13:16]) Regarding a person who shows consideration, King David said: “Jehovah will guard him and keep him alive. He will be pronounced happy in the earth.” ([Ps. 41:1, 2]) Giving expression to our feelings of compassion will also put us in line to receive Jehovah’s mercy, which in turn can result in our being eternally happy.—[Jas. 2:13]. w18.09 19 ¶11-12

^ (Luke 10:37) He said: “The one who acted mercifully toward him.” Jesus then said to him: “Go and do the same yourself.”

^ (Luke 10:30-35) In reply Jesus said: “A man was going down from Jerusalem to Jerʹi·cho and fell victim to robbers, who stripped him, beat him, and went off, leaving him half-dead. 31 Now by coincidence a priest was going down on that road, but when he saw him, he passed by on the opposite side. 32 Likewise, a Levite, when he came to the place and saw him, passed by on the opposite side. 33 But a certain Sa·marʹi·tan traveling the road came upon him, and at seeing him, he was moved with pity. 34 So he approached him and bandaged his wounds, pouring oil and wine on them. Then he mounted him on his own animal and brought him to an inn and took care of him. 35 The next day he took out two de·narʹi·i, gave them to the innkeeper, and said: ‘Take care of him, and whatever you spend besides this, I will repay you when I return.’

^ (1 Thess. 5:14) On the other hand, we urge you, brothers, to warn* the disorderly, speak consolingly to those who are depressed,* support the weak, be patient toward all.

Or “admonish.”

Or “those who are discouraged.” Lit., “those of little soul.”

^ (Jas. 1:27) The form of worship* that is clean and undefiled from the standpoint of our God and Father is this: to look after orphans and widows in their tribulation, and to keep oneself without spot from the world.

Or “religion.”

^ (Acts 20:35) I have shown you in all things that by working hard in this way, you must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

^ (Heb. 13:16) Moreover, do not forget to do good and to share what you have with others, for God is well-pleased with such sacrifices.

^ (Ps. 41:1, 2) Happy is anyone who shows consideration to the lowly one; Jehovah will rescue him in the day of calamity.  2 Jehovah will guard him and keep him alive. He will be pronounced happy in the earth; You will never turn him over to the will* of his enemies.

Or “desire; soul.” See Glossary.

^ (Jas. 2:13) For the one who does not practice mercy will have his judgment without mercy. Mercy triumphs over judgment.

Thursday, April 16

Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you.—[Isa. 41:10].

A faithful Christian sister named Yoshiko received bad news. Her doctor said that she had only a few months to live. How did she react? Yoshiko recalled a favorite Bible verse, today’s text. She then calmly told her doctor that she was not afraid, because Jehovah was grasping her hand. The comforting message found in that verse helped our dear sister to trust in Jehovah completely. That same verse can help us remain calm when dealing with severe trials. Initially, Jehovah had Isaiah record those words to comfort the Jews who would later be taken to Babylon as exiles. However, Jehovah had that message preserved for the benefit of not only the Jewish exiles but also all his people since that time. ([Isa. 40:8;][Rom. 15:4]) Today, we live in “critical times hard to deal with,” and more than ever, we need the encouragement found in the book of Isaiah.—[2 Tim. 3:1]. w19.01 2 ¶1-2

^ (Isa. 41:10) Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.’

^ (Isa. 40:8) The green grass dries up, The blossom withers, But the word of our God endures forever.”

^ (Rom. 15:4) For all the things that were written beforehand were written for our instruction, so that through our endurance and through the comfort from the Scriptures we might have hope.

^ (2 Tim. 3:1) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.

Friday, April 17

If the unbelieving one chooses to depart, let him depart.—[1 Cor. 7:15].

In such a separation, the two are still marriage mates and, even though living apart, would still face challenges. The apostle Paul gave this reason for staying united: “The unbelieving husband is sanctified in relation to his wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified in relation to the brother; otherwise, your children would be unclean, but now they are holy.” ([1 Cor. 7:14]) Many loyal Christians have remained with an unbelieving mate under very trying circumstances. They can testify that doing so was worthwhile in a special sense when their mate became a true worshipper. ([1 Cor. 7:16;] 1 Pet. 3:1, 2) Worldwide today, the Christian congregation abounds with successful marriages. You can likely find many happy couples in your local congregation. They are made up of loyal brothers who love their wife and devoted wives who prove to be loving mates, all showing that marriage can be honorable.—[Heb. 13:4]. w18.12 14 ¶18-19

^ (1 Cor. 7:15) But if the unbelieving one chooses to depart,* let him depart; a brother or a sister is not bound under such circumstances, but God has called you to peace.

Or “separate.”

^ (1 Cor. 7:14) For the unbelieving husband is sanctified in relation to his wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified in relation to the brother; otherwise, your children would be unclean, but now they are holy.

^ (1 Cor. 7:16) For wife, how do you know whether you will save your husband? Or, husband, how do you know whether you will save your wife?

^ (1 Pet. 3:1, 2) In the same way, you wives, be in subjection to your husbands, so that if any are not obedient to the word, they may be won without a word through the conduct of their wives, 2 because of having been eyewitnesses of your chaste conduct together with deep respect.

^ (Heb. 13:4) Let marriage be honorable among all, and let the marriage bed be without defilement, for God will judge sexually immoral people* and adulterers.

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

Saturday, April 18

Jehovah God planted a garden in Eden, . . . and there he put the man whom he had formed.—[Gen. 2:8].

Eden means “Pleasure,” and that garden was indeed pleasant. There was ample food, beautiful scenery, and delightful interaction with many animals. ([Gen. 1:29-31]) Pa·raʹdei·sos is the Greek term that translates the Hebrew word for “garden.” The Cyclopaedia by M’Clintock and Strong says about pa·raʹdei·sos: “A wide, open park, enclosed against injury, yet with its natural beauty unspoiled, with stately forest-trees, many of them bearing fruit, watered by clear streams, on whose banks roved large herds of antelopes or sheep—this was the scenery which connected itself in the mind of the Greek traveller.” (Compare Genesis 2:15, 16.) God put Adam and Eve in such a paradise, but they disqualified themselves by disobeying God. Thus, Paradise was lost for them and their offspring. (Gen. 3:23, 24) Though without human occupants, that garden apparently remained until the Deluge of Noah’s day. w18.12 3-4 ¶3-5

^ (Gen. 2:8) Further, Jehovah God planted a garden in Eʹden, toward the east; and there he put the man whom he had formed.

^ (Gen. 1:29-31) Then God said: “Here I have given to you every seed-bearing plant that is on the entire earth and every tree with seed-bearing fruit. Let them serve as food for you. 30 And to every wild animal of the earth and to every flying creature of the heavens and to everything moving on the earth in which there is life,* I have given all green vegetation for food.” And it was so. 31 After that God saw everything he had made, and look! it was very good. And there was evening and there was morning, a sixth day.

Or “life as a soul; a living soul.”

^ (Gen. 2:15, 16) Jehovah God took the man and settled him in the garden of Eʹden to cultivate it and to take care of it. 16 Jehovah God also gave this command to the man: “From every tree of the garden you may eat to satisfaction.

^ (Gen. 3:23, 24) With that Jehovah God expelled him from the garden of Eʹden to cultivate the ground from which he had been taken. 24 So he drove the man out, and he posted at the east of the garden of Eʹden the cherubs and the flaming blade of a sword that was turning continuously to guard the way to the tree of life.

Sunday, April 19

I, Jehovah, am . . . the One teaching you to benefit yourself.—[Isa. 48:17].

Parents endeavor to instill in their children good values. If the children choose to live within the values that they learned from their parents, they will be more likely to make decisions that they will not later regret. As a result, they will be free from many self-induced troubles and anxieties. Like a good parent, Jehovah wants his children to have the most fulfilling life possible. ([Isa. 48:18]) He therefore provides basic principles for moral conduct and for behavior toward others. In such matters he invites us to cultivate his very way of thinking and to share his values. Far from constraining us, this enhances, elevates, and expands our thinking ability. ([Ps. 92:5;] Prov. 2:1-5;[Isa. 55:9]) It helps us make choices that lead to happiness while still allowing us to blossom as individuals. ([Ps. 1:2, 3]) Yes, thinking like Jehovah is beneficial and desirable! w18.11 19-20 ¶7-8

^ (Isa. 48:17) This is what Jehovah says, your Repurchaser, the Holy One of Israel: “I, Jehovah, am your God, The One teaching you to benefit yourself,* The One guiding you in the way you should walk.

Or “for your own good.”

^ (Isa. 48:18) If only you would pay attention to my commandments! Then your peace would become just like a river And your righteousness like the waves of the sea.

^ (Ps. 92:5) How great your works are, O Jehovah! How very deep your thoughts are!

^ (Prov. 2:1-5) My son, if you accept my sayings And treasure up my commandments,  2 By making your ear attentive to wisdom And inclining your heart to discernment;  3 Moreover, if you call out for understanding And raise your voice for discernment;  4 If you keep seeking for it as for silver, And you keep searching for it as for hidden treasures;  5 Then you will understand the fear of Jehovah, And you will find the knowledge of God.

^ (Isa. 55:9) “For as the heavens are higher than the earth, So my ways are higher than your ways And my thoughts than your thoughts.

^ (Ps. 1:2, 3) But his delight is in the law of Jehovah, And he reads His law in an undertone* day and night.  3 He will be like a tree planted by streams of water, A tree that produces fruit in its season, The foliage of which does not wither. And everything he does will succeed.

Or “he meditates on His law.”

Monday, April 20

They speak abusively of you.—[1 Pet. 4:4].

To continue walking in the truth, we must not give in to pressure from others. When we started to walk in the truth, our relationship with non-Witness associates and family members changed. Some were tolerant; others became outright opposers. Family members, workmates, and schoolmates may try to get us to join them in their celebrations. How can we resist the pressure to conform to customs and holidays that do not honor Jehovah? We can do so by keeping Jehovah’s view of such practices clearly in mind. Reviewing discussions printed in our publications that show the origin of popular holidays can be helpful. When we remind ourselves of the Scriptural reasons for not participating in such holidays, we are convinced that we are walking in the way that “is acceptable to the Lord.” ([Eph. 5:10]) Trusting in Jehovah and his Word of truth will protect us from “trembling at men.”—[Prov. 29:25]. w18.11 11 ¶10, 12

^ (1 Pet. 4:4) They are puzzled that you do not continue running with them in the same decadent course of debauchery, so they speak abusively of you.

^ (Eph. 5:10) Keep on making sure of what is acceptable to the Lord;

^ (Prov. 29:25) Trembling at* men is* a snare, But the one trusting in Jehovah will be protected.

Or “Fear of.”

Or “lays.”

Tuesday, April 21

Jehovah was with Joseph and Jehovah made whatever he did successful.—[Gen. 39:23].

When we are faced with sudden changes, we might easily let worries about the future paralyze our life. This could have happened to Joseph. Instead, he evidently decided to make the best of his situation, thus giving Jehovah something to bless. Although in prison, Joseph worked hard to fulfill any task given him by the chief officer, just as he had done when working for Potiphar. (Gen. 39:21, 22) Like Joseph, we may find ourselves in a situation over which we have little or no control. However, if we remain patient and work hard at making the best of our circumstances, we will give Jehovah something to bless. ([Ps. 37:5]) True, we may at times feel “perplexed,” but we will never, as the apostle Paul put it, be “left in despair.” ([2 Cor. 4:8]; ftn.) These words of Paul will come true in our case, especially if we stay focused on our ministry. w18.10 29 ¶11, 13

^ (Gen. 39:23) The chief officer of the prison was looking after absolutely nothing that was in Joseph’s care, for Jehovah was with Joseph and Jehovah made whatever he did successful.

^ (Gen. 39:21, 22) But Jehovah continued with Joseph and kept showing loyal love to him and granting him favor in the eyes of the chief officer of the prison. 22 So the chief officer of the prison put Joseph in charge of all the prisoners in the prison, and everything that they were doing there, he was the one having it done.

^ (Ps. 37:5) Commit your way to* Jehovah; Rely on him, and he will act in your behalf.

Lit., “Roll your way upon.”

^ (2 Cor. 4:8) We are hard-pressed in every way, but not cramped beyond movement; we are perplexed, but not absolutely with no way out;*

Or possibly, “not left in despair.”

Wednesday, April 22

God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name.—[Heb. 6:10].

How do you feel when someone you know and respect forgets your name or, worse still, does not even recognize you? Such an experience can be very discouraging. Why? It is because each one of us has a natural desire to be accepted. The type of recognition we desire goes beyond being identified by others; we also want some acknowledgment of who we are and what we have accomplished. ([Num. 11:16]; ftn.; [Job 31:6]) Like many other natural desires, though, our desire to be appreciated can become unbalanced, distorted by our imperfections. It can make us crave inappropriate expressions of recognition. Satan’s world fuels a desire for fame and acknowledgment that distracts attention from the one who truly deserves to be recognized and worshipped, our heavenly Father, Jehovah God.—[Rev. 4:11]. w18.07 7 ¶1-2

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (Num. 11:16) Jehovah replied to Moses: “Gather for me 70 men from the elders of Israel, men whom you recognize as* elders and officials of the people, and take them to the tent of meeting, and have them stand there with you.

Or “who you know are; who are known to you as.”

^ (Job 31:6) Let God weigh me with accurate scales; Then he will recognize my integrity.

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

Thursday, April 23

The whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.—[1 John 5:19].

We are not surprised, then, that Satan and his demons would influence men in powerful positions to “speak lies.” (1 Tim. 4:1, 2) Religious leaders who lie are especially guilty because they endanger the future life prospects of those who believe their lies. If an individual accepts a false teaching and practices something that is actually condemned by God, it can cost that person his eternal life. ([Hos. 4:9]) Jesus knew that the religious leaders in his day were guilty of such deception. He told them to their face: “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you travel over sea and dry land to make one convert, and when he becomes one, you make him a subject for Gehenna [everlasting destruction] twice as much so as yourselves.” ([Matt. 23:15]; ftn.) Jesus condemned those false religious leaders in the strongest terms. They truly were ‘from their father the Devil, a murderer.’—[John 8:44]. w18.10 7 ¶5-6

^ (1 John 5:19) We know that we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.

^ (1 Tim. 4:1, 2) However, the inspired word* clearly says that in later times some will fall away from the faith, paying attention to misleading inspired statements* and teachings of demons, 2 by means of the hypocrisy of men who speak lies, whose conscience is seared as with a branding iron.

Lit., “the spirit.”

Lit., “misleading spirits.”

^ (Hos. 4:9) It will be the same for the people as for the priest; I will call them to account for their ways, And I will bring on them the consequences of their actions.

^ (Matt. 23:15) “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because you travel over sea and dry land to make one proselyte, and when he becomes one, you make him a subject for Ge·henʹna twice as much so as yourselves.

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

Friday, April 24

Happy are you when people reproach you and persecute you . . . for my sake.—[Matt. 5:11].

What did Jesus mean? He went on to say: “Rejoice and be overjoyed, since your reward is great in the heavens, for in that way they persecuted the prophets prior to you.” ([Matt. 5:12]) When the apostles were beaten and commanded to stop preaching, “they went out from before the Sanhedrin, rejoicing.” Of course, they did not relish the pain of being whipped. Yet, they rejoiced “because they had been counted worthy to be dishonored in behalf of [Jesus’] name.” ([Acts 5:41]) In our time, Jehovah’s people also endure with joy when they suffer in behalf of Jesus’ name or when they face difficult trials. ([Jas. 1:2-4]) Like the apostles, we do not take delight in any kind of suffering. But if we maintain our integrity to God during trials, Jehovah can help us to endure with fortitude. When we have the smile of approval of “the happy God,” we can be happy despite religious persecution or opposition at home.—[1 Tim. 1:11]. w18.09 21 ¶18-20

^ (Matt. 5:11) “Happy are you when people reproach* you and persecute you and lyingly say every sort of wicked thing against you for my sake.

Or “insult.”

^ (Matt. 5:12) Rejoice and be overjoyed, since your reward is great in the heavens, for in that way they persecuted the prophets prior to you.

^ (Acts 5:41) So they went out from before the Sanʹhe·drin, rejoicing because they had been counted worthy to be dishonored in behalf of his name.

^ (Jas. 1:2-4) Consider it all joy, my brothers, when you meet with various trials, 3 knowing as you do that this tested quality of your faith produces endurance. 4 But let endurance complete its work, so that you may be complete and sound in all respects, not lacking in anything.

^ (1 Tim. 1:11) according to the glorious good news of the happy God, with which I was entrusted.

Saturday, April 25

They are filled with trouble and sorrow.—[Ps. 90:10].

Because many in these “critical times” suffer from various degrees of emotional distress, countless individuals feel like just giving up. ([2 Tim. 3:1-5]) Estimates suggest that more than 800,000 people die every year from suicide—about one death every 40 seconds. Sad to say, even some Christians have succumbed to such pressures and have taken their own life. Even if our brothers and sisters do not necessarily feel like giving up, many today deal with stressful situations and need to be built up in love. Some endure persecution and ridicule. Others are the victims of criticism or backbiting at their workplace. Or they are exhausted because of working overtime or having to meet relentless deadlines. Still others deal with strength-sapping domestic problems, perhaps being the target of criticism by an unbelieving mate. As a result of these and other pressures, many in the congregation feel physically and emotionally drained. w18.09 13 ¶3, 5

^ (Ps. 90:10) The span of our life is 70 years, Or 80 if one is especially strong.* But they are filled with trouble and sorrow; They quickly pass by, and away we fly.

Or “because of special mightiness.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:1-5) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here. 2 For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal, 3 having no natural affection, not open to any agreement, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, without love of goodness, 4 betrayers, headstrong, puffed up with pride, lovers of pleasures rather than lovers of God, 5 having an appearance of godliness but proving false to its power; and from these turn away.

Sunday, April 26

No greater joy do I have than this: that I should hear that my children go on walking in the truth.—[3 John 4].

Christian parents cooperate with Jehovah when they set theocratic goals before their children. Many who have done so have later seen their sons and daughters take up full-time service assignments far from home. Some are missionaries; others pioneer where the need for publishers is greater; still others serve at Bethel. Distance might mean that families cannot get together as often as they would like to. Nevertheless, the self-sacrificing parents encourage their children to persevere in their assignments. Why? They find great joy and satisfaction in knowing that their children are putting Kingdom interests first. Perhaps many of these parents feel like Hannah, who said that she “lent” her son Samuel to Jehovah. These parents rightly view such cooperation as a precious privilege. They would not want things any other way.—[1 Sam. 1:28]. w18.08 24 ¶4

^ (3 John 4) No greater joy* do I have than this: that I should hear that my children go on walking in the truth.

Or possibly, “cause for thankfulness.”

^ (1 Sam. 1:28) I, in turn, now lend him to Jehovah. For all his days, he is lent to Jehovah.” And he* bowed down there to Jehovah.

Evidently referring to Elkanah.

Monday, April 27

It will be difficult for a rich man to enter the Kingdom of the heavens.—[Matt. 19:23].

Jesus did not say that it would be impossible. He also said: “Happy are you who are poor, for yours is the Kingdom of God.” ([Luke 6:20]) Yet, this did not mean that all poor people were specially blessed and responded to the teaching of Jesus. Many poor people did not respond. The point is, We simply cannot judge a person’s relationship with Jehovah by his material possessions. We are blessed to have many brothers and sisters, rich and poor, who love and serve Jehovah with a complete heart. The Scriptures instruct those who are rich “to place their hope, not on uncertain riches, but on God.” (1 Tim. 6:17-19) At the same time, God’s Word admonishes all of God’s people, rich and poor, to be careful not to love money. (1 Tim. 6:9, 10) Indeed, when we open our eyes and see our brothers as Jehovah sees them, we will not be tempted to judge them solely on what they have or do not have materially. w18.08 10-11 ¶11-12

^ (Matt. 19:23) Then Jesus said to his disciples: “Truly I say to you that it will be difficult for a rich man to enter the Kingdom of the heavens.

^ (Luke 6:20) And he looked up at his disciples and began to say: “Happy are you who are poor, for yours is the Kingdom of God.

^ (1 Tim. 6:17-19) Instruct* those who are rich in the present system of things* not to be arrogant,* and to place their hope, not on uncertain riches, but on God, who richly provides us with all the things we enjoy. 18 Tell them to work at good, to be rich in fine works, to be generous,* ready to share, 19 safely treasuring up for themselves a fine foundation for the future, so that they may get a firm hold on the real life.

Or “Order.”

Or “present age.” See Glossary.

Or “high-minded.”

Or “liberal.”

^ (1 Tim. 6:9, 10) But those who are determined to be rich fall into temptation and a snare and many senseless and harmful desires that plunge men into destruction and ruin. 10 For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

Wednesday, April 29

All things are lawful, but not all things are advantageous. All things are lawful, but not all things build up.—[1 Cor. 10:23].

Some individuals may feel that since some choices in life, such as education, employment, or career, are personal, they should have the freedom to choose what they please as long as their conscience permits it. Perhaps they have in mind Paul’s words to the Corinthian Christians about food: “Why should my freedom be judged by another person’s conscience?” ([1 Cor. 10:29]) While it is true that we have the freedom to make these personal choices, we need to remember that our freedom is relative and that all decisions we make have consequences. For that reason, Paul prefaced his statement with the words of today’s text. That certainly helps us to see that there are far more important factors to consider than our own preferences when it comes to exercising personal freedom in all aspects of our life. w18.04 10 ¶10

^ (1 Cor. 10:23) All things are lawful,* but not all things are advantageous. All things are lawful, but not all things build up.

Or “permissible.”

^ (1 Cor. 10:29) I do not mean your own conscience, but that of the other person. For why should my freedom be judged by another person’s conscience?

Thursday, April 30

Return to me, and I will return to you.—[Mal. 3:7].

A Christian today could be following the wrong path even while professing to worship Jehovah. ([Jude 11]) For instance, one could nurture immoral fantasies, greedy thoughts, or hateful feelings toward a fellow Christian. (1 John 2:15-17;[3:15]) This thinking can lead to sinful actions. All the while, one could be active in the ministry and regular at congregation meetings. Other humans may not be aware of our thoughts and conduct, but Jehovah sees all things and knows if we are not wholeheartedly on his side. (Jer. 17:9, 10) Even so, Jehovah is not quick to give up on us. When a person’s steps lead him away from God, Jehovah urges him: “Return to me.” Especially when we struggle with weaknesses, Jehovah wants us to take a stand against badness. ([Isa. 55:7]) If we do, he will in turn prove to be on our side by giving us the spiritual, emotional, and physical strength needed to “get the mastery over” our sinful inclinations.—[Gen. 4:7]. w18.07 18 ¶5-6

^ (Mal. 3:7) From the days of your forefathers you have turned aside from my regulations and have not kept them. Return to me, and I will return to you,” says Jehovah of armies. But you say: “How are we supposed to return?”

^ (Jude 11) Too bad for them, for they have followed the path of Cain and have rushed into the erroneous course of Baʹlaam for reward, and they have perished in the rebellious talk of Korʹah!

^ (1 John 2:15-17) Do not love either the world or the things in the world. If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him; 16 because everything in the world—the desire of the flesh and the desire of the eyes and the showy display of one’s means of life*—does not originate with the Father, but originates with the world. 17 Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire, but the one who does the will of God remains forever.

Or “the bragging about one’s possessions.”

^ (1 John 3:15) Everyone who hates his brother is a murderer,* and you know that no murderer has everlasting life remaining in him.

Or “manslayer.”

^ (Jer. 17:9, 10) The heart is more treacherous* than anything else and is desperate.* Who can know it? 10 I, Jehovah, am searching the heart, Examining the innermost thoughts,* To give to each one according to his ways, According to the fruitage of his works.

Or “deceitful.”

Or possibly, “incurable.”

Or “deepest emotions.” Lit., “kidneys.”

^ (Isa. 55:7) Let the wicked man leave his way And the evil man his thoughts; Let him return to Jehovah, who will have mercy on him, To our God, for he will forgive in a large way.*

Or “will freely forgive.”

^ (Gen. 4:7) If you turn to doing good, will you not be restored to favor?* But if you do not turn to doing good, sin is crouching at the door, and its craving is to dominate you; but will you get the mastery over it?”

Or “will there not be an exaltation?”

May

Friday, May 1

Love the foreign resident.—[Deut. 10:19].

In recent years, many countries have experienced an influx of refugees. Why not learn a greeting in the languages commonly spoken by newcomers in your area? Additionally, why not learn a few phrases that may capture their interest? You might then be able to direct them to jw.org and show them the variety of videos and publications available in their language. Jehovah lovingly provides the Life and Ministry Meeting so that we can become more effective in the field ministry. The practical instruction we receive at this meeting helps many of us feel more confident about making return visits and conducting Bible studies. Parents, help your children to let their light shine by teaching them to comment in their own words. Their simple, heartfelt expressions have sometimes prompted newly interested ones to recognize the ring of truth.—[1 Cor. 14:25]. w18.06 22-23 ¶7-9

^ (Deut. 10:19) You too must love the foreign resident, for you became foreign residents in the land of Egypt.

^ (1 Cor. 14:25) The secrets of his heart then become evident, so that he will fall facedown and worship God, declaring: “God is really among you.”

Saturday, May 2

Welcome one another, just as the Christ also welcomed you.—[Rom. 15:7].

It is good to remember that at one time we were all “strangers,” or foreigners, not close to God. ([Eph. 2:12]) But Jehovah drew us to him “with the cords of love.” ([Hos. 11:4;][John 6:44]) And Christ welcomed us. He opened the door, as it were, so that we could become part of God’s family. Since Jesus has kindly accepted us, as imperfect as we are, it should be unthinkable for us to reject anyone else! Divisions, prejudice, and hostility will doubtless increase in the world as we approach the end of this wicked system. (Gal. 5:19-21;[2 Tim. 3:13]) As servants of Jehovah, though, we seek the wisdom from above, which is impartial and promotes peace. (Jas. 3:17, 18) We rejoice as we forge friendships with people from other lands, accepting cultural differences and possibly even learning the languages of others. When we do this, peace flows just like a river, and justice like the waves of the sea.—Isa. 48:17, 18. w18.06 12 ¶18-19

^ (Rom. 15:7) So welcome one another, just as the Christ also welcomed you, with glory to God in view.

^ (Eph. 2:12) At that time you were without Christ, alienated from the state of Israel, strangers to the covenants of the promise; you had no hope and were without God in the world.

^ (Hos. 11:4) With the ropes of men* I kept drawing them, with the cords of love; And I was to them like one lifting a yoke from their jaws, And I gently brought food to each one.

Or “the ropes of kindness,” like those of a parent.

^ (John 6:44) No man can come to me unless the Father, who sent me, draws him, and I will resurrect him on the last day.

^ (Gal. 5:19-21) Now the works of the flesh are plainly seen, and they are sexual immorality,* uncleanness, brazen conduct,* 20 idolatry, spiritism,* hostility, strife, jealousy, fits of anger, dissensions, divisions, sects, 21 envy, drunkenness, wild parties,* and things like these. I am forewarning you about these things, the same way I already warned you, that those who practice such things will not inherit God’s Kingdom.

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

Or “shameless conduct.” Greek, a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

Or “sorcery; druggery.”

Or “revelries.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:13) But wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse, misleading and being misled.

^ (Jas. 3:17, 18) But the wisdom from above is first of all pure, then peaceable, reasonable, ready to obey, full of mercy and good fruits, impartial, not hypocritical. 18 Moreover, the fruit of righteousness is sown in peaceful conditions for* those who are making peace.

Or possibly, “by.”

^ (Isa. 48:17, 18) This is what Jehovah says, your Repurchaser, the Holy One of Israel: “I, Jehovah, am your God, The One teaching you to benefit yourself,* The One guiding you in the way you should walk. 18 If only you would pay attention to my commandments! Then your peace would become just like a river And your righteousness like the waves of the sea.

Or “for your own good.”

Sunday, May 3

[Have] your feet shod in readiness to declare the good news of peace.—[Eph. 6:15].

A Roman soldier who was not wearing his boots was not ready to march into battle. His sandallike boots were made of three layers of leather fastened together that gave him an excellent foothold. The design made the footwear both durable and comfortable. While the literal boots worn by Roman soldiers carried them into war, the symbolic footwear worn by Christians helps them deliver a message of peace. ([Isa. 52:7;][Rom. 10:15]) Even so, it takes courage to speak up when the opportunity arises. “I was afraid to witness to my classmates,” says 20-year-old Bo. “I think I was embarrassed. Looking back, I don’t know why I should have been. Now I’m happy to witness to my peers.” Many young ones have found that if they are well-prepared to declare the good news, they feel more comfortable doing it. w18.05 29 ¶9-11

^ (Eph. 6:15) and having your feet shod in readiness to declare the good news of peace.

^ (Isa. 52:7) How beautiful on the mountains are the feet of the one bringing good news, The one proclaiming peace, The one bringing good news of something better, The one proclaiming salvation, The one saying to Zion: “Your God has become King!”

^ (Rom. 10:15) How, in turn, will they preach unless they have been sent out? Just as it is written: “How beautiful are the feet of those who declare good news of good things!”

Monday, May 4

Keep bearing much fruit.—[John 15:8].

Jesus told his apostles: “I give you my peace.” ([John 14:27]) How does that gift—his peace—help us to bear fruit? As we endure, we experience in our heart a lasting feeling of peace that results from knowing that we have Jehovah’s and Jesus’ approval. ([Ps. 149:4;] Rom. 5:3, 4;[Col. 3:15]) After Jesus stated his desire that the joy experienced by the apostles might “be made full,” he explained to them the importance of showing self-sacrificing love. (John 15:11-13) Next, he said: “I have called you friends.” What a precious gift to receive—friendship with Jesus! What did the apostles have to do to remain his friends? They had to “go and keep bearing fruit.” (John 15:14-16) Some two years earlier, Jesus had instructed his apostles: “As you go, preach, saying: ‘The Kingdom of the heavens has drawn near.’” ([Matt. 10:7]) So on the last evening before his death, he encouraged them to endure in the work they had started.—[Matt. 24:13;][Mark 3:14]. w18.05 20-21 ¶15-16

^ (John 15:8) My Father is glorified in this, that you keep bearing much fruit and prove yourselves my disciples.

^ (John 14:27) I leave you peace; I give you my peace. I do not give it to you the way that the world gives it. Do not let your hearts be troubled nor let them shrink out of fear.

^ (Ps. 149:4) For Jehovah takes pleasure in his people. He adorns the meek with salvation.

^ (Rom. 5:3, 4) Not only that, but let us rejoice while in tribulations, since we know that tribulation produces endurance; 4 endurance, in turn, an approved condition; the approved condition, in turn, hope,

^ (Col. 3:15) Also, let the peace of the Christ rule in your hearts,* for you were called to that peace in one body. And show yourselves thankful.

Or “control your hearts.”

^ (John 15:11-13) “These things I have spoken to you, so that my joy may be in you and your joy may be made full. 12 This is my commandment, that you love one another just as I have loved you. 13 No one has love greater than this, that someone should surrender his life in behalf of his friends.

^ (John 15:14-16) You are my friends if you do what I am commanding you. 15 I no longer call you slaves, because a slave does not know what his master does. But I have called you friends, because I have made known to you all the things I have heard from my Father. 16 You did not choose me, but I chose you, and I appointed you to go and keep bearing fruit and that your fruit should remain, so that no matter what you ask the Father in my name, he may give it to you.

^ (Matt. 10:7) As you go, preach, saying: ‘The Kingdom of the heavens has drawn near.’

^ (Matt. 24:13) But the one who has endured to the end will be saved.

^ (Mark 3:14) And he formed* a group of 12, whom he also named apostles, those who were to accompany him and whom he would send out to preach

Or “appointed.”

Tuesday, May 5

Whatever a person is sowing, this he will also reap.—[Gal. 6:7].

Youths, make up your mind to focus your life on your desire to serve Jehovah. This means centering your life on spiritual goals. Other youths of your age probably center their lives on having a good time, and they will likely invite you to join them. Sooner or later you will need to show how determined you are to stick to the choices you have made. Do not be distracted by peer pressure. There are a number of ways to combat peer pressure. For instance, avoid situations that are known to be tempting. ([Prov. 22:3]) And remind yourself of the painful consequences of joining others in bad behavior. A further help is to admit your own need for advice. Humility will allow you to be open to suggestions from your parents and spiritually mature ones in the congregation. (1 Pet. 5:5, 6) Are you humble enough to accept sound advice? w18.04 28-29 ¶14-16

^ (Gal. 6:7) Do not be misled: God is not one to be mocked. For whatever a person is sowing, this he will also reap;

^ (Prov. 22:3) The shrewd one sees the danger and conceals himself, But the inexperienced keep right on going and suffer the consequences.*

Or “penalty.”

^ (1 Pet. 5:5, 6) In the same way, you younger men, be in subjection to the older men.* But all of you clothe* yourselves with humility* toward one another, because God opposes the haughty ones, but he gives undeserved kindness to the humble ones. 6 Humble yourselves, therefore, under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you in due time,

Or “the elders.”

Or “gird.”

Or “lowliness of mind.”

Wednesday, May 6

Hold fast to what you have until I come. And to the one who conquers and observes my deeds down to the end, I will give authority over the nations.—Rev. 2:25, 26.

In his messages to certain congregations of Asia Minor, Jesus expressed appreciation for the work his followers did. For example, he began his message to the congregation in Thyatira by saying: “I know your deeds, and your love and faith and ministry and endurance, and that your deeds of late are more than those you did at first.” ([Rev. 2:19]) Jesus not only mentioned their increased activity but also commended them for the qualities that motivated their good deeds. Although Jesus needed to counsel some in Thyatira, he still began and ended his message with encouragement. (Rev. 2:27, 28) Think of the authority Jesus has as head of all the congregations. He does not have to thank us for the work we do for him. Even so, he makes a point of expressing appreciation. What an excellent example he sets for elders! w19.02 16 ¶10

^ (Rev. 2:25, 26) Just the same, hold fast to what you have until I come. 26 And to the one who conquers and observes my deeds down to the end, I will give authority over the nations,

^ (Rev. 2:19) ‘I know your deeds, and your love and faith and ministry and endurance, and that your deeds of late are more than those you did at first.

^ (Rev. 2:27, 28) and he will shepherd the people with an iron rod so that they will be broken to pieces like clay vessels, just as I have received from my Father. 28 And I will give him the morning star.

Thursday, May 7

Judas and Silas . . . encouraged the brothers with many talks and strengthened them.—[Acts 15:32].

The first-century governing body proved to be a source of encouragement both to those taking the lead and to Christians in general. They sent two of their number, Peter and John, to pray for the new believers to receive holy spirit. ([Acts 8:5,][14-17]) How Philip himself as well as those he had converted must have been encouraged by this support from the governing body! Today, the Governing Body of Jehovah’s Witnesses gives encouragement to Bethel family members, to special full-time field workers, and indeed, to the entire international brotherhood of true Christians. And the result is the same as in the first century—rejoicing over the encouragement! In addition, in 2015 the Governing Body published the brochure Return to Jehovah, which has proved to be a rich source of encouragement to many throughout the world. w18.04 19 ¶18-20

^ (Acts 15:32) And Judas and Silas, since they were also prophets, encouraged the brothers with many talks and strengthened them.

^ (Acts 8:5) Now Philip went down to the city of Sa·marʹi·a and began to preach the Christ to them.

^ (Acts 8:14-17) When the apostles in Jerusalem heard that Sa·marʹi·a had accepted the word of God, they sent Peter and John to them; 15 and these went down and prayed for them to get holy spirit. 16 For it had not yet come upon any one of them, but they had only been baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus. 17 Then they laid their hands on them, and they began to receive holy spirit.

Friday, May 8

You will know the truth, and the truth will set you free.—[John 8:32].

People may think that the more freedom they have, the better off they will be, but the reality is that having unbounded freedom is a two-edged sword. We shudder to imagine what the world would be like if there were no restraints at all. For this reason, The World Book Encyclopedia states: “The laws of every organized society form a complicated pattern of balanced freedoms and restrictions.” “Complicated” is surely the right word. Just think of the volumes and volumes of laws written by man, let alone the armies of lawyers and judges needed to interpret and administer them. Jesus’ direction for gaining true freedom involves two requirements: First, accept the truth that he taught, and second, become his disciple. Doing so will lead to true freedom. But freedom from what? Jesus went on to explain: “Every doer of sin is a slave of sin. . . . If the Son sets you free, you will be truly free.”—[John 8:34,][36]. w18.04 6-7 ¶13-14

^ (John 8:32) and you will know the truth, and the truth will set you free.”

^ (John 8:34) Jesus answered them: “Most truly I say to you, every doer of sin is a slave of sin.

^ (John 8:36) So if the Son sets you free, you will be truly free.

Saturday, May 9

All of you have . . . fellow feeling.—[1 Pet. 3:8].

We enjoy being around people who care about our feelings and welfare. They try to put themselves in our place, to discern what we are thinking and feeling. They anticipate our needs and offer help—sometimes even before we ask for it. We appreciate people who show that they have “fellow feeling” for us. As Christians, we all want to show empathy, or fellow feeling. Realistically, though, we may need to work at it. Why? For one thing, we are imperfect. ([Rom. 3:23]) So we must fight the inborn tendency to think mainly of ourselves. Also, some of us may struggle to show empathy because of our upbringing or past circumstances. Finally, we could be influenced by the attitude of people around us. In these last days, many do not consider the feelings of others. Rather, they are “lovers of themselves.” (2 Tim. 3:1, 2) However, we can improve in showing fellow feeling by imitating Jehovah God and his Son, Jesus Christ. w19.03 14 ¶1-3

^ (1 Pet. 3:8) Finally, all of you have unity of mind,* fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.

Or “think in agreement.”

^ (Rom. 3:23) For all have sinned and fall short of the glory of God,

^ (2 Tim. 3:1, 2) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here. 2 For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal,

Sunday, May 10

Safeguard your heart.—[Prov. 4:23].

The last of the Ten Commandments prohibited coveting, or developing a wrong desire for what belongs to another. ([Deut. 5:21;][Rom. 7:7]) Jehovah gave this law to teach a valuable lesson—his people must guard their heart, that is, their thoughts, feelings, and reasonings. He knows that wicked acts begin as wicked thoughts and feelings. King David, for example, fell into that trap. Normally, he was a good man. But on one occasion, he coveted another man’s wife. His desire led to sin. (Jas. 1:14, 15) David committed adultery, tried to deceive the woman’s husband, and then had him killed. (2 Sam. 11:2-4;[12:7-11]) Jehovah sees beyond a person’s outward appearance. He sees what we really are inside, in our heart. ([1 Sam. 16:7]) No thought, no feeling, no action can be kept secret from him. He looks for and encourages the good in us. But he wants us to identify and control wrong thoughts before they become wrong actions.—2 Chron. 16:9; Matt. 5:27-30. w19.02 21 ¶9; 22 ¶11

^ (Prov. 4:23) Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart, For out of it are the sources of life.

^ (Deut. 5:21) “‘Neither must you desire your fellow man’s wife. Neither must you selfishly desire your fellow man’s house nor his field nor his slave man nor his slave girl nor his bull nor his donkey nor anything that belongs to your fellow man.’

^ (Rom. 7:7) What, then, are we to say? Is the Law sin? Certainly not! Really, I would not have come to know sin had it not been for the Law. For example, I would not have known covetousness if the Law had not said: “You must not covet.”

^ (Jas. 1:14, 15) But each one is tried by being drawn out and enticed* by his own desire. 15 Then the desire, when it has become fertile,* gives birth to sin; in turn sin, when it has been carried out, brings forth death.

Or “caught as by bait.”

Lit., “has conceived.”

^ (2 Sam. 11:2-4) One evening* David got up from his bed and walked around on the rooftop of the king’s house.* From the rooftop he saw a woman bathing, and the woman was very beautiful. 3 David sent someone to inquire about the woman, and he reported: “Is this not Bath-sheʹba the daughter of E·liʹam and the wife of U·riʹah the Hitʹtite?” 4 Then David sent messengers to bring her. So she came in to him, and he lay down with her. (This happened while she was purifying herself from her uncleanness.*) Afterward, she returned to her house.

Or “Late one afternoon.”

Or “palace.”

Possibly her menstrual uncleanness.

^ (2 Sam. 12:7-11) Then Nathan said to David: “You are the man! This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘I myself anointed you as king over Israel, and I rescued you from the hand of Saul. 8 I was willing to give you your master’s house and put your master’s wives in your arms, and I gave you the house of Israel and of Judah. And as if that were not enough, I was willing to do much more for you. 9 Why did you despise the word of Jehovah by doing what is bad in his eyes? You struck down U·riʹah the Hitʹtite with the sword! Then you took his wife as your wife after you killed him by the sword of the Amʹmon·ites. 10 Now a sword will never depart from your own house, because you despised me by taking the wife of U·riʹah the Hitʹtite as your wife.’ 11 This is what Jehovah says: ‘Here I am bringing against you calamity from within your own house; and before your own eyes, I will take your wives and give them to another man,* and he will lie down with your wives in broad daylight.*

Or “to your fellow man.”

Lit., “to the eyes of this sun.”

^ (1 Sam. 16:7) But Jehovah said to Samuel: “Do not pay attention to his appearance and how tall he is, for I have rejected him. For the way man sees is not the way God sees, because mere man sees what appears to the eyes, but Jehovah sees into the heart.”

^ (2 Chron. 16:9) For the eyes of Jehovah are roving about through all the earth to show his strength* in behalf of those whose heart is complete toward* him. You have acted foolishly in this matter; from now on there will be wars against you.”

Or “support.”

Or “completely devoted to.”

^ (Matt. 5:27-30) “You heard that it was said: ‘You must not commit adultery.’ 28 But I say to you that everyone who keeps on looking at a woman so as to have a passion for her has already committed adultery with her in his heart. 29 If, now, your right eye is making you stumble, tear it out and throw it away from you. For it is better for you to lose one of your members than for your whole body to be pitched into Ge·henʹna. 30 Also, if your right hand is making you stumble, cut it off and throw it away from you. For it is better for you to lose one of your members than for your whole body to land in Ge·henʹna.

Monday, May 11

Seek Jehovah, all you meek ones of the earth . . . Seek meekness.—[Zeph. 2:3].

The Bible describes Moses as being “by far the meekest of all the men on the face of the earth.” ([Num. 12:3]) Does this mean that he was weak, indecisive, and afraid of confrontations? That is how some might describe a meek person. But such an idea is far from the truth. Moses was a strong, decisive, and courageous servant of God. With Jehovah’s help, he confronted the mighty ruler of Egypt, led perhaps 3,000,000 people through a desert, and helped the nation of Israel conquer their enemies. We do not face the challenges that Moses overcame, but each day we must deal with people or situations that make it difficult to be meek. However, we have a powerful incentive to develop this quality. Jehovah promises that “the meek will possess the earth.” ([Ps. 37:11]) Would you describe yourself as being meek? Would others describe you that way? w19.02 8 ¶1-2

^ (Zeph. 2:3) Seek Jehovah, all you meek ones* of the earth, Who observe his righteous decrees.* Seek righteousness, seek meekness.* Probably* you will be concealed on the day of Jehovah’s anger.

Or “humble ones.”

Lit., “his judgment.”

Or “humility.”

Or “It may be that.”

^ (Num. 12:3) Now the man Moses was by far the meekest of all the men* on the face of the earth.

Or “was very humble (mild-tempered), more so than any other man.”

^ (Ps. 37:11) But the meek will possess the earth, And they will find exquisite delight in the abundance of peace.

Tuesday, May 12

Woe to those who say that . . . bad is good.—[Isa. 5:20].

Humans have had a conscience ever since man has been on the earth. After Adam and Eve broke Jehovah’s law, they hid themselves. This indicates that their conscience was bothering them. Those with a poorly trained conscience can be likened to a ship that is navigating with a defective compass. Setting off on a journey without an accurate compass can be treacherous. The winds and currents of the ocean can easily throw a ship off course. A properly calibrated compass can help the captain to keep the ship on course. Our conscience can be likened to a moral compass. It is an inner sense of right or wrong that can guide us in the right direction. But in order for our conscience to be an effective guide, it must be properly adjusted, or calibrated. When a person’s conscience is not properly trained, it does not act as a restraint from wrongdoing. (1 Tim. 4:1, 2) Such a conscience might even convince us that “bad is good.” w18.06 16 ¶1-3

^ (Isa. 5:20) Woe to those who say that good is bad and bad is good, Those who substitute darkness for light and light for darkness, Those who put bitter for sweet and sweet for bitter!

^ (1 Tim. 4:1, 2) However, the inspired word* clearly says that in later times some will fall away from the faith, paying attention to misleading inspired statements* and teachings of demons, 2 by means of the hypocrisy of men who speak lies, whose conscience is seared as with a branding iron.

Lit., “the spirit.”

Lit., “misleading spirits.”

Wednesday, May 13

Stop being molded by this system of things.—[Rom. 12:2].

We do well to recognize and reject worldly thinking when it is presented in less obvious ways. For example, a news report might be angled in such a way so as to favor certain political opinions. A human interest story might advance the world’s view of human goals and achievements. Some movies and books promote the “me first” and “family first” philosophies, making them seem reasonable, appealing, even right. Such viewpoints overlook the Scriptural view that our families and self-worth thrive when we love Jehovah above all. (Matt. 22:36-39) This does not mean that it is wrong to enjoy wholesome entertainment. Still, we do well to ask ourselves these questions: ‘Do we recognize the world’s teachings even when they are promoted indirectly? Do we limit our children’s exposure—and even our own—to certain programs or reading material? Do we counteract worldly ideas heard or seen by our children with Jehovah’s view of matters?’ w18.11 22 ¶18-19

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

^ (Matt. 22:36-39) “Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the Law?” 37 He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind.’ 38 This is the greatest and first commandment. 39 The second, like it, is this: ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’

Thursday, May 14

Do not be afraid, for I am with you.—[Isa. 41:10].

Jehovah shows that he is with us by giving us his full attention and his warm affection. Note how he expresses his tender and deep feelings for us. “You became precious in my eyes,” says Jehovah. “You were honored, and I have loved you.” ([Isa. 43:4]) No force in the universe can make Jehovah abandon his love for those who serve him; his loyalty to us is unshakable. ([Isa. 54:10]) Jehovah does not promise to remove the challenges that make life difficult, but he will not allow “the rivers” of problems to drown us or “the flame” of trials to do us any permanent damage. He guarantees that he will be with us, helping us to “pass through” those challenges. What will Jehovah do? He will help quiet our fears so that we can maintain our integrity to him, even if we face death. ([Isa. 41:13;][43:2]) When we trust in God’s promise “I will be with you,” we too will be courageous and strong as we endure trials. w19.01 3 ¶4-6

^ (Isa. 41:10) Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.’

^ (Isa. 43:4) For you became precious in my eyes, You were honored, and I have loved you. So I will give people in place of you And nations in exchange for your life.*

Or “soul.”

^ (Isa. 54:10) For the mountains may be removed And the hills may be shaken, But my loyal love will not be removed from you, Nor will my covenant of peace be shaken,” says Jehovah, the One having mercy on you.

^ (Isa. 41:13) For I, Jehovah your God, am grasping your right hand, The One saying to you, ‘Do not be afraid. I will help you.’

^ (Isa. 43:2) When you pass through the waters, I will be with you, And through the rivers, they will not flood over you. When you walk through the fire, you will not be scorched, Nor will the flame singe you.

Friday, May 15

Many are the plans in a man’s heart, but the counsel of Jehovah is what will prevail.—[Prov. 19:21].

If you are a young person, you may have been encouraged by teachers, guidance counselors, or others to pursue higher education and a lucrative career. Jehovah, however, advises you to take a different course. To be sure, he wants you to work hard while you are at school so that you are able to earn a living after you graduate. ([Col. 3:23]) But when you are deciding on your priorities in life, he encourages you to be guided by sound principles that take into account his purpose and his will for us during this time of the end. ([Matt. 24:14]) Jehovah knows what lies ahead for the present world, and he knows how soon its end will come. ([Isa. 46:10;][Matt. 24:3,][36]) He also knows us—what gives us true satisfaction and happiness as well as what leads us to disappointment and unhappiness. So no matter how reasonable human advice may seem, if it does not take God’s Word into account, it is not wisdom at all. w18.12 19 ¶1-2

^ (Prov. 19:21) Many are the plans in a man’s heart, But the counsel* of Jehovah is what will prevail.

Or “purpose.”

^ (Col. 3:23) Whatever you are doing, work at it whole-souled* as for Jehovah,* and not for men,

See Glossary, “Soul.”

See App. A5.

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Isa. 46:10) From the beginning I foretell the outcome, And from long ago the things that have not yet been done. I say, ‘My decision* will stand, And I will do whatever I please.’

Or “purpose; counsel.”

^ (Matt. 24:3) While he was sitting on the Mount of Olives, the disciples approached him privately, saying: “Tell us, when will these things be, and what will be the sign of your presence and of the conclusion of the system of things?”

^ (Matt. 24:36) “Concerning that day and hour nobody knows, neither the angels of the heavens nor the Son, but only the Father.

Saturday, May 16

The wicked will be no more.—[Ps. 37:10].

Instead, “the meek will possess the earth, and they will find exquisite delight in the abundance of peace.” David was also inspired to predict: “The righteous will possess the earth, and they will live forever on it.” ([Ps. 37:11,][29;][2 Sam. 23:2]) What effect do you think those assurances had on people who wanted to do God’s will? They would have a basis for expecting that if only righteous people were living on earth, in time a paradise like the garden of Eden would be restored. Over time, most Israelites claiming to serve Jehovah turned their backs on him and on true worship. So God let the Babylonians conquer his people, ruin their land, and carry many of them into exile. (2 Chron. 36:15-21; Jer. 4:22-27) Still, God’s prophets foretold that after 70 years, his people would return to their homeland. Those prophecies were fulfilled. But they also have meaning for us—a coming paradise on earth. w18.12 4 ¶9-10

^ (Ps. 37:10) Just a little while longer, and the wicked will be no more; You will look at where they were, And they will not be there.

^ (Ps. 37:11) But the meek will possess the earth, And they will find exquisite delight in the abundance of peace.

^ (Ps. 37:29) The righteous will possess the earth, And they will live forever on it.

^ (2 Sam. 23:2) The spirit of Jehovah spoke through me; His word was on my tongue.

^ (2 Chron. 36:15-21) Jehovah the God of their forefathers kept warning them by means of his messengers, warning them again and again, because he felt compassion for his people and for his dwelling place. 16 But they kept ridiculing the messengers of the true God, and they despised his words and mocked his prophets, until the rage of Jehovah came up against his people, until they were beyond healing. 17 So he brought against them the king of the Chal·deʹans, who killed their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary; he felt no compassion for young man or virgin, old or infirm. God gave everything into his hand. 18 All the utensils of the house of the true God, great and small, as well as the treasures of the house of Jehovah and the treasures of the king and his princes, everything he brought to Babylon. 19 He burned down the house of the true God, tore down the wall of Jerusalem, burned all its fortified towers with fire, and destroyed everything of value. 20 He carried off captive to Babylon those who escaped the sword, and they became servants to him and his sons until the kingdom* of Persia began to reign, 21 to fulfill Jehovah’s word spoken by Jeremiah, until the land had paid off its sabbaths. All the days it lay desolate it kept sabbath, to fulfill 70 years.

Or “royalty.”

^ (Jer. 4:22-27) “For my people are foolish; They take no note of me. They are stupid sons, with no understanding. They are clever* enough when it comes to doing bad, But they do not know how to do good.” 23 I saw the land, and look! it was empty and desolate. I looked at the heavens, and their light was no more. 24 I saw the mountains, and look! they were quaking, And the hills were shaking. 25 I saw, and look! there was no man, And the birds of the heavens had all fled. 26 I saw, and look! the orchard had become a wilderness, And its cities had all been torn down. It was because of Jehovah, Because of his burning anger. 27 For this is what Jehovah says: “The whole land will become desolate, But I will not carry out a complete extermination.

Or “wise.”

Sunday, May 17

As the heavens are higher than the earth, so my ways are higher than your ways and my thoughts than your thoughts.—[Isa. 55:9].

Much worldly advice is in conflict with the Scriptures. Still, might some of it be more suited to our times? “Wisdom is proved righteous by its works,” said Jesus. ([Matt. 11:19]) The world has made considerable advancement in technology; however, it has been unable to solve the major problems that stand in the way of happiness, such as war, racism, and crime. And what of its lenient view of morality? Many people acknowledge that this is, not solving, but contributing to family breakdown, illness, and other troubles. On the other hand, Christians who adopt God’s viewpoint are enjoying improved family relationships, the healthful benefits of moral cleanness, and peace among fellow believers on a worldwide scale. ([Isa. 2:4;] Acts 10:34, 35; 1 Cor. 6:9-11) Does this not show that Jehovah’s thinking is superior to that of the world? w18.11 20 ¶8-10

^ (Isa. 55:9) “For as the heavens are higher than the earth, So my ways are higher than your ways And my thoughts than your thoughts.

^ (Matt. 11:19) The Son of man did come eating and drinking, but people say, ‘Look! A man who is a glutton and is given to drinking wine, a friend of tax collectors and sinners.’ All the same, wisdom is proved righteous* by its works.”*

Or “is vindicated.”

Or “by its results.”

^ (Isa. 2:4) He will render judgment among the nations And set matters straight* respecting many peoples. They will beat their swords into plowshares And their spears into pruning shears. Nation will not lift up sword against nation, Nor will they learn war anymore.

Or “correct matters.”

^ (Acts 10:34, 35) At this Peter began to speak, and he said: “Now I truly understand that God is not partial, 35 but in every nation the man who fears him and does what is right is acceptable to him.

^ (1 Cor. 6:9-11) Or do you not know that unrighteous people will not inherit God’s Kingdom? Do not be misled.* Those who are sexually immoral,* idolaters, adulterers, men who submit to homosexual acts, men who practice homosexuality,* 10 thieves, greedy people, drunkards, revilers,* and extortioners will not inherit God’s Kingdom. 11 And yet that is what some of you were. But you have been washed clean; you have been sanctified; you have been declared righteous in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ and with the spirit of our God.

Or “deceived.”

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

Or “men who have sex with men.” Lit., “men who lie with men.”

Or “the verbally abusive.”

Monday, May 18

Bad associations spoil useful habits.—[1 Cor. 15:33].

Although we endeavor to have good relations with family members and treat them kindly, we must be careful not to compromise the truth to please them. While we will continue to try to get along well with family members, we will have close friendships only with those who love Jehovah. All who walk in the truth must be holy. ([Isa. 35:8;] 1 Pet. 1:14-16) When coming into the truth, all of us had to make adjustments to conform to the Bible’s righteous standards. Some had to undergo major changes. Whichever the case, we must never trade our pure, holy condition for the immoral filth of this world. How can we avoid succumbing to immoral conduct? Reflect on the high price that Jehovah paid in order for us to be holy—the precious blood of his Son, Jesus Christ. (1 Pet. 1:18, 19) To maintain our clean standing before Jehovah, we need to keep the value of Jesus’ ransom sacrifice foremost in our mind and heart. w18.11 11 ¶10-11

^ (1 Cor. 15:33) Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.*

Or “corrupt good morals.”

^ (Isa. 35:8) And a highway will be there, Yes, a way called the Way of Holiness. The unclean one will not travel on it. It is reserved for the one walking on the way; No one foolish will stray onto it.

^ (1 Pet. 1:14-16) As obedient children, stop being molded by* the desires you formerly had in your ignorance, 15 but like the Holy One who called you, become holy yourselves in all your conduct, 16 for it is written: “You must be holy, because I am holy.”

Or “fashioned after.”

^ (1 Pet. 1:18, 19) For you know that it was not with corruptible things, with silver or gold, that you were set free* from your futile way of life handed down to you by your forefathers.* 19 But it was with precious blood, like that of an unblemished and spotless lamb, that of Christ.

Lit., “you were ransomed; you were redeemed.”

Or “by tradition.”

Tuesday, May 19

I will show a waiting attitude for the God of my salvation. My God will hear me.—[Mic. 7:7].

Many full-time servants can testify that focusing on the ministry helped them to maintain their balance despite changing circumstances. As their examples show, if we make the best of our circumstances and wait confidently on Jehovah, we will maintain our inner peace. We may even realize that we have derived much spiritual benefit from adjusting to a new set of circumstances. If life takes an unexpected turn—whether as a result of a change in our theocratic assignments, health problems, or new family responsibilities—be assured that Jehovah cares for you and will help you at the right time. ([Heb. 4:16;] 1 Pet. 5:6, 7) In the meantime, try to make the best of your situation. Draw close to your heavenly Father through prayer, and learn to leave yourself in his caring hands. In this way, you too will maintain inner peace despite changing circumstances. w18.10 30 ¶17; 31 ¶19, 22

^ (Mic. 7:7) But as for me, I will keep on the lookout for Jehovah. I will show a waiting attitude* for the God of my salvation. My God will hear me.

Or “I will wait patiently.”

^ (Heb. 4:16) Let us, then, approach the throne of undeserved kindness with freeness of speech, so that we may receive mercy and find undeserved kindness to help us at the right time.

^ (1 Pet. 5:6, 7) Humble yourselves, therefore, under the mighty hand of God, so that he may exalt you in due time, 7 while you throw all your anxiety* on him, because he cares for you.

Or “cares; worries.”

Wednesday, May 20

[Jehovah] well knows how we are formed, remembering that we are dust.—[Ps. 103:14].

The Bible provides many examples of the considerate way in which Jehovah deals with his servants. For instance, note the thoughtful way that God helped young Samuel to deliver a judgment message to High Priest Eli as recorded at 1 Samuel 3:1-18. Jehovah’s Law commanded children to respect the aged, especially a chieftain. ([Ex. 22:28;][Lev. 19:32]) Can you imagine Samuel going up to Eli in the morning and boldly telling him God’s stinging judgment message? Of course not! Indeed, the account tells us that Samuel “was afraid to tell Eli of the vision.” However, God made clear to Eli that He was calling Samuel. As a result, Eli took charge of the situation and told Samuel to speak and not to hide “a single word.” Samuel obediently “told him everything,” and his words harmonized with an earlier message. (1 Sam. 2:27-36) The account involving Samuel and Eli shows us how considerate and wise Jehovah is. w18.09 23 ¶2; 24 ¶4-5

^ (Ps. 103:14) For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust.

^ (Ex. 22:28) “You must not curse* God nor curse a chieftain* among your people.

Or “revile.”

Or “ruler.”

^ (Lev. 19:32) “‘Before gray hair you should rise up, and you must show honor to an older man, and you must be in fear of your God. I am Jehovah.

^ (1 Sam. 2:27-36) A man of God came to Eʹli and said to him: “This is what Jehovah says: ‘Did I not plainly reveal myself to your father’s house while they were in Egypt as slaves to the house of Pharʹaoh? 28 And he was chosen out of all the tribes of Israel to serve as my priest and to go up on my altar to make sacrifices, to offer incense,* and to bear an ephʹod before me; and I gave to the house of your forefather all the offerings made by fire of the Israelites.* 29 Why do you men scorn* my sacrifice and my offering that I have commanded in my place of dwelling? Why do you keep honoring your sons more than me by fattening yourselves from the best portions of every offering of my people Israel? 30 “‘That is why the word of Jehovah the God of Israel is: “I did indeed say that your house and the house of your forefather would always walk before me.” But now Jehovah declares: “It is unthinkable, on my part, because those honoring me I will honor, but those despising me will be treated with contempt.” 31 Look! Days are coming when I will cut off your strength* and that of your father’s house, so that no man in your house will live to old age. 32 And you will look upon a rival in my dwelling amid all the good that is done to Israel, and never again will there be an old man in your house. 33 The man of yours whom I do not cut off from serving at my altar will cause your eyes to fail and will bring you grief,* but the greater number of your house will die by the sword of men. 34 And what happens to your two sons, Hophʹni and Phinʹe·has, will be the sign for you: On one day both of them will die. 35 Then I will raise up for myself a faithful priest. He will act in harmony with what is my heart’s desire;* and I will build for him a lasting house, and he will walk before my anointed one always. 36 Anyone who remains in your house will come and bow down to him for the payment of money and a loaf of bread, and will say: “Assign me, please, to one of the priestly offices to eat a piece of bread.”’”

Or possibly, “to make sacrificial smoke billow up.”

Lit., “sons of Israel.”

Lit., “kick at.”

Lit., “arm.”

Or “will cause your soul to pine away.”

Or “is in my heart and in my soul.”

Thursday, May 21

O Jehovah, who may be a guest in your tent? . . . The one who is . . . speaking the truth in his heart.—[Ps. 15:1, 2].

Spreading lies has become commonplace in today’s society. As stated in the article “Why We Lie” by Y. Bhattacharjee, “lying has come to be recognized as a deeply ingrained human trait.” People often resort to lying either to protect themselves or to promote themselves. They lie to cover up their mistakes and misdeeds or to gain economic and personal advantages. As the article states, there are people who “lie with ease, in ways big and small, to strangers, co-workers, friends, and loved ones.” What is the result of all this lying? Trust is lost and relationships can be ruined. The psalmist David prayed to Jehovah: “You find pleasure in truth in the inner person.” ([Ps. 51:6]) David knew that our being truthful comes from the inside, from our heart. In every aspect of life, true Christians “speak the truth with one another.”—[Zech. 8:16]. w18.10 7 ¶4; 8 ¶9-10; 10 ¶19

^ (Ps. 15:1, 2) O Jehovah, who may be a guest in your tent? Who may reside in your holy mountain?  2 The one who is walking faultlessly,* Practicing what is right And speaking the truth in his heart.

Or “with integrity.”

^ (Ps. 51:6) Look! You find pleasure in truth in the inner person; Teach my innermost self* true wisdom.

Or “my secret self.”

^ (Zech. 8:16) “‘These are the things you should do: Speak the truth with one another, and the judgments in your gates must promote truth and peace.

Friday, May 22

He led them in security, and they felt no fear.—[Ps. 78:53].

When the Israelites left Egypt in 1513 B.C.E., they may have numbered more than three million. Spanning three or even four generations, there were children, elderly ones, and no doubt some who were infirm or disabled. To lead such a vast crowd out of Egypt certainly called for an understanding and thoughtful Leader. Jehovah, by means of Moses, proved to be such. As a result, the Israelites felt safe as they left the only home they had ever known. ([Ps. 78:52]) How did Jehovah make his people feel safe and secure? For one thing, he led them out of Egypt in well-organized “battle formation.” ([Ex. 13:18]) Such organization surely reassured the Israelites that their God was in control. Also, Jehovah made his presence visibly manifest by means of “a cloud by day and . . . the light of a fire” at night. ([Ps. 78:14]) In effect, Jehovah was saying: “Do not be afraid. I am with you to guide and protect you.” w18.09 26 ¶11-12

^ (Ps. 78:53) He led them in security, And they felt no fear; The sea covered their enemies.

^ (Ps. 78:52) Then he brought his people out like a flock And guided them like a drove in the wilderness.

^ (Ex. 13:18) So God made the people go around by the way of the wilderness of the Red Sea. But it was in battle formation that the Israelites went up out of the land of Egypt.

^ (Ps. 78:14) He led them with a cloud by day And the whole night with the light of a fire.

Saturday, May 23

O that in the Grave you would conceal me, . . . that you would set a time limit for me and remember me.—[Job 14:13].

Back in Bible times, some of God’s faithful servants were so overwhelmed by their circumstances that they felt that they wanted to die. For example, pain-ridden Job lamented: “I loathe my life; I do not want to go on living.” ([Job 7:16]) Jonah was so disappointed with the way things had turned out in his assignment that he said: “Now, O Jehovah, please take away my life, for it is better for me to die than to live.” ([Jonah 4:3]) Also, at one point the faithful prophet Elijah felt so affected by his situation that he asked that he might die. He said: “It is enough! Now, O Jehovah, take my life away.” ([1 Ki. 19:4]) However, Jehovah valued those devoted servants and wanted them to live. Instead of condemning how they felt, he helped them to overcome their desire to die and built them up in love so that they could continue serving him faithfully. w18.09 13 ¶4

^ (Job 14:13) O that in the Grave* you would conceal me, That you would hide me until your anger passes by, That you would set a time limit for me and remember me!

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ (Job 7:16) I loathe my life; I do not want to go on living. Leave me alone, for my days are like a breath.

^ (Jonah 4:3) Now, O Jehovah, please take away my life,* for it is better for me to die than to live.”

Or “soul.”

^ (1 Ki. 19:4) He went a day’s journey into the wilderness and came and sat down under a broom tree, and he asked that he* might die. He said: “It is enough! Now, O Jehovah, take my life* away, for I am no better than my forefathers.”

Or “his soul.”

Or “soul.”

Sunday, May 24

We are God’s fellow workers.—[1 Cor. 3:9].

God’s fellow workers are noted for practicing hospitality. In the Christian Greek Scriptures, the term translated “hospitality” means “kindness to strangers.” ([Heb. 13:2]; ftn.) God’s Word recounts events that teach us to show such love. ([Gen. 18:1-5]) We can and should seize opportunities to help others regularly, whether they are “related to us in the faith” or not. ([Gal. 6:10]) Can you work with God by showing hospitality to visiting full-time servants? ([3 John 5,][8]) Such occasions often provide an opportunity for “an interchange of encouragement.” (Rom. 1:11, 12) God’s Word encourages men in the congregation to work with Jehovah by reaching out for privileges of service and oversight. ([1 Tim. 3:1,][8, 9;] 1 Pet. 5:2, 3) Those who do so want to assist others in both practical and spiritual matters. ([Acts 6:1-4]) And those who care for necessary congregation duties will tell you that it is most enjoyable to assist others. w18.08 24 ¶6-7; 25 ¶10

^ (1 Cor. 3:9) For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

^ (Heb. 13:2) Do not forget hospitality,* for through it some unknowingly entertained angels.

Or “kindness to strangers.”

^ (Gen. 18:1-5) Afterward, Jehovah appeared to him among the big trees of Mamʹre while he was sitting at the entrance of the tent during the hottest part of the day. 2 He looked up and saw three men standing some distance from him. When he saw them, he ran from the entrance of the tent to meet them, and he bowed down to the ground. 3 Then he said: “Jehovah, if I have found favor in your eyes, please do not pass by your servant. 4 Please, let a little water be brought and have your feet washed; then recline under the tree. 5 Seeing that you have come here to your servant, let me bring a piece of bread so that you may refresh yourselves.* Then you may go on your way.” At this they said: “All right. You may do as you have spoken.”

Lit., “strengthen your heart.”

^ (Gal. 6:10) So, then, as long as we have the opportunity,* let us work what is good toward all, but especially toward those related to us in the faith.

Lit., “appointed time.”

^ (3 John 5) Beloved one, you show your faithfulness in what you do for the brothers, even though they are strangers to you.

^ (3 John 8) So we are under obligation to show hospitality to such ones, so that we may become fellow workers in the truth.

^ (Rom. 1:11, 12) For I am longing to see you, that I may impart some spiritual gift to you for you to be made firm; 12 or, rather, that we may have an interchange of encouragement by one another’s faith, both yours and mine.

^ (1 Tim. 3:1) This statement is trustworthy: If a man is reaching out to be an overseer, he is desirous of a fine work.

^ (1 Tim. 3:8, 9) Ministerial servants should likewise be serious, not double-tongued,* not indulging in a lot of wine, not greedy of dishonest gain, 9 holding the sacred secret of the faith with a clean conscience.

Or “not deceitful in speech.”

^ (1 Pet. 5:2, 3) Shepherd the flock of God under your care, serving as overseers,* not under compulsion, but willingly before God; not for love of dishonest gain, but eagerly; 3 not lording it over those who are God’s inheritance, but becoming examples to the flock.

Or “carefully watching over it.”

^ (Acts 6:1-4) Now in those days when the disciples were increasing, the Greek-speaking Jews began complaining against the Hebrew-speaking Jews, because their widows were being overlooked in the daily distribution. 2 So the Twelve called the multitude of the disciples together and said: “It is not right for us to leave the word of God to distribute food to tables. 3 So, brothers, select for yourselves seven reputable men from among you, full of spirit and wisdom, that we may appoint them over this necessary matter; 4 but we will devote ourselves to prayer and to the ministry of the word.”

Monday, May 25

Do not severely criticize an older man. On the contrary, appeal to him as a father.—[1 Tim. 5:1].

Although Timothy had a measure of authority over such older brothers, he was to treat them with compassion and respect. However, how far would we take that principle? For example, should we feel obligated to defer to someone older if he is willfully sinning or is advocating something displeasing to Jehovah? Jehovah will not judge by the outward appearance and will not excuse a willful sinner simply because he is older. Note the principle found at [Isaiah 65:20]: “The sinner will be cursed, even though he is a hundred years of age.” A similar principle is demonstrated in Ezekiel’s vision. ([Ezek. 9:5-7]) Thus, our main concern must always be to show respect for the Ancient of Days, Jehovah God. (Dan. 7:9, 10,[13, 14]) If we do so, we will not be afraid to correct a person needing counsel, regardless of his age.—[Gal. 6:1]. w18.08 11 ¶13-14

^ (1 Tim. 5:1) Do not severely criticize an older man. On the contrary, appeal to him as a father, to younger men as brothers,

^ (Isa. 65:20) “No more will there be an infant from that place who lives but a few days, Nor an old man who fails to live out his days. For anyone who dies at a hundred will be considered a mere boy, And the sinner will be cursed, even though he is a hundred years of age.*

Or possibly, “And the one who falls short of a hundred will be considered cursed.”

^ (Ezek. 9:5-7) And to the others he said in my hearing: “Go through the city after him and strike. Do not let your eye feel sorry, and do not feel any compassion. 6 Old man, young man, virgin, little child, and women you should kill off completely. But do not go near to any man on whom there is the mark. You should start from my sanctuary.” So they started with the elders who were in front of the house. 7 Then he said to them: “Defile the house and fill the courtyards with the slain. Go!” So they went out and struck down people in the city.

^ (Dan. 7:9, 10) “I kept watching until thrones were set in place and the Ancient of Days sat down. His clothing was white like snow, and the hair of his head was like clean wool. His throne was flames of fire; its wheels were a burning fire. 10 A stream of fire was flowing and going out from before him. A thousand thousands kept ministering to him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him. The Court took its seat, and books were opened.

^ (Dan. 7:13, 14) “I kept watching in the visions of the night, and look! with the clouds of the heavens, someone like a son of man was coming; and he gained access to the Ancient of Days, and they brought him up close before that One. 14 And to him there were given rulership, honor, and a kingdom, that the peoples, nations, and language groups should all serve him. His rulership is an everlasting rulership that will not pass away, and his kingdom will not be destroyed.

^ (Gal. 6:1) Brothers, even if a man takes a false step before he is aware of it, you who have spiritual qualifications try to readjust such a man in a spirit of mildness. But keep an eye on yourself, for fear you too may be tempted.

Tuesday, May 26

The naive person believes every word, but the shrewd one ponders each step.—[Prov. 14:15].

As true Christians, we need to develop the ability to evaluate information and reach accurate conclusions. (Prov. 3:21-23;[8:4, 5]) If we do not cultivate this ability, we will be far more vulnerable to the efforts of Satan and his world to distort our thinking. ([Eph. 5:6;][Col. 2:8]) Of course, only if we have the facts can we reach right conclusions. Today, people are bombarded with information. Internet websites, television, and other mass media present a seemingly unending array of ideas. Many people are also flooded with e-mails, text messages, and reports from well-meaning friends and acquaintances. Since the deliberate spreading of wrong information and the distorting of facts are common, we have good reason to be cautious and to evaluate carefully what we hear. w18.08 3 ¶1, 3

^ (Prov. 14:15) The naive* person believes every word, But the shrewd one ponders each step.

Or “inexperienced.”

^ (Prov. 3:21-23) My son, do not lose sight of them.* Safeguard practical wisdom and thinking ability; 22 They will give you* life And be an adornment for your neck; 23 Then you will walk on your way in safety, And your foot will never stumble.*

Evidently referring to God’s qualities mentioned in the previous verses.

Or “your soul.”

Or “strike against anything.”

^ (Prov. 8:4, 5) “To you, O people, I am calling; I raise my voice to everyone.*  5 You inexperienced ones, learn shrewdness; You stupid ones, acquire an understanding heart.*

Lit., “to the sons of men.”

Lit., “understand heart.”

^ (Eph. 5:6) Let no man deceive you with empty words, for because of such things the wrath of God is coming upon the sons of disobedience.

^ (Col. 2:8) Look out that no one takes you captive* by means of the philosophy and empty deception according to human tradition, according to the elementary things of the world and not according to Christ;

Or “carries you off as his prey.”

Wednesday, May 27

You have found favor with God.—[Luke 1:30].

When it came time for God’s Son to be born as a human, Jehovah selected a humble virgin girl, Mary, to be the mother of this special child. Mary lived in the insignificant city of Nazareth, far from Jerusalem and its magnificent temple. ([Luke 1:26-33]) Mary revealed her deep spirituality when she later spoke to her relative Elizabeth. ([Luke 1:46-55]) Yes, Jehovah had been observing Mary, and he granted her this unexpected privilege because of her faithfulness. When Mary eventually gave birth to Jesus, Jehovah did not honor any of the prominent officials or rulers in Jerusalem and Bethlehem by letting them know what had happened. Angels appeared to lowly shepherds who were caring for sheep in the fields outside Bethlehem. ([Luke 2:8-14]) These shepherds then visited the newborn baby. ([Luke 2:15-17]) How pleasantly surprised Mary and Joseph must have been to see Jesus honored in such a manner! w18.07 9-10 ¶11-12

^ (Luke 1:30) So the angel said to her: “Do not be afraid, Mary, for you have found favor with God.

^ (Luke 1:26-33) In her sixth month, the angel Gaʹbri·el was sent from God to a city of Galʹi·lee named Nazʹa·reth, 27 to a virgin promised in marriage to a man named Joseph of David’s house, and the name of the virgin was Mary. 28 And coming in, the angel said to her: “Greetings, you highly favored one, Jehovah is with you.” 29 But she was deeply disturbed at his words and tried to understand what kind of greeting this might be. 30 So the angel said to her: “Do not be afraid, Mary, for you have found favor with God. 31 And look! you will become pregnant* and give birth to a son, and you are to name him Jesus. 32 This one will be great and will be called Son of the Most High, and Jehovah God will give him the throne of David his father, 33 and he will rule as King over the house of Jacob forever, and there will be no end to his Kingdom.”

Or “will conceive in your womb.”

^ (Luke 1:46-55) And Mary said: “My soul magnifies Jehovah, 47 and my spirit cannot keep from being overjoyed at God my Savior, 48 because he has looked upon the low position of his slave girl. For look! from now on all generations will declare me happy, 49 because the powerful One has done great deeds for me, and holy is his name, 50 and for generation after generation his mercy is upon those who fear him. 51 He has acted mightily with his arm; he has scattered those who are haughty in the intention of their hearts. 52 He has brought down powerful men from thrones and has exalted lowly ones; 53 he has fully satisfied hungry ones with good things and has sent away empty-handed those who had wealth. 54 He has come to the aid of Israel his servant, remembering his mercy, 55 just as he spoke to our forefathers, to Abraham and to his offspring,* forever.”

Lit., “seed.”

^ (Luke 2:8-14) There were also in the same region shepherds living out of doors and keeping watch in the night over their flocks. 9 Suddenly Jehovah’s angel stood before them, and Jehovah’s glory gleamed around them, and they became very fearful. 10 But the angel said to them: “Do not be afraid, for look! I am declaring to you good news of a great joy that all the people will have. 11 For today there was born to you in David’s city a savior, who is Christ the Lord. 12 And this is a sign for you: You will find an infant wrapped in strips of cloth and lying in a manger.” 13 Suddenly there was with the angel a multitude of the heavenly army,* praising God and saying: 14 “Glory in the heights above to God, and on earth peace among men of goodwill.”

Or “host.”

^ (Luke 2:15-17) So when the angels had departed from them into heaven, the shepherds began saying to one another: “Let us by all means go over to Bethʹle·hem and see what has taken place, which Jehovah has made known to us.” 16 And they went quickly and found Mary as well as Joseph, and the infant lying in the manger. 17 When they saw this, they made known the message that they had been told concerning this young child.

Thursday, May 28

Jehovah became furious at Solomon.—[1 Ki. 11:9].

Why was Jehovah’s anger raised against Solomon? The Bible reports: “Because his heart had inclined away from Jehovah . . . , who had appeared to him twice and had warned him about this very thing, that he should not go after other gods. But he did not obey what Jehovah had commanded.” As a result, God withdrew his approval and support. Solomon’s heirs lost the unified kingdom of Israel and suffered many calamities for generations to come. (1 Ki. 11:9-13) As in Solomon’s case, one of the greatest threats to spirituality is friendship with those who do not understand or respect Jehovah’s standards. Some may be associated with the congregation but may be spiritually weak. Others could be relatives, neighbors, coworkers, or schoolmates who are not worshippers of Jehovah. In any case, if our close associates do not show a high regard for Jehovah’s standards, they can in time destroy our good standing with God. w18.07 19 ¶9-10

^ (1 Ki. 11:9) Jehovah became furious at Solʹo·mon, because his heart had inclined away from Jehovah the God of Israel, who had appeared to him twice

^ (1 Ki. 11:9-13) Jehovah became furious at Solʹo·mon, because his heart had inclined away from Jehovah the God of Israel, who had appeared to him twice 10 and had warned him about this very thing, that he should not go after other gods. But he did not obey what Jehovah had commanded. 11 Jehovah now said to Solʹo·mon: “Because you have done this and you have not kept my covenant and my statutes as I commanded you, I will surely rip the kingdom away from you, and I will give it to one of your servants. 12 However, for the sake of your father David, I will not do it in your lifetime. I will rip it out of the hand of your son, 13 but I will not rip away the entire kingdom. One tribe I will give to your son, for the sake of David my servant and for the sake of Jerusalem, which I have chosen.”

Friday, May 29

The whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.—[1 John 5:19].

Satan uses movies and television shows to spread his way of thinking. He understands that storytelling does much more than entertain us; it teaches us how to think, feel, and act. Jesus made good use of this method of teaching. Take, for example, his parables of the neighborly Samaritan and of the son who left home and wasted his inheritance. ([Matt. 13:34;] Luke 10:29-37; 15:11-32) However, those who are infected with Satan’s thinking can use storytelling to corrupt us. We need to be balanced. Movies and TV shows can entertain and educate us without contaminating our thinking. But we must be cautious. When choosing entertainment, we do well to ask ourselves, ‘Is this movie or TV show teaching me that it is all right to give in to my fleshly desires?’ (Gal. 5:19-21;[Eph. 2:1-3]) What should you do if you detect that a program is promoting satanic thinking? Avoid it as you would a contagious disease! w19.01 15-16 ¶6-7

^ (1 John 5:19) We know that we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.

^ (Matt. 13:34) All these things Jesus spoke to the crowds by illustrations. Indeed, without an illustration he would not speak to them,

^ (Luke 10:29-37) But wanting to prove himself righteous, the man said to Jesus: “Who really is my neighbor?” 30 In reply Jesus said: “A man was going down from Jerusalem to Jerʹi·cho and fell victim to robbers, who stripped him, beat him, and went off, leaving him half-dead. 31 Now by coincidence a priest was going down on that road, but when he saw him, he passed by on the opposite side. 32 Likewise, a Levite, when he came to the place and saw him, passed by on the opposite side. 33 But a certain Sa·marʹi·tan traveling the road came upon him, and at seeing him, he was moved with pity. 34 So he approached him and bandaged his wounds, pouring oil and wine on them. Then he mounted him on his own animal and brought him to an inn and took care of him. 35 The next day he took out two de·narʹi·i, gave them to the innkeeper, and said: ‘Take care of him, and whatever you spend besides this, I will repay you when I return.’ 36 Who of these three seems to you to have made himself neighbor to the man who fell victim to the robbers?” 37 He said: “The one who acted mercifully toward him.” Jesus then said to him: “Go and do the same yourself.”

^ (Gal. 5:19-21) Now the works of the flesh are plainly seen, and they are sexual immorality,* uncleanness, brazen conduct,* 20 idolatry, spiritism,* hostility, strife, jealousy, fits of anger, dissensions, divisions, sects, 21 envy, drunkenness, wild parties,* and things like these. I am forewarning you about these things, the same way I already warned you, that those who practice such things will not inherit God’s Kingdom.

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

Or “shameless conduct.” Greek, a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

Or “sorcery; druggery.”

Or “revelries.”

^ (Eph. 2:1-3) Furthermore, God made you alive, though you were dead in your trespasses and sins, 2 in which you at one time walked according to the system of things* of this world, according to the ruler of the authority of the air, the spirit that is now at work in the sons of disobedience. 3 Yes, among them we all at one time conducted ourselves in harmony with the desires of our flesh, carrying out the will of the flesh and of our thoughts, and we were naturally children of wrath just as the rest.

Or “the course.”

Saturday, May 30

Accept the helmet of salvation.—[Eph. 6:17].

Just as a helmet protects a soldier’s brain, our “hope of salvation” protects our mind, our thinking ability. (1 Thess. 5:8;[Prov. 3:21]) How could Satan induce us to remove our helmet? Consider the way he dealt with Jesus. Satan surely knew that Jesus had the hope of eventually ruling mankind. But Jesus would have to wait until Jehovah’s appointed time. And before then, he would have to suffer and die. So Satan offered Jesus the chance to fulfill his hope sooner. Satan suggested that if Jesus would do one act of worship, he could have it all and have it right then. ([Luke 4:5-7]) Similarly, Satan knows that Jehovah offers us material benefits in the new system. But we have to wait, and we might have to suffer hardships in the meantime. So Satan offers us tempting opportunities to enjoy such a life now. He wants us to seek material benefits first—to have it all and have it now. Satan urges us to seek the Kingdom second.—Matt. 6:31-33. w18.05 30-31 ¶15-17

^ (Eph. 6:17) Also, accept the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the spirit, that is, God’s word,

^ (1 Thess. 5:8) But as for us who belong to the day, let us keep our senses and put on the breastplate of faith and love and the hope of salvation as a helmet

^ (Prov. 3:21) My son, do not lose sight of them.* Safeguard practical wisdom and thinking ability;

Evidently referring to God’s qualities mentioned in the previous verses.

^ (Luke 4:5-7) So he brought him up and showed him all the kingdoms of the inhabited earth in an instant of time. 6 Then the Devil said to him: “I will give you all this authority and their glory, because it has been handed over to me, and I give it to whomever I wish. 7 If you, therefore, do an act of worship before me, it will all be yours.”

^ (Matt. 6:31-33) So never be anxious and say, ‘What are we to eat?’ or, ‘What are we to drink?’ or, ‘What are we to wear?’ 32 For all these are the things the nations are eagerly pursuing. Your heavenly Father knows that you need all these things. 33 “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

Sunday, May 31

Let your heart be glad in the days of your youth.—[Eccl. 11:9].

Yes, Jehovah wants you as a young person to have a joyful heart. Keep yourself focused on theocratic goals, including Jehovah in all your plans. The earlier you start to do this, the sooner you will sense Jehovah’s guidance, protection, and blessing. Think of all the sound counsel you find in God’s Word, and take to heart the advice: “Remember, then, your Grand Creator in the days of your youth.” ([Eccl. 12:1]) Young people in the congregation deserve warm commendation for being determined to focus their lives on serving Jehovah. Youths do this by reaching out for spiritual goals and by giving the preaching work high priority. Moreover, they make up their mind not to be distracted by this world. Adolescents can be sure that their hard work is not in vain. They have the loving support of their brothers and sisters, and when they commit themselves to Jehovah, their plans in life will succeed. w18.04 29 ¶17, 19

^ (Eccl. 11:9) Rejoice, young man, while you are young, and let your heart be glad in the days of your youth. Follow the ways of your heart and go where your eyes lead you; but know that the true God will bring you into judgment* for all these things.

Or “call you to account.”

^ (Eccl. 12:1) Remember, then, your Grand Creator in the days of your youth, before the days of distress* come and the years arrive when you will say: “I have no pleasure in them”;

Or “the calamitous days.”

June

Monday, June 1

No matter what you ask the Father in my name, he [will] give it to you.—[John 15:16].

How strengthening this promise must have been for the apostles! Though they did not clearly grasp it, their Leader’s life on earth would soon end, but they would not be left without support. Jehovah was ready to answer their prayers for any help they needed to carry out the command to preach the Kingdom message. And indeed, shortly thereafter, they experienced how Jehovah answered their prayers for help. ([Acts 4:29,][31]) The same is true today. As we endure in bearing fruit, we enjoy Jesus’ friendship. Furthermore, we can be sure that Jehovah is ready to answer our prayers for help in overcoming obstacles that we may encounter as we preach the Kingdom good news. ([Phil. 4:13]) How grateful we are to be blessed with answered prayers and friendship with Jesus! These gifts from Jehovah strengthen us to keep on bearing fruit.—[Jas. 1:17]. w18.05 21 ¶17-18

^ (John 15:16) You did not choose me, but I chose you, and I appointed you to go and keep bearing fruit and that your fruit should remain, so that no matter what you ask the Father in my name, he may give it to you.

^ (Acts 4:29) And now, Jehovah, give attention to their threats, and grant to your slaves to keep speaking your word with all boldness,

^ (Acts 4:31) And when they had made supplication, the place where they were gathered together was shaken, and they were one and all filled with the holy spirit and were speaking the word of God with boldness.

^ (Phil. 4:13) For all things I have the strength through the one who gives me power.

^ (Jas. 1:17) Every good gift and every perfect present is from above, coming down from the Father of the celestial lights, who does not vary or change like the shifting shadows.*

Or “with whom there is not a variation of the turning of the shadow.”

Tuesday, June 2

Let us [encourage] one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.—Heb. 10:24, 25.

Within just five years, Jewish Christians living in Jerusalem would see a “day of Jehovah” approaching and recognize the sign Jesus had given them to flee for their lives from that city. (Acts 2:19, 20; Luke 21:20-22) That day of Jehovah arrived in 70 C.E. when the Romans executed Jehovah’s judgment on Jerusalem. Today, we have every reason to believe that the “great and very awe-inspiring” day of Jehovah is near. ([Joel 2:11]) The prophet Zephaniah said: “The great day of Jehovah is near! It is near and it is approaching very quickly!” ([Zeph. 1:14]) That prophetic warning also applies to our time. In view of the proximity of Jehovah’s day, Paul tells us to “be concerned about one another so as to incite to love and fine works.” ([Heb. 10:24], ftn.) We should, therefore, be increasingly interested in our brothers, so that we can encourage them whenever needed. w18.04 20 ¶1-2

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Acts 2:19, 20) And I will give wonders in heaven above and signs on earth below—blood and fire and clouds of smoke. 20 The sun will be turned into darkness and the moon into blood before the great and illustrious day of Jehovah comes.

^ (Luke 21:20-22) “However, when you see Jerusalem surrounded by encamped armies, then know that the desolating of her has drawn near. 21 Then let those in Ju·deʹa begin fleeing to the mountains, let those in the midst of her leave, and let those in the countryside not enter into her, 22 because these are days for meting out justice in order that all the things written may be fulfilled.

^ (Joel 2:11) Jehovah will raise his voice before his army, for his camp is very numerous. For the one carrying out His word is mighty; For the day of Jehovah is great and very awe-inspiring. Who can endure it?”

^ (Zeph. 1:14) The great day of Jehovah is near! It is near and it is approaching very quickly!* The sound of the day of Jehovah is bitter. There a warrior cries out.

Or “hurrying rapidly!”

^ (Heb. 10:24) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works,

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

Wednesday, June 3

Be courageous and strong. Do not be struck with terror or fear, for Jehovah your God is with you wherever you go.—[Josh. 1:9].

What reassuring encouragement Jehovah gave Joshua before settling His people in the Promised Land! Not only did Jehovah encourage individuals but he also gave words of encouragement to his people as a group. In prophetic terms this would prove to be of comfort to the Jews held captive in Babylon, Jehovah stated: “Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.” ([Isa. 41:10]) The early Christians had the same assurance, and so do God’s people today. (2 Cor. 1:3, 4) Jesus himself received encouragement from his Father. At his baptism, Jesus heard a voice from heaven say: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved.” ([Matt. 3:17]) How those words must have strengthened Jesus throughout his earthly ministry! w18.04 16 ¶3-5

^ (Josh. 1:9) Have I not commanded you? Be courageous and strong. Do not be struck with terror or fear, for Jehovah your God is with you wherever you go.”

^ (Isa. 41:10) Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.’

^ (2 Cor. 1:3, 4) Praised be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of tender mercies and the God of all comfort, 4 who comforts* us in all our trials* so that we may be able to comfort others in any sort of trial* with the comfort that we receive from God.

Or “encourages.”

Or “tribulation.”

Or “tribulation.”

^ (Matt. 3:17) Look! Also, a voice from the heavens said: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved.”

Thursday, June 4

As for the tree of the knowledge of good and bad, you must not eat from it.—[Gen. 2:17].

Upon reading Jehovah’s command to Adam, many today would say that Adam was denied the freedom to do what he wanted. In saying so, they are confusing the exercise of one’s free will with the right to decide what is good and what is bad. Adam and Eve did have the freedom to choose whether they would obey God or not. However, only Jehovah has the right to decide in the absolute sense what is good and what is bad, as symbolized by “the tree of the knowledge of good and bad” in the garden of Eden. ([Gen. 2:9]) By means of his command, Jehovah lovingly taught Adam and Eve the way to exercise true freedom. As it turned out, our first parents chose to disobey. Did Adam and Eve’s choice eventually enhance their freedom in any way? Sadly, it did not. In striving for self-determination, they lost the true freedom they had been given. w18.04 5-6 ¶9-12

^ (Gen. 2:17) But as for the tree of the knowledge of good and bad, you must not eat from it, for in the day you eat from it you will certainly die.”

^ (Gen. 2:9) Thus Jehovah God made to grow out of the ground every tree that was pleasing to look at and good for food and also the tree of life in the middle of the garden and the tree of the knowledge of good and bad.

Friday, June 5

During all their distress it was distressing to him.—[Isa. 63:9].

Jehovah does more than just feel compassion for his servants who suffer. He takes action to help them. For example, when the Israelites were suffering as slaves in Egypt, Jehovah understood their pain and felt moved to relieve it. Jehovah said to Moses: “I have certainly seen the affliction of my people . . . , and I have heard their outcry . . . I well know the pains they suffer. I will go down to rescue them out of the hand of the Egyptians.” ([Ex. 3:7, 8]) Because Jehovah felt compassion for his people, he freed them from slavery. Centuries later, in the Promised Land, the Israelites faced enemy attacks. How did Jehovah respond? He “was moved to pity over their groaning caused by those who oppressed them and those who were treating them abusively.” Again, empathy moved Jehovah to help his people. He sent judges to save the Israelites from their enemies.—[Judg. 2:16,][18]. w19.03 15 ¶4-5

^ (Isa. 63:9) During all their distress it was distressing to him. And his own personal messenger* saved them. In his love and compassion he repurchased them, And he lifted them up and carried them all the days of old.

Or “the angel of his presence.”

^ (Ex. 3:7, 8) Jehovah added: “I have certainly seen the affliction of my people who are in Egypt, and I have heard their outcry because of those who force them to work; I well know the pains they suffer. 8 I will go down to rescue them out of the hand of the Egyptians and to bring them up out of that land to a land good and spacious, a land flowing with milk and honey, the territory of the Caʹnaan·ites, the Hitʹtites, the Amʹor·ites, the Perʹiz·zites, the Hiʹvites, and the Jebʹu·sites.

^ (Judg. 2:16) So Jehovah would raise up judges who would save them from the hand of their plunderers.

^ (Judg. 2:18) Whenever Jehovah did raise up judges for them, Jehovah would be with the judge and save them from the hand of their enemies all the days of the judge; for Jehovah was moved to pity* over their groaning caused by those who oppressed them and those who were treating them abusively.

Or “felt regret.”

Saturday, June 6

Can a woman forget her nursing child or have no compassion for the son of her womb? Even if these women forget, I would never forget you.—[Isa. 49:15].

The first two of the Ten Commandments required that the Israelites devote themselves exclusively to Jehovah and warned against the worship of idols. ([Ex. 20:3-6]) Those commandments were not for Jehovah’s benefit. Rather, they were for the benefit of his people. When they worshipped the gods of other nations, they suffered. By contrast, Jehovah blessed his people when they were loyal to him and treated one another justly. ([1 Ki. 10:4-9]) Jehovah is not to blame when those who claim to serve him ignore his standards and harm his people. However, Jehovah loves us and knows when we suffer injustice. He feels our pain more keenly than a mother feels the suffering of her baby. Although he may not intervene immediately, in due time he will hold unrepentant wrongdoers to account for the way they have treated others. w19.02 22 ¶13-15

^ (Isa. 49:15) Can a woman forget her nursing child Or have no compassion for the son of her womb? Even if these women forget, I would never forget you.

^ (Ex. 20:3-6) You must not have any other gods besides me.* 4 “You must not make for yourself a carved image or a form* like anything that is in the heavens above or on the earth below or in the waters under the earth. 5 You must not bow down to them nor be enticed to serve them, for I, Jehovah your God, am a God who requires exclusive devotion, bringing punishment for the error of fathers upon sons, upon the third generation and upon the fourth generation of those who hate me, 6 but showing loyal love to the thousandth generation of those who love me and keep my commandments.

Or “in defiance of me.” Lit., “against my face.”

Or “representation.”

^ (1 Ki. 10:4-9) When the queen of Sheʹba had seen all the wisdom of Solʹo·mon, the house that he built, 5 the food of his table, the seating of his servants, the table service of his waiters and their attire, his cupbearers, and his burnt sacrifices that he regularly offered up at the house of Jehovah, she was left completely breathless.* 6 So she said to the king: “The report that I heard in my own land about your achievements* and about your wisdom was true. 7 But I did not put faith in the reports until I had come and had seen it with my own eyes. And look! I had not been told the half. You have far surpassed in wisdom and prosperity the report that I heard. 8 Happy are your men, and happy are your servants who stand before you constantly, listening to your wisdom! 9 May Jehovah your God be praised, who has taken pleasure in you by putting you on the throne of Israel. Because of Jehovah’s everlasting love for Israel, he appointed you as king to administer justice and righteousness.”

Lit., “there was no more spirit in her.”

Or “words.”

Sunday, June 7

Let, not my will, but yours take place.—[Luke 22:42].

In the weeks leading up to the Memorial, our meetings often focus on the example of Jesus and the humility he showed in giving his life as a ransom. We are moved to imitate his humble attitude and to do Jehovah’s will, even when it is difficult for us. We think about the courage he showed on the days before his death. He was fully aware that his enemies would soon humiliate, beat, and execute him. (Matt. 20:17-19) Still, he willingly faced death. When the time came, he said to his faithful apostles, who were with him in Gethsemane: “Get up, let us go. Look! My betrayer has drawn near.” ([Matt. 26:36,][46]) And when the armed mob came to arrest him, he stepped forward, identified himself, and ordered the soldiers to let his apostles go. ([John 18:3-8]) What outstanding courage Jesus displayed! Today, anointed Christians and those of the other sheep strive to imitate Jesus in showing courage. w19.01 27-28 ¶7-8

^ (Luke 22:42) saying: “Father, if you want to, remove this cup from me. Nevertheless, let, not my will, but yours take place.”

^ (Matt. 20:17-19) While going up to Jerusalem, Jesus took the 12 disciples aside privately and said to them on the road: 18 “Look! We are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of man will be handed over to the chief priests and the scribes. They will condemn him to death 19 and hand him over to men of the nations to be mocked and scourged and executed on a stake; and on the third day he will be raised up.”

^ (Matt. 26:36) Then Jesus came with them to the spot called Geth·semʹa·ne, and he said to the disciples: “Sit down here while I go over there and pray.”

^ (Matt. 26:46) Get up, let us go. Look! My betrayer has drawn near.”

^ (John 18:3-8) So Judas brought the detachment of soldiers and officers of the chief priests and of the Pharisees and came there with torches and lamps and weapons. 4 Then Jesus, knowing all the things that were going to happen to him, stepped forward and said to them: “Whom are you looking for?” 5 They answered him: “Jesus the Naz·a·reneʹ.” He said to them: “I am he.” Now Judas, his betrayer, was also standing with them. 6 However, when Jesus said to them, “I am he,” they drew back and fell to the ground. 7 So he asked them again: “Whom are you looking for?” They said: “Jesus the Naz·a·reneʹ.” 8 Jesus answered: “I told you that I am he. So if you are looking for me, let these men go.”

Monday, June 8

Seek meekness.—[Zeph. 2:3].

Just as an artist combines a number of appealing colors to produce a painting, we must combine a number of appealing qualities to be meek. Prominent among those qualities are humility, submissiveness, mildness, and inner strength. Only humble people will submit to God’s will. Part of God’s will is that we be mild. ([Matt. 5:5;][Gal. 5:23]) When we do God’s will, we make Satan furious. So even though we are humble and mild, many people who are part of Satan’s world hate us. (John 15:18, 19) As a result, we need inner strength to resist Satan. The opposite of a meek person is someone who is haughty, shows uncontrolled anger, and does not obey Jehovah. That describes Satan perfectly. No wonder he hates meek people! They expose the flaws in his personality. And even worse for Satan, they prove that he is a liar. Why? Because no matter what he says or does, he cannot stop meek people from serving Jehovah!—[Job 2:3-5]. w19.02 8-9 ¶3-5

^ (Zeph. 2:3) Seek Jehovah, all you meek ones* of the earth, Who observe his righteous decrees.* Seek righteousness, seek meekness.* Probably* you will be concealed on the day of Jehovah’s anger.

Or “humble ones.”

Lit., “his judgment.”

Or “humility.”

Or “It may be that.”

^ (Matt. 5:5) “Happy are the mild-tempered, since they will inherit the earth.

^ (Gal. 5:23) mildness, self-control. Against such things there is no law.

^ (John 15:18, 19) If the world hates you, you know that it has hated me before it hated you. 19 If you were part of the world, the world would be fond of what is its own. Now because you are no part of the world, but I have chosen you out of the world, for this reason the world hates you.

^ (Job 2:3-5) And Jehovah said to Satan: “Have you taken note of* my servant Job? There is no one like him on the earth. He is an upright man of integrity,* fearing God and shunning what is bad. He is still holding firmly to his integrity, even though you try to incite me against him to destroy* him for no reason.” 4 But Satan answered Jehovah: “Skin for skin. A man will give everything that he has for his life.* 5 But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike his bone and flesh, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”

Lit., “set your heart upon.”

Or “a blameless and upright man.”

Lit., “swallow.”

Or “soul.”

Tuesday, June 9

Do not be anxious, for I am your God.—[Isa. 41:10].

Jehovah knew that the inhabitants of Babylon would become afraid. Babylon would be attacked by the mighty armies of Medo-Persia. Jehovah would use this army to free his people from captivity to Babylon. ([Isa. 41:2-4]) When the Babylonians and people of other nations knew that their enemy was approaching, they tried to maintain their courage by saying to one another: “Be strong.” They also made more idol gods, hoping that these would protect them. ([Isa. 41:5-7]) Meanwhile, Jehovah calmed the hearts of the Jewish exiles by saying: “You, O Israel, [unlike your neighbors] are my servant . . . Do not be anxious, for I am your God.” ([Isa. 41:8-10]) Note that Jehovah said: “I am your God.” With those words, Jehovah reassured his loyal worshippers that he had not forgotten them and that they were still his people. He told them: “I will carry you . . . and rescue you.” Those reassuring words no doubt strengthened the Jewish exiles.—[Isa. 46:3, 4]. w19.01 4 ¶8

^ (Isa. 41:10) Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.’

^ (Isa. 41:2-4) Who has raised up someone from the sunrise,* Calling him in righteousness to His feet,* To hand over nations to him And to make him subdue kings? Who reduces them to dust before his sword, Like windblown stubble before his bow?  3 He pursues them, passing along unhindered Over paths that his feet have not traveled.  4 Who has acted and done this, Summoning the generations from the beginning? I, Jehovah, am the First One; And with the last ones I am the same.”

Or “from the east.”

That is, to serve Him.

^ (Isa. 41:5-7) The islands have seen it and have become afraid. The ends of the earth began to tremble. They draw near and come forward.  6 Each one helps his companion And says to his brother: “Be strong.”  7 So the craftsman strengthens the metalworker; The one who flattens with the forge hammer Strengthens the one hammering at the anvil. He says about the soldering: “It is good.” Then it is fastened with nails so that it will not topple over.

^ (Isa. 41:8-10) “But you, O Israel, are my servant, You, O Jacob, whom I have chosen, The offspring* of Abraham my friend,  9 You, whom I took from the ends of the earth, And you, whom I called from its most distant parts. I said to you, ‘You are my servant; I have chosen you; I have not rejected you. 10 Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.’

Lit., “seed.”

^ (Isa. 46:3, 4) “Listen to me, O house of Jacob, and all you who remain of the house of Israel, You whom I have supported from birth and carried from the womb.  4 Until you grow old I will be the same; Until your hair is gray I will keep bearing you. As I have done, I will carry you and bear you and rescue you.

Wednesday, June 10

A voice came out of the heavens: “You are my Son, the beloved; I have approved you.”—[Mark 1:11].

[Mark 1:9-11] records the first of three occasions when Jehovah spoke from heaven. Jehovah said: “You are my Son, the beloved; I have approved you.” How it must have touched Jesus’ heart to hear his Father’s voice expressing love and reassurance to him! Jehovah’s words confirmed three important facts about Jesus. First, Jesus is his Son. Second, Jehovah loves his Son. And third, Jehovah has approved his Son. By saying “You are my Son,” Jehovah indicated that his beloved Son, Jesus, had entered into a new relationship with Him. While Jesus was in heaven, he was a spirit son of God. However, at his baptism, he was anointed by holy spirit. At that time, God indicated that Jesus as His anointed Son now had the hope of returning to heaven to become God’s appointed King and High Priest. (Luke 1:31-33; Heb. 1:8, 9;[2:17]) So at Jesus’ baptism, his Father had good reason to say: “You are my Son.”—[Luke 3:22]. w19.03 8 ¶3-4

^ (Mark 1:11) And a voice came out of the heavens: “You are my Son, the beloved; I have approved you.”

^ (Mark 1:9-11) In the course of those days, Jesus came from Nazʹa·reth of Galʹi·lee and was baptized in the Jordan by John. 10 And immediately on coming up out of the water, he saw the heavens being parted and, like a dove, the spirit coming down upon him. 11 And a voice came out of the heavens: “You are my Son, the beloved; I have approved you.”

^ (Luke 1:31-33) And look! you will become pregnant* and give birth to a son, and you are to name him Jesus. 32 This one will be great and will be called Son of the Most High, and Jehovah God will give him the throne of David his father, 33 and he will rule as King over the house of Jacob forever, and there will be no end to his Kingdom.”

Or “will conceive in your womb.”

^ (Heb. 1:8, 9) But about the Son, he says: “God is your throne forever and ever, and the scepter of your Kingdom is the scepter of uprightness.* 9 You loved righteousness, and you hated lawlessness. That is why God, your God, anointed you with the oil of exultation more than your companions.”

Or “justice.”

^ (Heb. 2:17) Consequently, he had to become like his “brothers” in all respects, so that he could become a merciful and faithful high priest in things relating to God, in order to offer a propitiatory sacrifice* for the sins of the people.

Or “to offer an atoning sacrifice; to make atonement.”

^ (Luke 3:22) and the holy spirit in bodily form like a dove came down upon him, and a voice came out of heaven: “You are my Son, the beloved; I have approved you.”

Thursday, June 11

There is no wisdom . . . in opposition to Jehovah.—[Prov. 21:30].

Bad advice has its roots very early in human history when Satan entered the scene. A presumptuous, self-appointed adviser, he told Eve that she and her husband would be happier if they chose their own course in life. ([Gen. 3:1-6]) Satan’s motives were selfish. He wanted Adam and Eve—and their future offspring—to submit to and worship him rather than worship Jehovah. But it was Jehovah who had given them everything they had—each other, their beautiful garden home, and their perfect bodies with the potential of living forever. Sadly, Adam and Eve disobeyed God, cutting themselves off from him. The results, as you know, were tragic. Like flowers cut from a plant, they slowly began to wither and die. Their children also suffered from the curse of sin. ([Rom. 5:12]) Even so, most people still choose not to submit to God. They want to live life their own way. ([Eph. 2:1-3]) The results clearly show the truthfulness of today’s text. w18.12 20 ¶3-4

^ (Prov. 21:30) There is no wisdom, nor discernment, nor counsel in opposition to Jehovah.

^ (Gen. 3:1-6) Now the serpent was the most cautious* of all the wild animals of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it said to the woman: “Did God really say that you must not eat from every tree of the garden?” 2 At this the woman said to the serpent: “We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden. 3 But God has said about the fruit of the tree that is in the middle of the garden: ‘You must not eat from it, no, you must not touch it; otherwise you will die.’” 4 At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die. 5 For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.” 6 Consequently, the woman saw that the tree was good for food and that it was something desirable to the eyes, yes, the tree was pleasing to look at. So she began taking of its fruit and eating it. Afterward, she also gave some to her husband when he was with her, and he began eating it.

Or “shrewdest; craftiest.”

^ (Rom. 5:12) That is why, just as through one man sin entered into the world and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because they had all sinned—.

^ (Eph. 2:1-3) Furthermore, God made you alive, though you were dead in your trespasses and sins, 2 in which you at one time walked according to the system of things* of this world, according to the ruler of the authority of the air, the spirit that is now at work in the sons of disobedience. 3 Yes, among them we all at one time conducted ourselves in harmony with the desires of our flesh, carrying out the will of the flesh and of our thoughts, and we were naturally children of wrath just as the rest.

Or “the course.”

Friday, June 12

We . . . speak, not with words taught by human wisdom, but with those taught by the spirit, as we explain spiritual matters with spiritual words.—[1 Cor. 2:13].

The apostle Paul was an intelligent and learned man, knowing at least two languages. ([Acts 5:34;][21:37,][39;][22:2, 3]) Yet, when it came to matters of principle, he rejected worldly wisdom. Instead, he based his reasoning on the Scriptures. ([Acts 17:2;] 1 Cor. 2:6, 7) As a result, Paul enjoyed a successful ministry and anticipated an eternal reward. ([2 Tim. 4:8]) Certainly, God’s thinking is superior to that of today’s world. Living by his thoughts will bring us the greatest happiness and success. But Jehovah will not force his thinking on us. “The faithful and discreet slave” does not exercise control over the thoughts of individuals, and neither do the elders. ([Matt. 24:45;][2 Cor. 1:24]) Rather, each Christian has the personal responsibility to bring his or her thinking into harmony with God’s. w18.11 20-21 ¶12-13

^ (1 Cor. 2:13) These things we also speak, not with words taught by human wisdom, but with those taught by the spirit, as we explain* spiritual matters with spiritual words.

Or “combine.”

^ (Acts 5:34) But a Pharisee named Ga·maʹli·el rose in the Sanʹhe·drin; he was a Law teacher esteemed by all the people, and he gave the command to put the men outside for a little while.

^ (Acts 21:37) As he was about to be led into the soldiers’ quarters, Paul said to the military commander: “Am I allowed to say something to you?” He said: “Can you speak Greek?

^ (Acts 21:39) Then Paul said: “I am, in fact, a Jew, of Tarsus in Ci·liʹcia, a citizen of no obscure city. So I beg you, permit me to speak to the people.”

^ (Acts 22:2, 3) Well, when they heard that he was addressing them in the Hebrew language, they kept all the more silent, and he said: 3 “I am a Jew, born in Tarsus of Ci·liʹcia, but educated in this city at the feet of Ga·maʹli·el, instructed according to the strictness of the ancestral Law, and zealous for God just as all of you are this day.

^ (Acts 17:2) So according to Paul’s custom he went inside to them, and for three sabbaths he reasoned with them from the Scriptures,

^ (1 Cor. 2:6, 7) Now we speak wisdom among those who are mature, but not the wisdom of this system of things* nor that of the rulers of this system of things, who are to come to nothing. 7 But we speak God’s wisdom in a sacred secret, the hidden wisdom, which God foreordained before the systems of things for our glory.

Or “this age.” See Glossary.

^ (2 Tim. 4:8) From this time on, there is reserved for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, will give me as a reward in that day, yet not to me only, but also to all those who have loved his manifestation.

^ (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

^ (2 Cor. 1:24) Not that we are the masters over your faith, but we are fellow workers for your joy, for it is by your faith that you are standing.

Saturday, June 13

Grief and sighing will flee away.—[Isa. 35:10].

God foretold through Isaiah that after His people returned to their homeland, they would not have to struggle against harsh, dangerous elements; nor would they need to fear attacks from animals or beastlike men. Young and old would be safe. ([Isa. 11:6-9;][35:5-10;][51:3]) Isaiah also said that the whole earth—not just the nation of Israel—would “be filled with the knowledge of Jehovah as the waters cover the sea.” Isaiah further emphasized that the returnees would not be threatened by animals or humans. Their land would produce abundant fruit, made possible by an ample supply of water, even as the garden of Eden was well-watered. (Gen. 2:10-14;[Jer. 31:12]) Would that be the only fulfillment? There is no evidence that those returning from exile were miraculously cured. For example, the blind did not regain their sight. So God was indicating that literal healings would yet occur. w18.12 5 ¶11-12

^ (Isa. 35:10) Those redeemed by Jehovah will return and come to Zion with a joyful cry. Unending joy will crown their heads. Exultation and rejoicing will be theirs, And grief and sighing will flee away.

^ (Isa. 11:6-9) The wolf will reside for a while with the lamb, And with the young goat the leopard will lie down, And the calf and the lion* and the fattened animal will all be together;* And a little boy will lead them.  7 The cow and the bear will feed together, And their young will lie down together. The lion will eat straw like the bull.  8 The nursing child will play over the lair of a cobra, And a weaned child will put his hand over the den of a poisonous snake.  9 They will not cause any harm Or any ruin in all my holy mountain, Because the earth will certainly be filled with the knowledge of Jehovah As the waters cover the sea.

Or “the maned young lion.”

Or possibly, “And the calf and the lion will feed together.”

^ (Isa. 35:5-10) At that time the eyes of the blind will be opened, And the ears of the deaf will be unstopped.  6 At that time the lame will leap like the deer, And the tongue of the speechless will shout for joy. For waters will burst forth in the wilderness, And streams in the desert plain.  7 The heat-parched ground will become a reedy pool, And the thirsty ground springs of water. In the lairs where jackals rested, There will be green grass and reeds and papyrus.  8 And a highway will be there, Yes, a way called the Way of Holiness. The unclean one will not travel on it. It is reserved for the one walking on the way; No one foolish will stray onto it.  9 No lion will be there, And no vicious wild beasts will come on it. They will not be found there; Only the repurchased ones will walk there. 10 Those redeemed by Jehovah will return and come to Zion with a joyful cry. Unending joy will crown their heads. Exultation and rejoicing will be theirs, And grief and sighing will flee away.

^ (Isa. 51:3) For Jehovah will comfort Zion. He will bring comfort to all her ruins, And he will make her wilderness like Eʹden And her desert plain like the garden of Jehovah. Exultation and rejoicing will be found in her, Thanksgiving and melodious song.

^ (Gen. 2:10-14) Now there was a river flowing out of Eʹden to water the garden, and from there it divided into four rivers.* 11 The name of the first is Piʹshon; it is the one encircling the entire land of Havʹi·lah, where there is gold. 12 The gold of that land is good. Bdellium gum and onyx stone are also there. 13 The name of the second river is Giʹhon; it is the one encircling the entire land of Cush. 14 The name of the third river is Hidʹde·kel;* it is the one going to the east of As·syrʹi·a. And the fourth river is the Eu·phraʹtes.

Lit., “it became four heads.”

Or “Tigris.”

^ (Jer. 31:12) They will come and shout joyfully on the height of Zion And become radiant over the goodness of* Jehovah, Over the grain and the new wine and the oil, And over the young of the flock and the herd. They* will become like a well-watered garden, And they will never languish again.”

Or “the good things from.”

Or “Their soul.”

Sunday, June 14

Go on walking in the truth.—[3 John 3].

Walking in the truth is an ongoing process, a path that we hope to follow throughout eternity. How can we strengthen our determination to go on walking in the truth? Continue to study the precious truths of God’s Word and meditate on them. Yes, buy truth by regularly setting aside time to feed on the precious truths of God’s Word. You will thus deepen your appreciation for the truth and strengthen your resolve never to sell it. In addition to buying truth, Proverbs 23:23 says that we should also buy “wisdom and discipline and understanding.” Knowledge alone is not enough. We must put the truth to work in our lives. With understanding, we discern the harmony of all of Jehovah’s sayings. Wisdom moves us to act on what we know. At times, the truth disciplines us, showing us where we need to make changes. May we always be responsive to such guidance. Its value is far more than silver.—[Prov. 8:10]. w18.11 9 ¶3; 11 ¶13-14

^ (3 John 3) For I rejoiced very much when brothers came and bore witness about the truth you hold, as you go on walking in the truth.

^ (Prov. 23:23) Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding.

Or “Acquire.”

^ (Prov. 8:10) Take my discipline instead of silver, And knowledge rather than the finest gold,

Monday, June 15

Buy truth and never sell it.—[Prov. 23:23].

What is your most precious possession? Would you be willing to exchange it for something of lesser value? For Jehovah’s dedicated worshippers, the answers to these questions are simple. Our most precious possession is our relationship with Jehovah, and we would not trade it for anything. We also treasure Bible truth, which made cultivating that bond with our heavenly Father possible. ([Col. 1:9, 10]) Just think of all that our Grand Instructor teaches us in his Word, the Bible! He reveals the truth about his meaningful name and his appealing qualities. He informs us about the outstanding provision of the ransom, which he lovingly provided for us by means of his Son, Jesus. Jehovah also informs us about the Messianic Kingdom and the hope of the earthly Paradise. He teaches us how we should conduct ourselves. We treasure these truths because they enable us to draw close to our Creator. They give meaning to our life. w18.11 3 ¶1-2

^ (Prov. 23:23) Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding.

Or “Acquire.”

^ (Col. 1:9, 10) That is also why from the day we heard of it, we have never stopped praying for you and asking that you may be filled with the accurate knowledge of his will in all wisdom and spiritual comprehension, 10 so as to walk worthily of Jehovah* in order to please him fully as you go on bearing fruit in every good work and increasing in the accurate knowledge of God;

See App. A5.

Tuesday, June 16

Do not lie to one another.—[Col. 3:9].

Deceitful people cannot keep anything secret from Jehovah, for “all things are naked and openly exposed” to him. ([Heb. 4:13]) As an example, Ananias and Sapphira schemed in their hearts to deceive the apostles. They sold some property but brought only part of the proceeds of the sale to the apostles. The couple wanted to make themselves look good in the congregation, appearing to be more generous with their donation than they really were. Yet, Jehovah could see what they had done, and he punished them accordingly. ([Acts 5:1-10]) How does Jehovah feel about lying? Satan as well as all unrepentant, malicious liars who imitate him are heading for “the lake of fire.” ([Rev. 20:10;][21:8;][Ps. 5:6]) We know that Jehovah “is not a mere man who tells lies.” In fact, “it is impossible for God to lie.” ([Num. 23:19;][Heb. 6:18]) “Jehovah hates . . . a lying tongue.” (Prov. 6:16, 17) To have his approval, we must live by his standard of truthfulness. w18.10 8 ¶10-13

^ (Col. 3:9) Do not lie to one another. Strip off the old personality* with its practices,

Lit., “man.”

^ (Heb. 4:13) And there is not a creation that is hidden from his sight, but all things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes of the one to whom we must give an account.

^ (Acts 5:1-10) However, a man named An·a·niʹas, together with his wife Sap·phiʹra, sold some property. 2 But he secretly held back some of the price, with his wife’s knowledge, and he brought just a part of it and deposited it at the feet of the apostles. 3 But Peter said: “An·a·niʹas, why has Satan emboldened you to lie to the holy spirit and secretly hold back some of the price of the field? 4 As long as it remained with you, did it not remain yours? And after it was sold, was it not in your control? Why have you thought up such a deed as this in your heart? You have lied, not to men, but to God.” 5 On hearing these words, An·a·niʹas collapsed and died. And great fear came over all those who heard about it. 6 Then the younger men rose, wrapped him in cloths, carried him out, and buried him. 7 Now after an interval of about three hours his wife came in, not knowing what had happened. 8 Peter said to her: “Tell me, did you two sell the field for so much?” She said: “Yes, for that amount.” 9 So Peter said to her: “Why did you two agree to make a test of the spirit of Jehovah? Look! The feet of those who buried your husband are at the door, and they will carry you out.” 10 Instantly she collapsed at his feet and died. When the young men came in, they found her dead and they carried her out and buried her alongside her husband.

^ (Rev. 20:10) And the Devil who was misleading them was hurled into the lake of fire and sulfur, where both the wild beast and the false prophet already were; and they will be tormented* day and night forever and ever.

Or “restrained; imprisoned.”

^ (Rev. 21:8) But as for the cowards and those without faith and those who are disgusting in their filth and murderers and the sexually immoral* and those practicing spiritism and idolaters and all the liars, their portion will be in the lake that burns with fire and sulfur. This means the second death.”

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

^ (Ps. 5:6) You will destroy those who speak lies. Jehovah detests violent and deceptive people.*

Or “a man of bloodshed and deception.”

^ (Num. 23:19) God is not a mere man who tells lies, Nor a son of man who changes his mind.* When he says something, will he not do it? When he speaks, will he not carry it out?

Or “who feels regret.”

^ (Heb. 6:18) in order that through two unchangeable things in which it is impossible for God to lie, we who have fled to the refuge may have strong encouragement to take firm hold of the hope set before us.

^ (Prov. 6:16, 17) There are six things that Jehovah hates; Yes, seven things that he* detests: 17 Haughty eyes, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood,

Or “his soul.”

Wednesday, June 17

Ponder over these things.—[1 Tim. 4:15].

Suppose your employer asked you to contribute funds for an upcoming celebration connected with false religion. What would you do? Rather than wait for these situations to arise, why not give thought now to Jehovah’s thinking on such matters? Then, should any of these situations occur, you will find it easier to do and say the right thing. Giving advance thought to the need to remain loyal can also prove helpful in the event of a medical emergency. While we are firmly resolved to avoid the transfusion of whole blood or any of its four major components, some procedures involving blood require making a personal decision based on Bible principles that indicate Jehovah’s thinking. (Acts 15:28, 29) Surely the best time to weigh such matters is not in a hospital, possibly when we are in pain and under pressure to make a quick decision. Now would be the time to do research, complete a legal medical document indicating your wishes, and speak with your doctor. w18.11 24 ¶5; 26 ¶15-16

^ (1 Tim. 4:15) Ponder over* these things; be absorbed in them, so that your advancement may be plainly seen by all people.

Or “Meditate on.”

^ (Acts 15:28, 29) For the holy spirit and we ourselves have favored adding no further burden to you except these necessary things: 29 to keep abstaining from things sacrificed to idols, from blood, from what is strangled, and from sexual immorality. If you carefully keep yourselves from these things, you will prosper. Good health to you!”

Thursday, June 18

The one listening to me will dwell in security.—[Prov. 1:33].

Jehovah is a loving shepherd who tenderly embraces his people, protecting them from their enemies. How reassuring these truths are to us as we face the end of the present system of things! Jehovah will continue to care for his people during the fast-approaching great tribulation. ([Rev. 7:9, 10]) Hence, whether young or old, sound in body or disabled, God’s people will not panic or cower in fear during the tribulation. In fact, they will do the very opposite! They will bear in mind these words of Jesus Christ: “Stand up straight and lift up your heads, because your deliverance is getting near.” ([Luke 21:28]) They will maintain that confidence even in the face of the attack by Gog—a coalition of powerful nations. ([Ezek. 38:2,][14-16]) Why will God’s people remain confident? They know that Jehovah does not change. He will always prove to be a caring and considerate Savior.—[Isa. 26:20]. w18.09 26 ¶15-16

^ (Prov. 1:33) But the one listening to me will dwell in security And be undisturbed by the dread of calamity.”

^ (Rev. 7:9, 10) After this I saw, and look! a great crowd, which no man was able to number, out of all nations and tribes and peoples and tongues,* standing before the throne and before the Lamb, dressed in white robes; and there were palm branches in their hands. 10 And they keep shouting with a loud voice, saying: “Salvation we owe to our God, who is seated on the throne, and to the Lamb.”

Or “languages.”

^ (Luke 21:28) But as these things start to occur, stand up straight and lift up your heads, because your deliverance is getting near.”

^ (Ezek. 38:2) “Son of man, set your face against Gog of the land of Maʹgog, the head chieftain* of Meʹshech and Tuʹbal, and prophesy against him.

Or “chief prince.”

^ (Ezek. 38:14-16) “So prophesy, son of man, and say to Gog, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “On that day when my people Israel are dwelling in security, will you not know it? 15 You will come from your place, from the remotest parts of the north, you and many peoples with you, all of them riding on horses, a great assembly, a vast army. 16 Like clouds covering the land, you will come against my people Israel. In the final part of the days I will bring you against my land so that the nations may know me when I sanctify myself through you before their eyes, O Gog.”’

^ (Isa. 26:20) Go, my people, enter your inner rooms, And shut your doors behind you. Hide yourself for a brief moment Until the wrath* has passed by.

Or “denunciation.”

Friday, June 19

You became precious in my eyes, . . . and I have loved you.—[Isa. 43:4].

How encouraging it must have been for faithful Israelites to hear Jehovah’s words above. As one of Jehovah’s servants, you too can be sure that Jehovah loves you most tenderly. God’s Word promises concerning those pursuing pure worship: “As a mighty One, he will save. He will exult over you with great joy.” (Zeph. 3:16, 17) No matter what trials his people may face, Jehovah promises to sustain and comfort them. “You will nurse and be carried on the hip, and you will be bounced on the knees. As a mother comforts her son, so I will keep comforting you.” (Isa. 66:12, 13) What a heartwarming scene—a loving mother carrying a baby on her hip or bouncing him on her knees! In this way Jehovah touchingly illustrates the intensity and tenderness of his love for true worshippers. Never doubt that you are personally very precious and dear to Jehovah.—[Jer. 31:3]. w18.09 13 ¶6-7

^ (Isa. 43:4) For you became precious in my eyes, You were honored, and I have loved you. So I will give people in place of you And nations in exchange for your life.*

Or “soul.”

^ (Zeph. 3:16, 17) On that day it will be said to Jerusalem: “Do not be afraid, O Zion. Do not let your hands drop down. 17 Jehovah your God is in your midst. As a mighty One, he will save. He will exult over you with great joy. He will become silent* in his love. He will rejoice over you with shouts of joy.

Or “quiet; at ease; satisfied.”

^ (Isa. 66:12, 13) For this is what Jehovah says: “Here I am extending to her peace just like a river And the glory of nations like a flooding torrent. You will nurse and be carried on the hip, And you will be bounced on the knees. 13 As a mother comforts her son, So I will keep comforting you; And over Jerusalem you will be comforted.

^ (Jer. 31:3) From far away Jehovah appeared to me and said: “I have loved you with an everlasting love. That is why I have drawn you to me with loyal love.*

Or “have continued to show loyal love to you.”

Saturday, June 20

Who volunteers to come forward today with a gift in hand for Jehovah?—1 Chron. 29:5.

On various occasions in the history of ancient Israel, volunteers were needed. ([Ex. 36:2;][Neh. 11:2]) Today, you also have many opportunities to volunteer your time, resources, and skills to help your brothers and sisters. And you will feel great joy and receive many blessings from making yourself available. Those who volunteer for theocratic projects often make new friends. Consider the example of Margie, a sister who has worked on Kingdom Hall construction projects for 18 years. Over the years, she has taken several younger sisters under her wing to give them training. She has found the experience to be an excellent way of encouraging one another spiritually. ([Rom. 1:12]) During trying periods of her life, Margie has received encouragement from those whose friendships she forged on construction projects. Have you ever volunteered for such a construction project? w18.08 25 ¶9, 11

^ (1 Chron. 29:5) the gold for the goldwork and the silver for the silverwork, and for all the work to be done by the craftsmen. Now who volunteers to come forward today with a gift in hand for Jehovah?”

^ (Ex. 36:2) Moses then called Bezʹal·el and O·hoʹli·ab and every skilled man into whose heart Jehovah had put wisdom, everyone whose heart impelled him to volunteer to do the work.

^ (Neh. 11:2) Moreover, the people blessed all the men who volunteered to live in Jerusalem.

^ (Rom. 1:12) or, rather, that we may have an interchange of encouragement by one another’s faith, both yours and mine.

Sunday, June 21

Never let anyone look down on your youth. Instead, become an example to the faithful ones in speaking, in conduct, in love, in faith, in chasteness.—[1 Tim. 4:12].

At the time that Paul wrote these words, Timothy may have been in his early 30’s. Yet, Paul had assigned him to care for weighty responsibilities. Regardless of the underlying reason for this counsel, the point is clear. We must not judge younger brothers simply based on their age. We do well to remember that even our Lord Jesus carried out his entire earthly ministry while he was in his early 30’s. We may be part of a culture that tends to look down on younger men. If so, elders in the congregation may hesitate to recommend qualified young brothers to serve as ministerial servants or elders. All elders do well to remember that the Scriptures do not give a minimum age for a man to be recommended as a ministerial servant or an elder.—1 Tim. 3:1-10,[12, 13;][Titus 1:5-9]. w18.08 11-12 ¶15-16

^ (1 Tim. 4:12) Never let anyone look down on your youth. Instead, become an example to the faithful ones in speaking, in conduct, in love, in faith, in chasteness.*

Or “purity.”

^ (1 Tim. 3:1-10) This statement is trustworthy: If a man is reaching out to be an overseer, he is desirous of a fine work. 2 The overseer should therefore be irreprehensible, a husband of one wife, moderate in habits, sound in mind,* orderly, hospitable, qualified to teach, 3 not a drunkard, not violent,* but reasonable, not quarrelsome, not a lover of money, 4 a man presiding over* his own household in a fine manner, having his children in subjection with all seriousness 5 (for if any man does not know how to preside over* his own household, how will he care for the congregation of God?), 6 not a newly converted man, for fear that he might get puffed up with pride and fall into the judgment passed on the Devil. 7 Moreover, he should also have a fine testimony* from outsiders so that he does not fall into reproach* and a snare of the Devil. 8 Ministerial servants should likewise be serious, not double-tongued,* not indulging in a lot of wine, not greedy of dishonest gain, 9 holding the sacred secret of the faith with a clean conscience. 10 Also, let these be tested as to fitness* first; then let them serve as ministers, as they are free from accusation.

Or “have good judgment; be sensible.”

Or “a smiter.”

Or “managing.”

Or “manage.”

Or “a good reputation.”

Or “disgrace.”

Or “not deceitful in speech.”

Or “tested as to whether they qualify.”

^ (1 Tim. 3:12, 13) Let ministerial servants be husbands of one wife, presiding in a fine manner over their children and their own households. 13 For the men who minister in a fine manner are acquiring for themselves a fine standing and great freeness of speech in the faith that is in Christ Jesus.

^ (Titus 1:5-9) I left you in Crete so that you would correct the things that were defective* and make appointments of elders in city after city, as I instructed you: 6 if there is any man free from accusation, a husband of one wife, having believing children who are not accused of debauchery* or rebelliousness. 7 For as God’s steward, an overseer must be free from accusation, not self-willed, not quick-tempered, not a drunkard, not violent,* not greedy of dishonest gain, 8 but hospitable, a lover of goodness, sound in mind,* righteous, loyal, self-controlled, 9 holding firmly to the faithful word* as respects his art of teaching, so that he may be able both to encourage* by the teaching that is wholesome* and to reprove those who contradict.

Or “deficient.”

Or “wildness.”

Or “a smiter.”

Or “having good judgment; sensible.”

Or “the trustworthy message.”

Or “exhort.”

Or “healthful; beneficial.”

Monday, June 22

[Turn] away from . . . the falsely called “knowledge.”—[1 Tim. 6:20].

To make good decisions, we need solid facts. Therefore, we need to be highly selective and to choose carefully what information we will read. ([Phil. 4:8, 9]) We should not waste our time viewing questionable Internet news sites or reading unsubstantiated reports circulated via e-mail. It is especially important to avoid websites promoted by apostates. Their whole purpose is to tear down God’s people and to distort the truth. Poor quality information will lead to poor decisions. Never underestimate the powerful effect that misleading information can have on your mind and heart. Consider what happened in Moses’ time when 10 of the 12 spies who were sent to explore the Promised Land brought back a bad report. (Num. 13:25-33) Their exaggerated and outrageous account completely disheartened Jehovah’s people. ([Num. 14:1-4,][6-10]) Instead of getting the facts and showing confidence in Jehovah, they chose to believe the bad report. w18.08 4 ¶4-5

^ (1 Tim. 6:20) Timothy, guard what has been entrusted to you, turning away from the empty speeches that violate what is holy and from the contradictions of the falsely called “knowledge.”

^ (Phil. 4:8, 9) Finally, brothers, whatever things are true, whatever things are of serious concern, whatever things are righteous, whatever things are chaste,* whatever things are lovable, whatever things are well-spoken-of, whatever things are virtuous, and whatever things are praiseworthy, continue considering* these things. 9 The things that you learned as well as accepted and heard and saw in connection with me, practice these, and the God of peace will be with you.

Or “pure.”

Or “thinking about; meditating on.”

^ (Num. 13:25-33) At the end of 40 days, they returned from spying out the land. 26 So they came back to Moses and Aaron and all the assembly of the Israelites in the wilderness of Paʹran, at Kaʹdesh. They brought back a report to all the assembly and showed them the fruitage of the land. 27 This is what they reported to Moses: “We entered the land into which you sent us, and it is indeed flowing with milk and honey, and this is its fruitage. 28 Nevertheless, the people who dwell in the land are strong, and the fortified cities are very great. We also saw the Anʹa·kim there. 29 The A·malʹek·ites are dwelling in the land of the Negʹeb, and the Hitʹtites, the Jebʹu·sites, and the Amʹor·ites are dwelling in the mountainous region, and the Caʹnaan·ites are dwelling by the sea and along the Jordan.” 30 Then Caʹleb tried to calm the people as they stood before Moses by saying: “Let us go up immediately, and we are sure to take possession of it, because we can surely conquer it.” 31 But the men who went up with him said: “We are not able to go up against the people, because they are stronger than we are.” 32 And they kept on giving the Israelites a bad report about the land that they had spied out, saying: “The land that we passed through to spy out is a land that devours its inhabitants, and all the people whom we saw in it are men of extraordinary size. 33 And there we saw the Nephʹi·lim, the sons of Aʹnak, who are from* the Nephʹi·lim, and in comparison we seemed like grasshoppers, both to us and to them.”

Or “descendants of.”

^ (Num. 14:1-4) Then all the assembly raised their voice, and the people continued crying out and weeping all through that night. 2 All the Israelites began to murmur against Moses and Aaron, and the whole assembly spoke against them, saying: “If only we had died in the land of Egypt, or if only we had died in this wilderness! 3 Why is Jehovah bringing us to this land to fall by the sword? Our wives and children will become plunder. Is it not better for us to return to Egypt?” 4 They were even saying to one another: “Let us appoint a leader and return to Egypt!”

^ (Num. 14:6-10) Joshua the son of Nun and Caʹleb the son of Je·phunʹneh, who were among those who spied out the land, ripped their garments apart, 7 and they said this to all the assembly of the Israelites: “The land that we passed through to spy out is a very, very good land. 8 If Jehovah is pleased with us, he will certainly bring us into this land and give it to us, a land that is flowing with milk and honey. 9 But you must not rebel against Jehovah, and you must not fear the people of the land, for we will devour them.* Their protection has been removed from them, and Jehovah is with us. Do not fear them.” 10 However, all the assembly talked of stoning them. But Jehovah’s glory appeared on the tent of meeting to all the people of Israel.

Lit., “for they are bread to us.”

Tuesday, June 23

Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.—[1 Cor. 15:33].

Most people have some good qualities, and many outside the congregation do not engage in blatant misconduct. If that is true of your acquaintances, can you assume that they are good associations? Ask yourself what effect their companionship will have on your relationship with Jehovah. Will they improve it? What is in their heart? For example, are their conversations almost exclusively about fashion, money, gadgets, entertainment, or other material pursuits? Does their speech often include disparaging comments about others or obscene jesting? Jesus aptly warned: “Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks.” ([Matt. 12:34]) If you realize that your associates pose a threat to your good standing with Jehovah, act decisively by limiting and if necessary ending such friendships.—[Prov. 13:20]. w18.07 19 ¶11

^ (1 Cor. 15:33) Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.*

Or “corrupt good morals.”

^ (Matt. 12:34) Offspring of vipers, how can you speak good things when you are wicked? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks.

^ (Prov. 13:20) The one walking with the wise will become wise, But the one who has dealings with the stupid will fare badly.

Wednesday, June 24

Moses was by far the meekest of all the men.—[Num. 12:3].

When Moses was 80 years old, Jehovah assigned him to deliver Israel from bondage in Egypt. ([Ex. 3:10]) Several times, Moses tried to excuse himself. But Jehovah remained patient and even empowered Moses to perform miracles. ([Ex. 4:2-9,][21]) He could have frightened Moses into speedy submission. Instead, Jehovah was patient and kind, making an effort to reassure his modest and humble servant. Did this considerate approach work? Absolutely! Moses became an outstanding leader who tried to deal with others in the same mild and considerate way that Jehovah dealt with him. If you have a measure of authority, how important it is that you imitate Jehovah by being considerate, kind, and patient when dealing with those under your care! (Col. 3:19-21; 1 Pet. 5:1-3) When you strive to imitate Jehovah and the Greater Moses, Jesus Christ, you will be both approachable and refreshing to others.—Matt. 11:28, 29. w18.09 24-25 ¶7-10

^ (Num. 12:3) Now the man Moses was by far the meekest of all the men* on the face of the earth.

Or “was very humble (mild-tempered), more so than any other man.”

^ (Ex. 3:10) Now come, I will send you to Pharʹaoh, and you will bring my people the Israelites out of Egypt.”

^ (Ex. 4:2-9) Then Jehovah said to him: “What is that in your hand?” He answered: “A rod.” 3 He said: “Throw it on the ground.” So he threw it on the ground, and it became a serpent; and Moses fled from it. 4 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Reach out your hand and seize it by the tail.” So he reached out and seized it, and it became a rod in his hand. 5 God then said: “This is so that they may believe that Jehovah the God of their forefathers, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob, has appeared to you.” 6 Jehovah said to him once more: “Put your hand, please, into the upper fold of your garment.” So he put his hand into the fold of his garment. When he drew it out, why, his hand was stricken with leprosy like snow! 7 Then he said: “Return your hand into the upper fold of your garment.” So he returned his hand into his garment. When he drew it out of the garment, it was restored like the rest of his flesh! 8 He said: “If they will not believe you or pay attention to the first sign, then they will certainly heed the next sign. 9 Still, even if they will not believe these two signs and refuse to listen to your voice, you will take some water from the Nile River and pour it out on the dry land, and the water that you take from the Nile will become blood on the dry land.”

^ (Ex. 4:21) Then Jehovah said to Moses: “After you have returned to Egypt, see that you perform before Pharʹaoh all the miracles that I have empowered you to do. But I will allow his heart to become obstinate, and he will not send the people away.

^ (Col. 3:19-21) You husbands, keep on loving your wives and do not be bitterly angry* with them. 20 You children, be obedient to your parents in everything, for this is well-pleasing to the Lord. 21 You fathers, do not be exasperating* your children, so that they do not become downhearted.*

Or “be harsh.”

Or “provoking; irritating.”

Or “discouraged.”

^ (1 Pet. 5:1-3) Therefore, as a fellow elder, a witness of the sufferings of the Christ and a sharer of the glory that is to be revealed, I make this appeal* to the elders among you: 2 Shepherd the flock of God under your care, serving as overseers,* not under compulsion, but willingly before God; not for love of dishonest gain, but eagerly; 3 not lording it over those who are God’s inheritance, but becoming examples to the flock.

Or “exhortation.”

Or “carefully watching over it.”

^ (Matt. 11:28, 29) Come to me, all you who are toiling* and loaded down, and I will refresh you. 29 Take my yoke upon you and learn from me,* for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and you will find refreshment for yourselves.

Or “struggling hard.” Or possibly, “weary; tired.”

Or “become my disciples (learners).”

Thursday, June 25

How good and how pleasant it is for brothers to dwell together in unity!—[Ps. 133:1].

Why not be resolved to have a positive influence, promoting unity among your brothers and sisters? If you are already doing so, that is commendable. Could you “widen out,” that is, do it to a greater extent and more consistently? (2 Cor. 6:11-13, ftn.) What about increasing your efforts to let the light of Bible truth shine in your neighborhood? Your kind words and deeds may well attract a neighbor to the truth. Ask yourself: ‘How do my neighbors view me? Do I keep my home and property tidy, thus reflecting well on the neighborhood? Do I take the initiative to be helpful to others?’ When you are in conversation with other Witnesses, why not draw them out on how their kindness and good conduct have affected relatives, neighbors, workmates, or schoolmates? It is quite likely that you will hear positive experiences.—[Eph. 5:9]. w18.06 24 ¶13-14

^ (Ps. 133:1) Look! How good and how pleasant it is For brothers to dwell together in unity!

^ (2 Cor. 6:11-13) We have opened our mouth to speak* to you, Corinthians, and we have opened wide our heart. 12 We are not restricted in* our affections for you, but you are restricted in your own tender affections for us. 13 So in response—I speak as to my children—you too open your hearts wide.*

Or “have spoken openly.”

Or “cramped for room in.”

Or “you too widen out.”

^ (Eph. 5:9) for the fruitage of the light consists of every sort of goodness and righteousness and truth.

Friday, June 26

The hour is coming when everyone who kills you will think he has offered a sacred service to God.—[John 16:2].

That warning was true of those who murdered the disciple Stephen, and it has been true of others like them. ([Acts 6:8,][12;][7:54-60]) How ironic that in committing such evil crimes as murder, religious fanatics violate the very laws of the One whom they claim to worship! ([Ex. 20:13]) Clearly, their consciences are treacherous guides! How can we prevent our conscience from becoming ineffective? The laws and principles contained in God’s Word are “beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight, for disciplining in righteousness.” ([2 Tim. 3:16]) Therefore, by diligently studying the Bible, meditating on what it says, and applying it in our lives, we can train our conscience to be more sensitive to God’s thinking, and it can thus serve as a reliable guide. w18.06 16-17 ¶3-4

^ (John 16:2) Men will expel you from the synagogue. In fact, the hour is coming when everyone who kills you will think he has offered a sacred service to God.

^ (Acts 6:8) Now Stephen, full of divine favor and power, was performing great wonders and signs among the people.

^ (Acts 6:12) And they stirred up the people, the elders, and the scribes, and coming upon him suddenly, they forcibly seized him and led him to the Sanʹhe·drin.

^ (Acts 7:54-60) Well, at hearing these things, they were infuriated in their hearts and began to grind their teeth at him. 55 But he, being full of holy spirit, gazed into heaven and caught sight of God’s glory and of Jesus standing at God’s right hand, 56 and he said: “Look! I see the heavens opened up and the Son of man standing at God’s right hand.” 57 At this they cried out at the top of their voices and put their hands over their ears and rushed at him all together. 58 After throwing him outside the city, they began stoning him. The witnesses laid down their outer garments at the feet of a young man called Saul. 59 As they were stoning Stephen, he made this appeal: “Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.” 60 Then, kneeling down, he cried out with a strong voice: “Jehovah, do not charge this sin against them.” And after saying this, he fell asleep in death.

^ (Ex. 20:13) “You must not murder.

^ (2 Tim. 3:16) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness,

Or “correcting.”

Saturday, June 27

Accept . . . the sword of the spirit, that is, God’s word.—[Eph. 6:17].

The sword used by Roman infantrymen at the time Paul wrote his letter was about 20 inches (50 cm) long and was designed for hand-to-hand combat. One reason that Roman soldiers were so effective is that they practiced with their weapons every day. Paul likens God’s Word to a sword that Jehovah has given us. But we must learn to use it skillfully when defending our beliefs—or when adjusting our own thinking. (2 Cor. 10:4, 5;[2 Tim. 2:15]) There is no need to feel intimidated by Satan and the demons. They are formidable but not unbeatable. And they are mortal. Soon, during the Thousand Year Reign of Christ, they will be confined to a state of complete inactivity, after which they will be destroyed. ([Rev. 20:1-3,][7-10]) We know our enemy, his tactics, and his intentions. With Jehovah’s help, we can stand firm against him! w18.05 30 ¶15; 31 ¶19-21

^ (Eph. 6:17) Also, accept the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the spirit, that is, God’s word,

^ (2 Cor. 10:4, 5) For the weapons of our warfare are not fleshly, but powerful by God for overturning strongly entrenched things. 5 For we are overturning reasonings and every lofty thing raised up against the knowledge of God, and we are bringing every thought into captivity to make it obedient to the Christ;

^ (2 Tim. 2:15) Do your utmost to present yourself approved to God, a workman with nothing to be ashamed of, handling the word of the truth aright.

^ (Rev. 20:1-3) And I saw an angel coming down out of heaven with the key of the abyss and a great chain in his hand. 2 He seized the dragon, the original serpent, who is the Devil and Satan, and bound him for 1,000 years. 3 And he hurled him into the abyss and shut it and sealed it over him, so that he would not mislead the nations anymore until the 1,000 years were ended. After this he must be released for a little while.

^ (Rev. 20:7-10) Now as soon as the 1,000 years have ended, Satan will be released from his prison, 8 and he will go out to mislead those nations in the four corners of the earth, Gog and Maʹgog, to gather them together for the war. The number of these is as the sand of the sea. 9 And they advanced over the whole earth and encircled the camp of the holy ones and the beloved city. But fire came down out of heaven and consumed them. 10 And the Devil who was misleading them was hurled into the lake of fire and sulfur, where both the wild beast and the false prophet already were; and they will be tormented* day and night forever and ever.

Or “restrained; imprisoned.”

Sunday, June 28

The serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die.”—[Gen. 3:4].

Adam no doubt knew that serpents cannot talk. So he may have surmised that a spirit creature had spoken with Eve through the serpent. ([Gen. 3:1-6]) Adam and Eve knew virtually nothing about this spirit. Even so, Adam made a conscious choice to turn his back on his loving heavenly Father and join this stranger in resisting God’s will. ([1 Tim. 2:14]) Immediately, Jehovah began to reveal information about this enemy who had corrupted Adam and Eve, promising that this wicked one would eventually be destroyed. But Jehovah also warned that for a time, the spirit creature who spoke through the serpent would have the power to oppose those who love God. ([Gen. 3:15]) In his wisdom, Jehovah has never told us the personal name of the angelic son who rebelled against him. And God chose not to reveal even the descriptive name of that enemy until some 2,500 years after the initial rebellion.—[Job 1:6]. w18.05 22 ¶1-2

^ (Gen. 3:4) At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die.

^ (Gen. 3:1-6) Now the serpent was the most cautious* of all the wild animals of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it said to the woman: “Did God really say that you must not eat from every tree of the garden?” 2 At this the woman said to the serpent: “We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden. 3 But God has said about the fruit of the tree that is in the middle of the garden: ‘You must not eat from it, no, you must not touch it; otherwise you will die.’” 4 At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die. 5 For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.” 6 Consequently, the woman saw that the tree was good for food and that it was something desirable to the eyes, yes, the tree was pleasing to look at. So she began taking of its fruit and eating it. Afterward, she also gave some to her husband when he was with her, and he began eating it.

Or “shrewdest; craftiest.”

^ (1 Tim. 2:14) Also, Adam was not deceived, but the woman was thoroughly deceived and became a transgressor.

^ (Gen. 3:15) And I will put enmity* between you and the woman and between your offspring* and her offspring.* He will crush* your head, and you will strike* him in the heel.”

Or “hostility.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “bruise; strike.”

Or “bruise; crush.”

^ (Job 1:6) Now the day came when the sons of the true God* entered to take their station before Jehovah, and Satan also entered among them.

A Hebrew idiom that refers to angelic sons of God.

Monday, June 29

These are the ones who . . . bear fruit with endurance.—[Luke 8:15].

If you have ever felt discouraged when preaching in less responsive territories, you will relate to the apostle Paul. During his approximately 30-year-long ministry, he helped numerous individuals to become disciples of Christ. ([Acts 14:21;] 2 Cor. 3:2, 3) Still, he did not succeed in moving many Jews to become true worshippers. On the contrary, most rebuffed Paul, and some even persecuted him. ([Acts 14:19;][17:1,][4, 5,][13]) How did that adverse reaction from the Jews affect Paul? He freely admitted: “I am telling the truth in Christ . . . I have great grief and unceasing pain in my heart.” ([Rom. 9:1-3]) Why did Paul experience such feelings? His heart was in the preaching work. He preached to the Jews out of deep concern for them. So it pained Paul to see them reject God’s mercy. Like Paul, we preach to people out of heartfelt concern.—[Matt. 22:39;][1 Cor. 11:1]. w18.05 13 ¶4-5

^ (Luke 8:15) As for that on the fine soil, these are the ones who, after hearing the word with a fine and good heart, retain it and bear fruit with endurance.

^ (Acts 14:21) After declaring the good news to that city and making quite a few disciples, they returned to Lysʹtra, I·coʹni·um, and Antioch.

^ (2 Cor. 3:2, 3) You yourselves are our letter, inscribed on our hearts and known and being read by all mankind. 3 For you are shown to be a letter of Christ written by us as ministers, inscribed not with ink but with the spirit of a living God, not on stone tablets but on fleshly tablets, on hearts.

^ (Acts 14:19) But Jews arrived from Antioch and I·coʹni·um and persuaded the crowds, and they stoned Paul and dragged him outside the city, imagining that he was dead.

^ (Acts 17:1) They now traveled through Am·phipʹo·lis and Ap·ol·loʹni·a and came to Thes·sa·lo·niʹca, where there was a synagogue of the Jews.

^ (Acts 17:4, 5) As a result, some of them became believers and associated themselves with Paul and Silas, and so did a great multitude of the Greeks who worshipped God, along with quite a few of the principal women. 5 But the Jews, getting jealous, gathered together some wicked men who were loitering at the marketplace and formed a mob and proceeded to throw the city into an uproar. They assaulted the house of Jaʹson and were seeking to have Paul and Silas brought out to the mob.

^ (Acts 17:13) But when the Jews from Thes·sa·lo·niʹca learned that the word of God was also being proclaimed by Paul in Be·roeʹa, they came there to incite and agitate the crowds.

^ (Rom. 9:1-3) I am telling the truth in Christ; I am not lying, as my conscience bears witness with me in holy spirit, 2 that I have great grief and unceasing pain in my heart. 3 For I could wish that I myself were separated from the Christ as the cursed one for the sake of my brothers, my relatives according to the flesh,

^ (Matt. 22:39) The second, like it, is this: ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’

^ (1 Cor. 11:1) Become imitators of me, just as I am of Christ.

Tuesday, June 30

Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down, but a good word cheers it up.—[Prov. 12:25].

Paul showed that even one who has the responsibility of encouraging others needs to be built up himself. To Christians living in Rome, he wrote: “I am longing to see you, that I may impart some spiritual gift to you for you to be made firm; or, rather, that we may have an interchange of encouragement by one another’s faith, both yours and mine.” (Rom. 1:11, 12) Yes, Paul, who gave outstanding encouragement to others, at times needed to be built up himself. (Rom. 15:30-32) Those who live a life of self-sacrifice should be commended. Brothers and sisters who remain single because they want to obey the admonition to marry “only in the Lord” make up another group that merits encouragement. ([1 Cor. 7:39]) Also, Christians who remain faithful through persecution or illness need to hear encouragement.—2 Thess. 1:3-5. w18.04 21 ¶3-5

^ (Prov. 12:25) Anxiety in a man’s heart weighs it down,* But a good word cheers it up.

Or “depresses him.”

^ (Rom. 1:11, 12) For I am longing to see you, that I may impart some spiritual gift to you for you to be made firm; 12 or, rather, that we may have an interchange of encouragement by one another’s faith, both yours and mine.

^ (Rom. 15:30-32) Now I urge you, brothers, through our Lord Jesus Christ and through the love of the spirit, that you exert yourselves with me in prayers to God for me, 31 that I may be rescued from the unbelievers in Ju·deʹa and that my ministry in behalf of Jerusalem may prove to be acceptable to the holy ones, 32 so that by God’s will I will come to you with joy and be refreshed together with you.

^ (1 Cor. 7:39) A wife is bound as long as her husband is alive. But if her husband should fall asleep in death, she is free to be married to whomever she wants, only in the Lord.

^ (2 Thess. 1:3-5) We are obligated always to give thanks to God for you, brothers. This is fitting, because your faith is growing exceedingly and the love of each and every one of you is increasing toward one another. 4 As a result we ourselves take pride in you among the congregations of God because of your endurance and faith in all your persecutions and the hardships* that you are suffering.* 5 This is a proof of the righteous judgment of God, leading to your being counted worthy of the Kingdom of God, for which you are indeed suffering.

Or “tribulations.”

Or “enduring.”

July

Wednesday, July 1

Keep perceiving what the will of Jehovah is.—[Eph. 5:17].

We are living in “critical times” that are “hard to deal with,” and life is going to become even more difficult before a new day dawns and true peace is restored to this earth. ([2 Tim. 3:1]) So we do well to ask ourselves, ‘Where am I looking for help and direction?’ Centuries ago, a psalmist acknowledged the need for us to raise our eyes to Jehovah for help in times of need. ([Ps. 123:1-4]) He compared our looking to Jehovah with the way a servant looks to his master. What did the psalmist mean by that? Well, not only does a servant look to his master for food and protection but the servant needs constantly to watch his master to discern his wishes and then to carry them out. In a similar way, we daily need to search God’s Word to ascertain what Jehovah’s will is for us personally and then to follow that direction. Only then can we be sure that Jehovah will show us favor in our time of need. w18.07 12 ¶1-2

^ (Eph. 5:17) On this account stop being unreasonable, but keep perceiving what the will of Jehovah* is.

See App. A5.

^ (2 Tim. 3:1) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here.

^ (Ps. 123:1-4) To you I raise my eyes, You who are enthroned in the heavens.  2 As the eyes of servants look to the hand of their master, And the eyes of a servant girl to the hand of her mistress, So our eyes look to Jehovah our God Until he shows us favor.  3 Show us favor, O Jehovah, show us favor, For we have had our full share of contempt.  4 We have had our full share of* ridicule from the self-assured And the contempt of the arrogant.

Or “Our soul has had more than enough.”

Thursday, July 2

If the Son sets you free, you will be truly free.—[John 8:36].

Jesus was talking about liberation from the greatest bondage and oppression that humankind has ever experienced—being “a slave of sin.” ([John 8:34]) Not only can sin lead us to doing what is bad but it can also prevent us from doing what we know is right or from living up to what we know we are capable of. In that sense we are slaves of sin, and the outcome is frustration, pain, suffering, and finally death. ([Rom. 6:23]) It is only when the shackles of sin are thrown off that we can hope to have the true freedom that our first human parents once enjoyed. Jesus’ statement “if you remain in my word” implies that there are certain requirements or boundaries for being set free by him. ([John 8:31]) As dedicated Christians, we have disowned ourselves and have chosen to live within the bounds of Christ’s teachings as his disciples. ([Matt. 16:24]) Just as Jesus promised, we will be truly free when the benefits of his ransom sacrifice are fully applied to us. w18.04 7 ¶14-16

^ (John 8:36) So if the Son sets you free, you will be truly free.

^ (John 8:34) Jesus answered them: “Most truly I say to you, every doer of sin is a slave of sin.

^ (Rom. 6:23) For the wages sin pays is death, but the gift God gives is everlasting life by Christ Jesus our Lord.

^ (John 8:31) Then Jesus went on to say to the Jews who had believed him: “If you remain in my word, you are really my disciples,

^ (Matt. 16:24) Then Jesus said to his disciples: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake and keep following me.

Friday, July 3

You alone truly know the human heart.—2 Chron. 6:30.

Jehovah shows consideration for the feelings of his people—even when their thinking is not always sound. Consider the case of Jonah. God sent this prophet to proclaim a message of judgment against the Ninevites. When they repented, God chose to spare them. However, Jonah was not happy about this outcome. He “became hot with anger” because his prophecy of doom did not come true. But Jehovah was patient with Jonah and helped him to adjust his thinking. (Jonah 3:10–4:11) In time, Jonah got the point, and he was even used by Jehovah to record this account for our benefit. ([Rom. 15:4]) Jehovah’s dealings with his people assure us that he has empathy for his servants. He is aware of the pain and suffering of each one of us. He understands our intimate thoughts, our deepest emotions, and our limitations. And “he will not let [us] be tempted beyond what [we] can bear.” ([1 Cor. 10:13]) How comforting that assurance is! w19.03 16 ¶6-7

^ (2 Chron. 6:30) then may you hear from the heavens, your dwelling place, and may you forgive; and reward each one according to all his ways, for you know his heart (you alone truly know the human heart),

^ (Rom. 15:4) For all the things that were written beforehand were written for our instruction, so that through our endurance and through the comfort from the Scriptures we might have hope.

^ (1 Cor. 10:13) No temptation has come upon you except what is common to men. But God is faithful, and he will not let you be tempted beyond what you can bear, but along with the temptation he will also make the way out so that you may be able to endure it.

Saturday, July 4

All things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes of the one to whom we must give an account.—[Heb. 4:13].

Under the Mosaic Law, appointed older men were responsible for handling not only spiritual matters but also civil and criminal cases. Consider a few examples. If an Israelite killed someone, he was not arbitrarily executed. The elders of his city would investigate the circumstances before deciding if the death penalty was appropriate. (Deut. 19:2-7,[11-13]) The elders also judged numerous aspects of daily life—from resolving public controversies over property to settling private marital disputes. ([Ex. 21:35;] Deut. 22:13-19) When the elders were fair and the Israelites obeyed the Law, everyone benefited, and the nation brought honor to Jehovah. (Lev. 20:7, 8; Isa. 48:17, 18) From this we see that every aspect of our life is important to Jehovah. He wants us to be just and loving when dealing with others. And he takes notice of what we say and do, even in the privacy of our home. w19.02 23 ¶16-18

^ (Heb. 4:13) And there is not a creation that is hidden from his sight, but all things are naked and openly exposed to the eyes of the one to whom we must give an account.

^ (Deut. 19:2-7) you should set apart three cities in the midst of your land that Jehovah your God is giving you to possess. 3 You should divide the territory of the land that Jehovah your God has given you to possess into three parts, and prepare the roads so that any manslayer can flee to one of those cities. 4 “Now this is what should take place regarding the manslayer who may flee there in order to live: When he strikes his fellow man unintentionally and he did not previously hate him; 5 as when he goes with his fellow man into the forest to gather wood and he raises his hand to cut the tree with the ax, but the axhead flies off the handle and hits his fellow man and he dies, the manslayer should flee to one of these cities to live. 6 Otherwise, in the heat of anger,* the avenger of blood may chase after the manslayer, overtake him, and kill him, because the distance to the city was too far. However, he did not deserve to die, since he did not previously hate his fellow man. 7 That is why I am commanding you: ‘Set three cities apart.’

Lit., “because his heart is hot.”

^ (Deut. 19:11-13) “But if a man hated his fellow man and he was waiting to attack him and he fatally wounded him* and he died, and the man has fled to one of these cities, 12 the elders of his city should then summon him from there and deliver him into the hand of the avenger of blood, and he must die. 13 You* should not feel sorry for him, and you must remove the guilt of innocent blood out of Israel, so that it may go well for you.

Or “his soul.”

Lit., “Your eye.”

^ (Ex. 21:35) If a man’s bull hurts another’s bull and it dies, then they must sell the live bull and divide the price paid for it; they should also divide the dead animal.

^ (Deut. 22:13-19) “If a man takes a wife and has relations with her but then comes to hate her* 14 and he accuses her of misconduct and gives her a bad name by saying: ‘I have taken this woman, but when I had relations with her, I did not find evidence that she was a virgin,’ 15 the father and mother of the girl should produce the evidence of the girl’s virginity for the elders at the gate of the city. 16 The girl’s father must say to the elders, ‘I gave my daughter to this man as a wife, but he hates* her 17 and is accusing her of misconduct by saying: “I have found out that your daughter does not have evidence of virginity.” Now this is the evidence of my daughter’s virginity.’ They will then spread out the cloth before the elders of the city. 18 The city elders will take the man and discipline him. 19 They will fine him 100 silver shekels* and give them to the girl’s father, because the man defamed a virgin of Israel, and she will continue to be his wife. He will not be allowed to divorce her as long as he lives.

Or “then rejects her.”

Or “rejects.”

A shekel equaled 11.4 g (0.367 oz t). See App. B14.

^ (Lev. 20:7, 8) “‘You must sanctify yourselves and become holy, because I am Jehovah your God. 8 And you must keep my statutes and carry them out. I am Jehovah, who is sanctifying you.

^ (Isa. 48:17, 18) This is what Jehovah says, your Repurchaser, the Holy One of Israel: “I, Jehovah, am your God, The One teaching you to benefit yourself,* The One guiding you in the way you should walk. 18 If only you would pay attention to my commandments! Then your peace would become just like a river And your righteousness like the waves of the sea.

Or “for your own good.”

Sunday, July 5

He let himself be afflicted, but he would not open his mouth.—[Isa. 53:7].

When we are under stress, it is difficult to be meek. Our words may become harsh and our tone cold. If you have ever felt stressed, consider the example of Jesus. During the final months of his life on earth, Jesus was under intense stress. He knew that he would be executed and that he would suffer terribly. (John 3:14, 15;[Gal. 3:13]) Some months before his death, he said that he was distressed. ([Luke 12:50]) And just days before his death, Jesus said: “I am troubled.” We can sense his humility and his submissiveness to God as he poured out his feelings in prayer. (John 12:27, 28) When the time came, Jesus courageously handed himself over to God’s enemies, who executed him in the most agonizing and humiliating way possible. Despite the stress, despite the suffering, Jesus meekly did God’s will. Without a doubt, we can say that Jesus is the most outstanding example of someone showing meekness under stress!—[Isa. 53:10]. w19.02 11 ¶14-15

^ (Isa. 53:7) He was oppressed and he let himself be afflicted, But he would not open his mouth. He was brought like a sheep to the slaughter, Like a ewe that is silent before its shearers, And he would not open his mouth.

^ (John 3:14, 15) And just as Moses lifted up the serpent in the wilderness, so the Son of man must be lifted up, 15 so that everyone believing in him may have everlasting life.

^ (Gal. 3:13) Christ purchased us, releasing us from the curse of the Law by becoming a curse instead of us, because it is written: “Accursed is every man hung upon a stake.”

^ (Luke 12:50) Indeed, I have a baptism with which to be baptized, and how I am distressed until it is finished!

^ (John 12:27, 28) Now I am troubled, and what should I say? Father, save me out of this hour. Nevertheless, this is why I have come to this hour. 28 Father, glorify your name.” Then a voice came out of heaven: “I have glorified it and will glorify it again.”

^ (Isa. 53:10) But it was Jehovah’s will* to crush him, and he let him become sick. If you will present his life* as a guilt offering, He will see his offspring,* he will prolong his days, And through him the delight* of Jehovah will have success.

Or “But Jehovah took delight.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “will; good pleasure.”

Monday, July 6

Let us consider one another so as to incite to love and fine works.—[Heb. 10:24].

To attend meetings regularly, we may need to demonstrate courage in the face of difficult circumstances. Some of our brothers and sisters attend meetings despite being burdened by grief, discouragement, or health problems. Others courageously attend meetings despite strong opposition from family members or governmental authorities. Think for a moment about how our example affects our brothers who are imprisoned for their faith. ([Heb. 13:3]) When they hear that we keep serving Jehovah in spite of our trials, they are strengthened to maintain their faith, courage, and integrity. When Paul was in prison in Rome, he rejoiced whenever he heard that his brothers were serving God faithfully. ([Phil. 1:3-5,][12-14]) Shortly before or just after his release, Paul wrote his letter to the Hebrews. In that letter he urged those faithful Christians to never forsake meeting together.—[Heb. 10:25]. w19.01 28 ¶9

^ (Heb. 10:24) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works,

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Heb. 13:3) Keep in mind those in prison,* as though you were imprisoned with them, and those being mistreated, since you yourselves also are in the body.*

Lit., “the bound ones; those in bonds.”

Or possibly, “as if you were suffering with them.”

^ (Phil. 1:3-5) I thank my God always when I remember you 4 in every supplication of mine for all of you. I offer each supplication with joy, 5 because of the contribution you have made to* the good news from the first day until this moment.

Or “because of your participation in furthering.”

^ (Phil. 1:12-14) Now I want you to know, brothers, that my situation has actually turned out for the advancement of the good news, 13 so that my prison bonds for the sake of Christ have become public knowledge among all the Prae·toʹri·an Guard and all the rest. 14 Now most of the brothers in the Lord have gained confidence because of my prison bonds, and they are showing all the more courage to speak the word of God fearlessly.

^ (Heb. 10:25) not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Tuesday, July 7

The whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.—[1 John 5:19].

Satan wants us to become like him—a rebel who ignores Jehovah’s standards and is motivated by selfishness. He surrounds us with people who are already corrupted by him and hopes that they will “spoil” or “corrupt” the way we think and act. ([1 Cor. 15:33]; ftn.) Satan also tries to infect our heart by getting us to trust human wisdom rather than Jehovah’s thinking. ([Col. 2:8]) Consider just one idea promoted by Satan—that getting rich should be a primary goal in life. Those who think this way might become wealthy, or they might not. Either way, they are in danger. Why? Because they may become so focused on making money that they will sacrifice their health, their family relationships, and even their friendship with God just to reach their goal. ([1 Tim. 6:10]) We can be grateful that our wise heavenly Father helps us to have a balanced view of money.—[Eccl. 7:12;][Luke 12:15]. w19.01 15 ¶6; 17 ¶9

^ (1 John 5:19) We know that we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one.

^ (1 Cor. 15:33) Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.*

Or “corrupt good morals.”

^ (Col. 2:8) Look out that no one takes you captive* by means of the philosophy and empty deception according to human tradition, according to the elementary things of the world and not according to Christ;

Or “carries you off as his prey.”

^ (1 Tim. 6:10) For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

^ (Eccl. 7:12) For wisdom is a protection just as money is a protection, but the advantage of knowledge is this: Wisdom preserves the life of its owner.

^ (Luke 12:15) Then he said to them: “Keep your eyes open and guard against every sort of greed, because even when a person has an abundance, his life does not result from the things he possesses.”

Wednesday, July 8

Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.—[Matt. 25:21].

Even before Jehovah’s Son came to earth and set a perfect example of how to impart encouragement, faithful servants of Jehovah were conscious of the need to be encouraging. When threatened by the Assyrians, Hezekiah assembled the military chiefs and the people of Judah to encourage them. “And the people were strengthened by [his] words.” (2 Chron. 32:6-8) Although in need of consolation himself, Job gave his three “troublesome comforters” a lesson in giving encouragement. He told them that if he had been in their place, he ‘would have strengthened them with the words of his mouth, and the consolation of his lips would have brought them relief.’ ([Job 16:1-5]) Finally, Job received encouragement from Elihu and from Jehovah himself.—Job 33:24, 25;[36:1,][11;][42:7,][10]. w18.04 16 ¶6; 17 ¶8-9

^ (Matt. 25:21) His master said to him: ‘Well done, good and faithful slave! You were faithful over a few things. I will appoint you over many things. Enter into the joy of your master.’*

Or “Rejoice with your master; Come and share your master’s happiness.”

^ (2 Chron. 32:6-8) He then appointed military chiefs over the people and assembled them at the public square of the city gate and encouraged them,* saying: 7 “Be courageous and strong. Do not be afraid or be terrified because of the king of As·syrʹi·a and all the multitude with him, for there are more with us than there are with him. 8 With him is an arm of flesh,* but with us is Jehovah our God to help us and to fight our battles.” And the people were strengthened by the words of King Hez·e·kiʹah of Judah.

Lit., “spoke to their heart.”

Or “is human strength.”

^ (Job 16:1-5) Job said in reply:  2 “I have heard many things like these before. All of you are troublesome comforters!  3 Is there an end to empty* words? What provokes you to answer this way?  4 I could also speak as you do. If you were in my place,* I could make persuasive speeches against you And shake my head at you.  5 Instead, though, I would strengthen you with the words of my mouth, And the consolation of my lips would bring relief.

Or “blustery.”

Or “If your soul were in place of my soul.”

^ (Job 33:24, 25) Then God shows him favor and says, ‘Spare him from going down into the pit!* I have found a ransom! 25 Let his flesh become fresher* than in youth; Let him return to the days of his youthful vigor.’

Or “grave.”

Or “healthier.”

^ (Job 36:1) E·liʹhu continued:

^ (Job 36:11) If they obey and serve him, They will live out their days in prosperity, And their years will be pleasant.

^ (Job 42:7) After Jehovah had spoken these words to Job, Jehovah said to Elʹi·phaz the Teʹman·ite: “My anger burns against you and your two companions, for you have not spoken the truth about me as my servant Job has.

^ (Job 42:10) After Job had prayed for his companions, Jehovah removed Job’s tribulation and restored his prosperity.* Jehovah gave him double what he had before.

Lit., “Jehovah turned back the captivity of Job.”

Thursday, July 9

I will fortify you, yes, I will help you.—[Isa. 41:10].

Isaiah had already described how Jehovah would fortify, or strengthen, his people, saying: “Jehovah will come with power, and his arm will rule for him.” ([Isa. 40:10]) The Bible often uses the word “arm” symbolically to signify power. So the statement that Jehovah’s “arm will rule” reminds us that Jehovah is a powerful King. He used his unbeatable strength to support and defend his servants in the past, and he continues to strengthen and protect those who trust in him today. (Deut. 1:30, 31;[Isa. 43:10], ftn.) Especially when enemies persecute us, Jehovah keeps his promise: “I will fortify you.” In some parts of the world today, our enemies are trying hard to stop our preaching work or ban our organization. Even so, we are not overly anxious about such attacks. Jehovah has given us a guarantee that fills us with strength and confidence. He promises us: “No weapon formed against you will have any success.”—[Isa. 54:17]. w19.01 5-6 ¶12-13

^ (Isa. 41:10) Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.’

^ (Isa. 40:10) Look! The Sovereign Lord Jehovah will come with power, And his arm will rule for him. Look! His reward is with him, And the wage he pays is before him.

^ (Deut. 1:30, 31) Jehovah your God will go before you and will fight for you, just as he did in Egypt before your very eyes. 31 And you saw in the wilderness how Jehovah your God carried you just as a man carries his son, everywhere you went until you came to this place.’

^ (Isa. 43:10) “You are my witnesses,” declares Jehovah, “Yes, my servant whom I have chosen, So that you may know and have faith in me* And understand that I am the same One. Before me no God was formed, And after me there has been none.

Or “and trust me.”

^ (Isa. 54:17) No weapon formed against you will have any success, And you will condemn any tongue that rises up against you in the judgment. This is the heritage* of the servants of Jehovah, And their righteousness is from me,” declares Jehovah.

Or “inheritance.”

Friday, July 10

Happy are those conscious of their spiritual need.—[Matt. 5:3].

Unlike the animals, you have a spiritual need, which only your Creator can satisfy. ([Matt. 4:4]) When you listen appreciatively to him, you gain insight, wisdom, and happiness. God satisfies your spiritual need by means of his Word and the abundance of spiritual food that he provides through “the faithful and discreet slave.” ([Matt. 24:45]) And how varied and rich that food is! (Isa. 65:13, 14) The spiritual food that God provides will give you wisdom and thinking ability, which can protect you in many ways. (Prov. 2:10-14) For example, these qualities open your eyes to false teachings, such as the view that there is no Creator. They protect you against the lie that money and possessions are the key to happiness. And they help you to recognize and resist wrong desires and self-destructive behavior. So continue to search for godly wisdom and thinking ability, viewing them as treasures! w18.12 20 ¶6-7

^ (Matt. 5:3) “Happy are those conscious of their spiritual need, since the Kingdom of the heavens belongs to them.

^ (Matt. 4:4) But he answered: “It is written: ‘Man must live, not on bread alone, but on every word that comes from Jehovah’s mouth.’”

^ (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

^ (Isa. 65:13, 14) Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: “Look! My servants will eat, but you will go hungry. Look! My servants will drink, but you will go thirsty. Look! My servants will rejoice, but you will suffer shame. 14 Look! My servants will shout joyfully because of the good condition of the heart, But you will cry out because of the pain of heart And you will wail because of a broken spirit.

^ (Prov. 2:10-14) When wisdom enters your heart And knowledge becomes pleasant to your soul,* 11 Thinking ability will keep watch over you, And discernment will safeguard you, 12 To save you from the bad course, From the man speaking perverse things, 13 From those leaving the upright paths To walk in the ways of darkness, 14 From those who rejoice in wrongdoing, Who find joy in the perverseness of evil,

See Glossary.

Saturday, July 11

The days of my people will be like the days of a tree.—[Isa. 65:22].

Will the time come when our days “will be like the days of a tree”? Some trees live thousands of years. Humans would have to be healthy in order to have lifespans of such length. If they could live in the conditions that Isaiah foretold, it would be a dream come true, a paradise! And that prophecy will be fulfilled! Reflect on how the promises point to a future paradise: People of the whole earth will be blessed by God. No one will face danger from animals or beastlike humans. The blind, deaf, and lame will be cured. People will be able to build their own homes and enjoy growing wholesome food. They will live longer than trees. Yes, we find indications in the Bible that such a future is ahead. Still, some might claim that we are reading more into those prophecies than is justified. What solid reason do you have to look forward to a real paradise on earth? The greatest man who ever lived provided a solid reason.—[Luke 23:43]. w18.12 5 ¶13-15

^ (Isa. 65:22) They will not build for someone else to inhabit, Nor will they plant for others to eat. For the days of my people will be like the days of a tree, And the work of their hands my chosen ones will enjoy to the full.

^ (Luke 23:43) And he said to him: “Truly I tell you today, you will be with me in Paradise.”

Sunday, July 12

Be transformed by making your mind over.—[Rom. 12:2].

The mind is flexible and can keep changing. To a large extent, any such changes will be determined by what we allow into our mind and what we choose to dwell on. By dwelling or meditating on Jehovah’s way of thinking, we can prove to ourselves that his viewpoints are right. It will then be our natural desire to bring our thoughts into alignment with his. Note, however, that in order to make our mind over to Jehovah’s way of thinking, we need to “stop being molded by this system.” We must stop taking into our minds ideas or viewpoints that are in opposition to God’s. The importance of this preliminary step can be illustrated with food. A person might seek to improve his health by eating food that is nutritious. But of what value would that be if he is also ingesting regular doses of contaminated food? Similarly, feeding on Jehovah’s thoughts will be of limited value if we are corrupting our mind with worldly ideas. w18.11 21 ¶14-15

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

Monday, July 13

Stand firm . . . with the belt of truth fastened around your waist.—[Eph. 6:14].

We must be firmly resolved to live in harmony with the truth day by day. Wear the belt of truth around your waist. In Bible times, the belt of a soldier supported and protected his waist and his internal organs. For his belt to provide protection, however, it had to be tight. A loose belt gave little support. How does our spiritual belt of truth protect us? If we keep it wrapped tightly around us like a belt, the truth will guard us from faulty reasoning and will help us to make sound decisions. When we are tempted or under trial, Bible truth will strengthen our resolve to do what is right. Just as a soldier would never have thought of going into battle without his belt, we must be determined never to loosen or remove our belt of truth. Rather, we do all we can to keep it tight around our body by living in harmony with the truth. w18.11 12 ¶15

^ (Eph. 6:14) Stand firm, therefore, with the belt of truth fastened around your waist, wearing the breastplate of righteousness,

Tuesday, July 14

Buy truth and never sell it.—[Prov. 23:23].

We do not find the truth in God’s Word without effort. We must be willing to make whatever sacrifices are needed to obtain it. As the wise writer of Proverbs notes, once we “buy,” or acquire, “truth,” we must be careful not to “sell,” or lose, it. Even something that is free may come at a cost. The Hebrew word translated “buy” at Proverbs 23:23 can also mean “acquire.” Both words imply making an effort or exchanging something for an item of value. We might illustrate the idea of buying truth this way. Let us say that a market advertises “Free Bananas.” Will those bananas miraculously appear on our table? No. We have to make the effort to go to the market to pick them up. Are the bananas free? Yes, but we must expend the effort and take the time to go to the market. Similarly, we do not need money to buy truth. However, we must make an effort to obtain it. w18.11 4 ¶4-5

^ (Prov. 23:23) Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding.

Or “Acquire.”

^ (Prov. 23:23) Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding.

Or “Acquire.”

Wednesday, July 15

His face shone as the sun, and his outer garments became brilliant.—[Matt. 17:2].

Jesus had invited Peter, James, and John to accompany him up into a high mountain. While there, they saw a remarkable vision. Jesus’ face shone brightly and his clothes glistened. Two figures, representing Moses and Elijah, began talking to Jesus about his coming death and resurrection. ([Luke 9:29-32]) Next, a bright cloud covered them, and they heard a voice from the cloud—God’s voice! The vision gave a preview of Jesus’ future glory and power as King of God’s Kingdom. No doubt, Christ was encouraged and fortified for the sufferings and painful death he would endure. The vision also built up the disciples’ faith and strengthened them for the tests of integrity and years of hard work that lay ahead. Some 30 years later, the apostle Peter referred to the vision of the transfiguration, showing that the vision was still vivid in his mind.—2 Pet. 1:16-18. w19.03 10 ¶7-8

^ (Matt. 17:2) And he was transfigured before them; his face shone as the sun, and his outer garments became brilliant* as the light.

Or “white.”

^ (Luke 9:29-32) And as he was praying, the appearance of his face changed and his clothing became glitteringly white.* 30 And look! two men were conversing with him; they were Moses and E·liʹjah. 31 These appeared with glory and began talking about his departure, which he was about to fulfill at Jerusalem. 32 Now Peter and those with him were weighed down with sleep, but when they became fully awake, they saw his glory and the two men standing with him.

Or “as bright as a flash of lightning.”

^ (2 Pet. 1:16-18) No, it was not by following artfully contrived false stories that we made known to you the power and presence of our Lord Jesus Christ, but rather, we were eyewitnesses of his magnificence. 17 For he received from God the Father honor and glory when words such as these* were conveyed to him by the magnificent glory: “This is my Son, my beloved, whom I myself have approved.” 18 Yes, these words we heard coming from heaven while we were with him in the holy mountain.

Lit., “such a voice.”

Thursday, July 16

We recommend ourselves as God’s ministers, . . . by truthful speech.—[2 Cor. 6:4,][7].

What is one way that true Christians distinguish themselves from members of false religions? We “speak the truth.” (Zech. 8:16, 17) We will tell the truth in ways big and small—to strangers, coworkers, friends, and loved ones. What if you are a young person who wants to fit in with your peers? Make sure that you never lead a double life, appearing to be chaste when around family and the congregation but acting entirely different when around worldly youths and on social media. That is living a lie, playing false to your parents, to fellow worshippers, and to God. ([Ps. 26:4, 5]) Jehovah knows when we are only ‘honoring him with our lips, but our heart is far removed from him.’ ([Mark 7:6]) How much better it is to do as the proverb says: “Let your heart not envy sinners, but be in the fear of Jehovah all day long.”—[Prov. 23:17]. w18.10 9 ¶14-15

^ (2 Cor. 6:4) but in every way we recommend ourselves as God’s ministers, by the endurance of much, by tribulations, by times of need, by difficulties,

^ (2 Cor. 6:7) by truthful speech, by God’s power; through the weapons of righteousness in the right hand* and in the left,*

Perhaps for offense.

Perhaps for defense.

^ (Zech. 8:16, 17) “‘These are the things you should do: Speak the truth with one another, and the judgments in your gates must promote truth and peace. 17 Do not scheme calamity against one another in your hearts, and do not love any false oath; for these are all things that I hate,’ declares Jehovah.”

^ (Ps. 26:4, 5) I do not associate* with deceitful men, And I avoid those who hide what they are.*  5 I hate the company of evil men, And I refuse to associate* with the wicked.

Lit., “sit.”

Or “I do not mingle with hypocrites.”

Lit., “sit.”

^ (Mark 7:6) He said to them: “Isaiah aptly prophesied about you hypocrites, as it is written, ‘This people honor me with their lips, but their hearts are far removed from me.

^ (Prov. 23:17) Let your heart not envy sinners, But be in the fear of Jehovah all day long,

Friday, July 17

God is love, and the one who remains in love remains in union with God and God remains in union with him.—[1 John 4:16].

God’s people are a spiritual family—one marked by love. ([1 John 4:21]) That love is usually reflected, not in rare heroic acts, but in countless smaller ways, such as by thoughtful words and kind deeds. When we treat others kindly and considerately, we “become imitators of God, as beloved children.” ([Eph. 5:1]) Jesus perfectly imitated his Father. “Come to me, all you who are toiling and loaded down,” said Jesus, “and I will refresh you . . . , for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart.” (Matt. 11:28, 29) When we imitate Christ’s example by “[showing] consideration to the lowly one,” we receive our heavenly Father’s favor and find great happiness. ([Ps. 41:1]) So, let us manifest our love by continuing to show consideration for others in the family, in the congregation, and in the field ministry. w18.09 28 ¶1-2

^ (1 John 4:16) And we have come to know and believe the love that God has for us. God is love, and the one who remains in love remains in union with God and God remains in union with him.

^ (1 John 4:21) And we have this commandment from him, that whoever loves God must also love his brother.

^ (Eph. 5:1) Therefore, become imitators of God, as beloved children,

^ (Matt. 11:28, 29) Come to me, all you who are toiling* and loaded down, and I will refresh you. 29 Take my yoke upon you and learn from me,* for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and you will find refreshment for yourselves.

Or “struggling hard.” Or possibly, “weary; tired.”

Or “become my disciples (learners).”

^ (Ps. 41:1) Happy is anyone who shows consideration to the lowly one; Jehovah will rescue him in the day of calamity.

Saturday, July 18

We are God’s fellow workers.—[1 Cor. 3:9].

When disasters strike, God’s people have opportunities to work with God by helping their brothers in practical ways. For example, they give financial support to those affected. (John 13:34, 35; Acts 11:27-30) Another practical way is by assisting with cleaning or reconstruction. Gabriela, a sister from Poland whose home was virtually destroyed by a flood, cheered up when brothers from nearby congregations came to her aid. “I don’t want to talk about what I lost—those are just material things,” she relates. “Rather, I want to tell you how much I gained. This experience reassured me that being a part of the Christian congregation is a unique privilege as well as a source of joy and happiness.” Many who receive help after a disaster say that they feel richer from the experience. And those who work with Jehovah to provide such help enjoy great satisfaction themselves.—[Acts 20:35;] 2 Cor. 9:6, 7. w18.08 26 ¶12

^ (1 Cor. 3:9) For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

^ (John 13:34, 35) I am giving you a new commandment, that you love one another; just as I have loved you, you also love one another. 35 By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (Acts 11:27-30) In those days prophets came down from Jerusalem to Antioch. 28 One of them named Agʹa·bus stood up and foretold through the spirit that a great famine was about to come on the entire inhabited earth, which, in fact, did take place in the time of Claudius. 29 So the disciples determined, each according to what he could afford, to send relief to the brothers living in Ju·deʹa; 30 and this they did, sending it to the elders by the hand of Barʹna·bas and Saul.

^ (Acts 20:35) I have shown you in all things that by working hard in this way, you must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

^ (2 Cor. 9:6, 7) But as to this, whoever sows sparingly will also reap sparingly, and whoever sows bountifully will also reap bountifully. 7 Let each one do just as he has resolved in his heart, not grudgingly* or under compulsion, for God loves a cheerful giver.

Or “reluctantly.”

Sunday, July 19

Safeguard your heart.—[Prov. 4:23].

If we are to succeed in safeguarding our heart, we must be able to identify dangers and react quickly to protect ourselves. The word translated “safeguard” reminds us of the work done by a watchman. In King Solomon’s day, watchmen stood guard on the walls of a city and sounded an alarm if they saw danger approaching. That mental picture helps us understand what we must do to stop Satan from corrupting our thinking. In ancient times, watchmen worked closely with city gatekeepers. (2 Sam. 18:24-26) Together, they helped protect the city by making sure that the gates were closed whenever an enemy came near. ([Neh. 7:1-3]) Our Bible-trained conscience can act as our watchman and warn us when Satan tries to invade our heart—in other words, when he tries to influence our thoughts, feelings, motives, or desires. Whenever our conscience sounds the alarm, we need to listen and shut the gate, so to speak. w19.01 17 ¶10-11

^ (Prov. 4:23) Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart, For out of it are the sources of life.

^ (2 Sam. 18:24-26) Now David was sitting between the two city gates, and the watchman went up to the roof of the gate by the wall. He looked up and saw a man running by himself. 25 So the watchman called out and told the king. The king said: “If he is by himself, he has news to tell.” As he came steadily nearer, 26 the watchman saw another man running. The watchman then called to the gatekeeper: “Look! Another man running by himself!” The king said: “This one is also bringing news.”

^ (Neh. 7:1-3) As soon as the wall had been rebuilt I set up the doors; then the gatekeepers, the singers, and the Levites were appointed. 2 I then put my brother Ha·naʹni in charge of Jerusalem, along with Han·a·niʹah the chief of the Fortress, for he was a most trustworthy man and feared the true God more than many others. 3 So I said to them: “The gates of Jerusalem should not be opened until the heat of the day, and while they are standing guard, they should shut the doors and bolt them. And assign the inhabitants of Jerusalem as guards, each to his assigned guardpost and each in front of his own house.”

Monday, July 20

Let them serve as ministers, as they are free from accusation.—[1 Tim. 3:10].

Younger men must be evaluated, not by personal or cultural viewpoints, but by the measuring stick of God’s Word. (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) Unscriptural cultural views can hold back qualified brothers. In one country, a well-qualified ministerial servant was entrusted with weighty responsibilities. Although the elders in his congregation agreed that the young brother met the Scriptural qualifications of an elder to a reasonable degree, he was not recommended for appointment. A few older elders insisted that the brother looked too young to be viewed as an elder. Sadly, the brother was held back from appointment simply because of the way he looked. Reports indicate that this way of thinking affects many in various parts of the world. How important it is that we rely on the Scriptures rather than on our own viewpoints! That is the only way to obey Jesus and stop judging by the outward appearance.—[John 7:24]. w18.08 12 ¶16-17

^ (1 Tim. 3:10) Also, let these be tested as to fitness* first; then let them serve as ministers, as they are free from accusation.

Or “tested as to whether they qualify.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

^ (John 7:24) Stop judging by the outward appearance, but judge with righteous judgment.”

Tuesday, July 21

When anyone replies to a matter before he hears the facts, it is foolish and humiliating.—[Prov. 18:13].

There is danger in quickly forwarding e-mails and text messages. In some lands, our work is under restriction or outright ban. Our opposers in such lands may purposely circulate reports designed to instill fear or to cause us to distrust one another. Consider what happened in the former Soviet Union. The secret police, known as the KGB, spread rumors that various prominent brothers had betrayed Jehovah’s people. Many put confidence in such false reports, and as a result, they separated themselves from Jehovah’s organization. How sad! Thankfully, many later returned, but some never did. Their faith was shipwrecked. ([1 Tim. 1:19]) How can we avoid such a disastrous outcome? Refuse to circulate negative or unsubstantiated reports. Do not be naive, or gullible. Be sure you have the facts. w18.08 4 ¶8

^ (Prov. 18:13) When anyone replies to a matter before he hears the facts, It is foolish and humiliating.

^ (1 Tim. 1:19) holding faith and a good conscience, which some have thrust aside, resulting in the shipwreck of their faith.

Wednesday, July 22

Truly I tell you today, you will be with me in Paradise.—[Luke 23:43].

In the earliest available Greek manuscripts, punctuation was not consistently used. Thus, the question arises: Was Jesus saying, “I tell you, today you will be with me in Paradise”? Or was he saying, “I tell you today, you will be with me in Paradise”? Recall that Jesus had earlier told his followers: “The Son of man will be in the heart of the earth for three days and three nights.” ([Matt. 12:40;][16:21;][17:22, 23;][Mark 10:34;] Acts 10:39, 40) So Jesus did not go to any Paradise on the day he and that criminal died. Jesus was “in the Grave [or “Hades”]” for days, until God resurrected him. (Acts 2:31, 32; ftn.) That dying criminal did not know that Jesus had made a covenant with his faithful apostles to be with him in the heavenly Kingdom. ([Luke 22:29]) Furthermore, that criminal had not even been baptized. ([John 3:3-6,][12]) Thus, what Jesus promised must be an earthly paradise that was to be fulfilled later. w18.12 6 ¶17-18, 20-21

^ (Luke 23:43) And he said to him: “Truly I tell you today, you will be with me in Paradise.”

^ (Matt. 12:40) For just as Joʹnah was in the belly of the huge fish for three days and three nights, so the Son of man will be in the heart of the earth for three days and three nights.

^ (Matt. 16:21) From that time forward, Jesus began explaining to his disciples that he must go to Jerusalem and suffer many things from the elders and chief priests and scribes and be killed, and on the third day be raised up.

^ (Matt. 17:22, 23) It was while they were gathered together in Galʹi·lee that Jesus said to them: “The Son of man is going to be betrayed into men’s hands, 23 and they will kill him, and on the third day he will be raised up.” And they were very much grieved.

^ (Mark 10:34) and these will mock him and spit on him and scourge him and kill him, but three days later he will rise.”

^ (Acts 10:39, 40) And we are witnesses of all the things he did both in the country of the Jews and in Jerusalem; but they did away with him by hanging him on a stake. 40 God raised this one up on the third day and allowed him to become manifest,*

Or “to become visible; to be seen.”

^ (Acts 2:31, 32) he foresaw and spoke about the resurrection of the Christ, that neither was he forsaken in the Grave nor did his flesh see corruption. 32 God resurrected this Jesus, and of this we are all witnesses.

^ (Luke 22:29) and I make a covenant with you, just as my Father has made a covenant with me, for a kingdom,

^ (John 3:3-6) In response Jesus said to him: “Most truly I say to you, unless anyone is born again, he cannot see the Kingdom of God.” 4 Nic·o·deʹmus said to him: “How can a man be born when he is old? He cannot enter into the womb of his mother a second time and be born, can he?” 5 Jesus answered: “Most truly I say to you, unless anyone is born from water and spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God. 6 What has been born from the flesh is flesh, and what has been born from the spirit is spirit.

^ (John 3:12) If I have told you earthly things and you still do not believe, how will you believe if I tell you heavenly things?

Thursday, July 23

Make for us a god who will go ahead of us, because we do not know what has happened to this Moses.—[Ex. 32:1].

Soon the Israelites were worshipping a golden calf! Despite this obvious act of disobedience, the Israelites somehow fooled themselves into thinking that they were still on Jehovah’s side. Why, Aaron even called their calf worship “a festival to Jehovah”! How did Jehovah react? He felt betrayed. Jehovah told Moses that the people had “corrupted themselves” and had “deviated from the way [He] commanded them to go.” In his “burning anger,” Jehovah even considered wiping out the newly formed nation of Israel. ([Ex. 32:5-10]) However, Jehovah decided not to eliminate the Israelites. ([Ex. 32:14]) Although initially involved in setting up the idol, Aaron repented and joined the rest of the Levites who declared themselves to be on Jehovah’s side. While thousands lost their lives because of their idolatry, those who were on Jehovah’s side were promised a blessing.—[Ex. 32:26-29]. w18.07 20 ¶13-16

^ (Ex. 32:1) Meanwhile, the people saw that Moses was taking a long time coming down from the mountain. So the people gathered around Aaron and said to him: “Get up, make for us a god who will go ahead of us, because we do not know what has happened to this Moses, the man who led us up out of the land of Egypt.”

^ (Ex. 32:5-10) When Aaron saw this, he built an altar before it. Then Aaron called out: “There is a festival to Jehovah tomorrow.” 6 So they got up early on the next day and began offering up burnt offerings and presenting communion sacrifices. After that the people sat down to eat and drink. Then they got up to have a good time. 7 Jehovah now said to Moses: “Go, descend, because your people, whom you led up out of the land of Egypt, have corrupted themselves. 8 They have quickly deviated from the way I commanded them to go. They have made for themselves a statue* of a calf, and they keep bowing down to it and sacrificing to it and saying, ‘This is your God, O Israel, who led you up out of the land of Egypt.’” 9 Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “I have seen that this is an obstinate* people. 10 So now let me be, and I will exterminate them in my burning anger, and let me make a great nation from you instead.”

Or “molten statue.”

Lit., “stiff-necked.”

^ (Ex. 32:14) So Jehovah began to reconsider* the calamity that he had spoken of bringing on his people.

Or “felt regret over.”

^ (Ex. 32:26-29) Then Moses took his position in the gate of the camp and said: “Who is on Jehovah’s side? Come to me!” And all the Levites gathered around him. 27 He now said to them: “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘Each of you must fasten on his sword and pass through all the camp from gate to gate, killing his brother, his neighbor, and his close companion.’” 28 The Levites did what Moses said. So about 3,000 men were killed on that day. 29 Then Moses said: “Set yourselves apart* for Jehovah today, for each of you has gone against his own son and his own brother; today he will give you a blessing.”

Lit., “Fill your hand.”

Friday, July 24

Beware of the scribes . . . who love greetings in the marketplaces . . . and the most prominent places at evening meals.—[Luke 20:46].

What is the greatest form of recognition that we can strive for? It is not the kind of attention that people seek in the academic, business, and entertainment fields of this world. Rather, it is the kind that Paul described for us in these words: “Now that you have come to know God or, rather, have come to be known by God, how is it that you are turning back again to the weak and beggarly elementary things and want to slave for them over again?” ([Gal. 4:9]) What a wonderful privilege it is to “come to be known by God,” the Supreme Ruler of the universe! He is willing to have an intimate relationship with us. As one scholar stated, we “become objects of his favourable attention.” When Jehovah acknowledges us as his friends, we achieve the very reason for our existence.—Eccl. 12:13, 14. w18.07 8 ¶3-4

^ (Luke 20:46) “Beware of the scribes who like to walk around in robes and who love greetings in the marketplaces and front seats in the synagogues and the most prominent places at evening meals,

^ (Gal. 4:9) But now that you have come to know God or, rather, have come to be known by God, how is it that you are turning back again to the weak and beggarly elementary things and want to slave for them over again?

^ (Eccl. 12:13, 14) The conclusion of the matter, everything having been heard, is: Fear the true God and keep his commandments, for this is the whole obligation of man. 14 For the true God will judge every deed, including every hidden thing, as to whether it is good or bad.

Saturday, July 25

I ponder over your reminders.—[Ps. 119:99].

In order to benefit from God’s laws, we must grow to love and respect them. ([Amos 5:15]) But how do we actually do that? A key is to learn to view things the way Jehovah views them. To illustrate: Imagine that you are having difficulty sleeping well. Your doctor prescribes a program involving diet, exercise, and lifestyle changes. After trying the program, you find that it works! You probably would greatly appreciate your doctor for helping you to improve the quality of your life. In like manner, our Creator has given us laws that can protect us from the damaging effects of sin and thus improve our life. Think about how we benefit from following the Bible’s laws about lying, scheming, stealing, sexual immorality, violence, and spiritism. (Prov. 6:16-19;[Rev. 21:8]) When we experience the rich rewards that come from doing things Jehovah’s way, our heart naturally grows in love and appreciation for both Jehovah and his laws. w18.06 17 ¶5-6

^ (Ps. 119:99) I have more insight than all my teachers, Because I ponder over* your reminders.

Or “study.”

^ (Amos 5:15) Hate what is bad, and love what is good, Let justice prevail in the city gate. It may be that Jehovah the God of armies Will show favor to the remaining ones of Joseph.’

^ (Prov. 6:16-19) There are six things that Jehovah hates; Yes, seven things that he* detests: 17 Haughty eyes, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood, 18 A heart plotting wicked schemes, and feet that run quickly to evil, 19 A false witness who lies with every breath, And anyone sowing contentions among brothers.

Or “his soul.”

^ (Rev. 21:8) But as for the cowards and those without faith and those who are disgusting in their filth and murderers and the sexually immoral* and those practicing spiritism and idolaters and all the liars, their portion will be in the lake that burns with fire and sulfur. This means the second death.”

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

Sunday, July 26

Are you the King of the Jews?—[John 18:33].

Perhaps the governor feared that Jesus could cause political unrest, a principal concern throughout Pilate’s rule. Jesus answered: “My Kingdom is no part of this world.” ([John 18:36]) He would not get involved in politics, for his Kingdom was to be a heavenly one. He told Pilate that his work on earth was to “bear witness to the truth.” ([John 18:37]) When we understand our assignment as clearly as Jesus understood his, we will avoid even lending tacit, or unspoken, support for political independence movements. This may not be easy. “People in our area are becoming more and more radical,” notes one traveling overseer. “A nationalistic spirit has taken over, and many take for granted that political independence will improve their lives. Thankfully, the brothers have safeguarded their Christian unity by concentrating on preaching the good news of the Kingdom. They look to God to solve injustice and the other problems we face.” w18.06 4-5 ¶6-7

^ (John 18:33) So Pilate entered the governor’s residence again and called Jesus and said to him: “Are you the King of the Jews?”

^ (John 18:36) Jesus answered: “My Kingdom is no part of this world. If my Kingdom were part of this world, my attendants would have fought that I should not be handed over to the Jews. But as it is, my Kingdom is not from this source.”

^ (John 18:37) So Pilate said to him: “Well, then, are you a king?” Jesus answered: “You yourself are saying that I am a king. For this I have been born, and for this I have come into the world, that I should bear witness to the truth. Everyone who is on the side of the truth listens to my voice.”

Monday, July 27

Oppose the Devil, and he will flee from you.—[Jas. 4:7].

Only three books of the Hebrew Scriptures, 1 Chronicles, Job, and Zechariah, mention Satan, which means “Resister.” Why was little said about our enemy prior to the arrival of the Messiah? Apparently, Jehovah did not want to give Satan undue prominence by devoting large portions of the Hebrew Scriptures to discussing him and his activity. Jehovah’s primary purpose for inspiring that section of the Scriptures was to identify the Messiah and lead God’s people to him. ([Luke 24:44;][Gal. 3:24]) When that was accomplished and the Messiah arrived, Jehovah used him and his disciples to reveal much of what we know about Satan and the angels who joined him. That is fitting, since it is Jesus and his anointed corulers whom Jehovah will use to crush Satan and his followers. ([Rom. 16:20;][Rev. 17:14;][20:10]) Remember, the Devil’s power is limited. We are backed by Jehovah, Jesus, and the faithful angels. With their help, we can resist our enemy. w18.05 22-23 ¶2-4

^ (Jas. 4:7) Therefore, subject yourselves to God; but oppose the Devil, and he will flee from you.

^ (Luke 24:44) He then said to them: “These are my words that I spoke to you while I was yet with you, that all the things written about me in the Law of Moses and in the Prophets and Psalms must be fulfilled.”

^ (Gal. 3:24) So the Law became our guardian* leading to Christ, so that we might be declared righteous through faith.

Or “tutor.”

^ (Rom. 16:20) For his part, the God who gives peace will crush Satan under your feet shortly. May the undeserved kindness of our Lord Jesus be with you.

^ (Rev. 17:14) These will battle with the Lamb, but because he is Lord of lords and King of kings, the Lamb will conquer them. Also, those with him who are called and chosen and faithful will do so.”

^ (Rev. 20:10) And the Devil who was misleading them was hurled into the lake of fire and sulfur, where both the wild beast and the false prophet already were; and they will be tormented* day and night forever and ever.

Or “restrained; imprisoned.”

Tuesday, July 28

He takes away every branch in me not bearing fruit.—[John 15:2].

Jehovah views us as his servants only if we bear fruit. ([Matt. 13:23;][21:43]) Hence, in the illustration found at [John 15:1-5], the fruitage that each Christian must bear cannot refer to new disciples whom we may be privileged to make. ([Matt. 28:19]) Otherwise, faithful Witnesses who do not succeed in making disciples because of preaching in an unresponsive territory would be like the barren branches in Jesus’ illustration. However, such a conclusion is unthinkable! Why? Because we cannot force people to become disciples. It would go against Jehovah’s loving ways to disqualify his servants for failing to do something that is beyond their reach. Whatever Jehovah asks of us is always reachable. (Deut. 30:11-14) What, then, is the fruit we must bear? Clearly, the fruit must refer to an activity that each of us is able to carry out. What activity? The preaching of the good news of God’s Kingdom.—[Matt. 24:14]. w18.05 14 ¶8-9

^ (John 15:2) He takes away every branch in me not bearing fruit, and he cleans every one bearing fruit, so that it may bear more fruit.

^ (Matt. 13:23) As for the one sown upon the fine soil, this is the one hearing the word and getting the sense of it, who really does bear fruit and produces, this one 100 times more, that one 60, the other 30.”

^ (Matt. 21:43) This is why I say to you, the Kingdom of God will be taken from you and be given to a nation producing its fruits.

^ (John 15:1-5) “I am the true vine, and my Father is the cultivator. 2 He takes away every branch in me not bearing fruit, and he cleans every one bearing fruit, so that it may bear more fruit. 3 You are already clean because of the word that I have spoken to you. 4 Remain in union with me, and I will remain in union with you. Just as the branch cannot bear fruit by itself unless it remains in the vine, neither can you unless you remain in union with me. 5 I am the vine; you are the branches. Whoever remains in union with me and I in union with him, this one bears much fruit; for apart from me you can do* nothing at all.

Or “produce.”

^ (Matt. 28:19) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit,

^ (Deut. 30:11-14) “Now this commandment that I am commanding you today is not too difficult for you, nor is it beyond your reach.* 12 It is not in the heavens, so that you have to say, ‘Who will ascend to the heavens and get it for us, so that we may hear it and observe it?’ 13 Nor is it on the other side of the sea, so that you have to say, ‘Who will cross over to the other side of the sea and get it for us, so that we may hear it and observe it?’ 14 For the word is very near you, in your own mouth and in your own heart, so that you may do it.

Lit., “nor is it far away.”

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

Wednesday, July 29

You are from your father the Devil, . . . a liar and the father of the lie.—[John 8:44].

Whether called pastors, priests, rabbis, swamis, or by some other title, religious leaders abound in the world today. Like their first-century counterparts, they are “suppressing the truth” from God’s Word and have “exchanged the truth of God for the lie.” ([Rom. 1:18,][25]) They promote such false teachings as “once saved, always saved,” the immortality of the human soul, reincarnation, and the foolish idea that God would condone homosexual lifestyles and same-sex marriages. Politicians have used lies to mislead mankind. One of the biggest lies is yet to be heard when men proclaim that they have achieved “peace and security!” But “then sudden destruction is to be instantly on them.” May we not be taken in by their attempt to minimize how precarious this system of things really is! In truth, we “know very well that Jehovah’s day is coming exactly as a thief in the night.”—1 Thess. 5:1-4. w18.10 7-8 ¶6-8

^ (John 8:44) You are from your father the Devil, and you wish to do the desires of your father. That one was a murderer when he began, and he did not stand fast in the truth, because truth is not in him. When he speaks the lie, he speaks according to his own disposition, because he is a liar and the father of the lie.

^ (Rom. 1:18) For God’s wrath is being revealed from heaven against all ungodliness and unrighteousness of men who are suppressing the truth in an unrighteous way,

^ (Rom. 1:25) They exchanged the truth of God for the lie and venerated* and rendered sacred service to the creation rather than the Creator, who is praised forever. Amen.

Or “worshipped.”

^ (1 Thess. 5:1-4) Now as for the times and the seasons, brothers, you need nothing to be written to you. 2 For you yourselves know very well that Jehovah’s* day is coming exactly as a thief in the night. 3 Whenever it is that they are saying, “Peace and security!” then sudden destruction is to be instantly on them, just like birth pains on a pregnant woman, and they will by no means escape. 4 But you, brothers, you are not in darkness, so that the day should overtake you as it would thieves,

See App. A5.

Thursday, July 30

You must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: “There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.”—[Acts 20:35].

Jesus Christ, through his anointed brothers and supportive “princes” of the other sheep, provides encouragement and guidance to despondent and discouraged ones in this time of need. That is as it should be, for these elders are not “masters” over the faith of others but “are fellow workers” for the joy of their brothers. (Isa. 32:1, 2;[2 Cor. 1:24]) The apostle Paul set an example to be imitated. He wrote to the persecuted Christians in Thessalonica: “Having tender affection for you, we were determined to impart to you, not only the good news of God but also our very selves, because you became so beloved to us.” ([1 Thess. 2:8]) Showing that just a word of encouragement does not always suffice, Paul told the elders from Ephesus the words of today’s text. w18.04 21-22 ¶6-8

^ (Acts 20:35) I have shown you in all things that by working hard in this way, you must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

^ (Isa. 32:1, 2) Look! A king will reign for righteousness, And princes will rule for justice.  2 And each one will be like a hiding place* from the wind, A place of concealment* from the rainstorm, Like streams of water in a waterless land, Like the shadow of a massive crag in a parched land.

Or “a shelter.”

Or “A refuge.”

^ (2 Cor. 1:24) Not that we are the masters over your faith, but we are fellow workers for your joy, for it is by your faith that you are standing.

^ (1 Thess. 2:8) So having tender affection for you, we were determined* to impart to you, not only the good news of God but also our very selves,* because you became so beloved to us.

Lit., “well-pleased.”

Or “souls.”

Friday, July 31

Jehovah is the Spirit, and where the spirit of Jehovah is, there is freedom.—[2 Cor. 3:17].

To enjoy and benefit from that freedom, we must ‘turn to Jehovah,’ that is, come into a personal relationship with him. ([2 Cor. 3:16]) The Israelites in the wilderness did not view Jehovah’s dealings with them in a spiritual way. It was as if their hearts and minds were veiled and hardened, focused only on using their newfound freedom from Egypt in a physical, or fleshly, way. ([Heb. 3:8-10]) The freedom that is associated with the spirit of Jehovah, however, is more than liberation from physical slavery. Far beyond what human efforts can hope to achieve, the spirit of Jehovah brings liberation from enslavement to sin and death, as well as from slavery to false worship and its practices. ([Rom. 6:23;][8:2]) What a glorious freedom that is! A person can enjoy the benefits of such freedom even when imprisoned or enslaved.—Gen. 39:20-23. w18.04 9 ¶3-5

^ (2 Cor. 3:17) Now Jehovah* is the Spirit, and where the spirit of Jehovah* is, there is freedom.

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ (2 Cor. 3:16) But when one turns to Jehovah,* the veil is taken away.

See App. A5.

^ (Heb. 3:8-10) do not harden your hearts as on the occasion of provoking to bitter anger, as in the day of testing in the wilderness, 9 where your forefathers put me to the test and tried me, despite seeing my works for 40 years. 10 This is why I became disgusted with this generation and said: ‘They always go astray in their hearts, and they have not come to know my ways.’

^ (Rom. 6:23) For the wages sin pays is death, but the gift God gives is everlasting life by Christ Jesus our Lord.

^ (Rom. 8:2) For the law of the spirit that gives life in union with Christ Jesus has set you free from the law of sin and of death.

^ (Gen. 39:20-23) So Joseph’s master took him and gave him over to the prison, the place where the prisoners of the king were kept under arrest, and he remained there in the prison. 21 But Jehovah continued with Joseph and kept showing loyal love to him and granting him favor in the eyes of the chief officer of the prison. 22 So the chief officer of the prison put Joseph in charge of all the prisoners in the prison, and everything that they were doing there, he was the one having it done. 23 The chief officer of the prison was looking after absolutely nothing that was in Joseph’s care, for Jehovah was with Joseph and Jehovah made whatever he did successful.

August

Saturday, August 1

God recommends his own love to us in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.—[Rom. 5:8].

At meetings we are regularly reminded of what Jehovah and Jesus have done for us. Filled with gratitude, we try to imitate Jesus by how we live each day. (2 Cor. 5:14, 15) In addition, our heart stirs us to praise Jehovah for providing the ransom. One way we can praise him is by making heartfelt comments at our meetings. We can show the depth of our love for Jehovah and his Son by being willing to make sacrifices for them. Often, we must make sacrifices of various kinds to attend our meetings. Many congregations hold one meeting at the end of a workday when we are most likely tired. And another meeting is held on the weekend when other people are resting. Does Jehovah notice that we attend our meetings even though we are tired? Certainly he does! In fact, the greater our struggle, the more Jehovah appreciates the love we show for him.—Mark 12:41-44. w19.01 29 ¶12-13

^ (Rom. 5:8) But God recommends his own love to us* in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.

Or “demonstrates (shows) his own love for us.”

^ (2 Cor. 5:14, 15) For the love the Christ has compels us, because this is what we have concluded, that one man died for all; so, then, all had died. 15 And he died for all so that those who live should live no longer for themselves, but for him who died for them and was raised up.

^ (Mark 12:41-44) And he sat down with the treasury chests in view and began observing how the crowd was dropping money into the treasury chests, and many rich people were dropping in many coins. 42 Now a poor widow came and dropped in two small coins of very little value. 43 So he called his disciples to him and said to them: “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than all the others who put money into the treasury chests. 44 For they all put in out of their surplus, but she, out of her want,* put in everything she had, all she had to live on.”

Or “poverty.”

Sunday, August 2

When the Lord caught sight of her, he was moved with pity.—[Luke 7:13].

Jesus himself experienced some of the challenges people faced. For example, Jesus apparently grew up in a poor family. From working with his adoptive father, Joseph, Jesus learned how to do hard physical work. ([Matt. 13:55;][Mark 6:3]) It seems that Joseph died sometime before the end of Jesus’ ministry. So Jesus likely felt the pain of losing a loved one in death. And Jesus knew what it was like to be in a family with differing religious views. ([John 7:5]) Those circumstances and others would have helped Jesus to understand the challenges and feelings of ordinary people. Jesus’ concern was especially evident when he performed miracles. Jesus did not perform miracles out of a mere sense of duty. He was “moved with pity” for those who were suffering. (Matt. 20:29-34; Mark 1:40-42) Jesus sympathized with people and wanted to help them.—Mark 7:32-35; Luke 7:12-15. w19.03 16 ¶10-11

^ (Luke 7:13) When the Lord caught sight of her, he was moved with pity for her, and he said to her: “Stop weeping.”

^ (Matt. 13:55) Is this not the carpenter’s son? Is not his mother called Mary, and his brothers James and Joseph and Simon and Judas?

^ (Mark 6:3) This is the carpenter, the son of Mary and the brother of James, Joseph, Judas, and Simon, is it not? And his sisters are here with us, are they not?” So they began to stumble because of him.

^ (John 7:5) His brothers were, in fact, not exercising faith in him.

^ (Matt. 20:29-34) As they were going out of Jerʹi·cho, a large crowd followed him. 30 And look! two blind men sitting beside the road heard that Jesus was passing by and cried out: “Lord, have mercy on us, Son of David!” 31 But the crowd rebuked them, telling them to keep silent; yet they cried all the louder, saying: “Lord, have mercy on us, Son of David!” 32 So Jesus stopped, called them, and said: “What do you want me to do for you?” 33 They said to him: “Lord, let our eyes be opened.” 34 Moved with pity, Jesus touched their eyes, and immediately they recovered their sight, and they followed him.

^ (Mark 1:40-42) There also came to him a leper, pleading with him even on bended knee, saying to him: “If you just want to, you can make me clean.” 41 At that he was moved with pity, and he stretched out his hand and touched him, and said to him: “I want to! Be made clean.” 42 Immediately the leprosy vanished from him, and he became clean.

^ (Mark 7:32-35) Here they brought him a deaf man with a speech impediment, and they pleaded with him to lay his hand on him. 33 And he took him aside privately, away from the crowd. Then he put his fingers into the man’s ears, and after spitting, he touched his tongue. 34 And looking up into heaven, he sighed deeply and said to him: “Ephʹpha·tha,” that is, “Be opened.” 35 At this his ears were opened, and his speech impediment was removed, and he began speaking normally.

^ (Luke 7:12-15) As he got near the gate of the city, why look! there was a dead man being carried out, the only son of his mother. Besides, she was a widow. A considerable crowd from the city was also with her. 13 When the Lord caught sight of her, he was moved with pity for her, and he said to her: “Stop weeping.” 14 With that he approached and touched the bier,* and the bearers stood still. Then he said: “Young man, I say to you, get up!”* 15 And the dead man sat up and started to speak, and Jesus gave him to his mother.

Or “funeral stretcher.”

Or “wake up!”

Monday, August 3

Continue putting up with one another.—[Col. 3:13].

It was the final night of Jesus’ earthly life. Imagine the stress Jesus felt. Would he remain perfectly faithful until death? The lives of billions of people hung in the balance. (Rom. 5:18, 19) Even more important, his Father’s reputation was involved. ([Job 2:4]) Then, during his last meal with his closest friends, the apostles, their conversation degenerated into “a heated dispute” over “which one of them was considered to be the greatest.” Remarkably, Jesus did not become irritated. Instead, he responded with mildness. Kindly, but firmly, Jesus explained—again—the attitude they should have. And he then commended his friends for loyally sticking with him. (Luke 22:24-28; John 13:1-5,[12-15]) We can imitate Jesus and remain mild-tempered even when we are under stress if we remember that we all say and do things that irritate others. ([Prov. 12:18;][Jas. 3:2,][5]) And try to mention the good that you see in others.—[Eph. 4:29]. w19.02 11-12 ¶16-17

^ (Col. 3:13) Continue putting up with one another and forgiving one another freely even if anyone has a cause for complaint against another. Just as Jehovah* freely forgave you, you must also do the same.

See App. A5.

^ (Rom. 5:18, 19) So, then, as through one trespass the result to men of all sorts was condemnation, so too through one act of justification the result to men of all sorts is their being declared righteous for life. 19 For just as through the disobedience of the one man many were made sinners, so also through the obedience of the one person many will be made righteous.

^ (Job 2:4) But Satan answered Jehovah: “Skin for skin. A man will give everything that he has for his life.*

Or “soul.”

^ (Luke 22:24-28) However, there also arose a heated dispute among them over which one of them was considered to be the greatest. 25 But he said to them: “The kings of the nations lord it over them, and those having authority over them are called Benefactors. 26 You, though, are not to be that way. But let the one who is the greatest among you become as the youngest, and the one taking the lead as the one ministering. 27 For which one is greater, the one dining* or the one serving? Is it not the one dining?* But I am among you as the one serving. 28 “However, you are the ones who have stuck with me in my trials;

Or “reclining at the table.”

Or “reclining at the table.”

^ (John 13:1-5) Now because he knew before the festival of the Passover that his hour had come for him to leave this world and go to the Father, Jesus, having loved his own who were in the world, loved them to the end. 2 The evening meal was going on,* and the Devil had already put it into the heart of Judas Is·carʹi·ot, the son of Simon, to betray him. 3 So Jesus, knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands and that he came from God and was going to God, 4 got up from the evening meal and laid aside his outer garments. And taking a towel, he wrapped it around his waist. 5 After that he put water into a basin and started to wash the feet of the disciples and to dry them off with the towel that was wrapped around him.

Or possibly, “was being prepared.”

^ (John 13:12-15) When, now, he had washed their feet and had put his outer garments on, he again reclined at the table and said to them: “Do you understand what I have done to you? 13 You address me as ‘Teacher’ and ‘Lord,’ and you are correct, for I am such. 14 Therefore, if I, the Lord and Teacher, washed your feet, you also should wash the feet of one another. 15 For I set the pattern for you, that just as I did to you, you should also do.

^ (Prov. 12:18) Thoughtless speech is like the stabs of a sword, But the tongue of the wise is a healing.

^ (Jas. 3:2) For we all stumble* many times. If anyone does not stumble in word, he is a perfect man, able to bridle also his whole body.

Or “make mistakes.”

^ (Jas. 3:5) So, too, the tongue is a small part of the body, and yet it makes great brags. See how small a fire it takes to set a great forest ablaze!

^ (Eph. 4:29) Let a rotten word not come out of your mouth, but only what is good for building up as the need may be, to impart what is beneficial to the hearers.

Tuesday, August 4

Jehovah . . . has firmly established his throne for justice.—[Ps. 9:7].

The Mosaic Law limited the possibility that a person would be falsely accused of a crime. A defendant had the right to know who was accusing him. (Deut. 19:16-19;[25:1]) And before he could be convicted, at least two witnesses had to give evidence. ([Deut. 17:6;][19:15]) What about an Israelite who committed a crime that was seen by only one witness? He could not assume that he would get away with his wrongdoing. Jehovah saw what he did. Yes, Jehovah sets the perfect example; nothing he does is unfair. He rewards those who loyally uphold his standards, but he punishes those who abuse their power. (2 Sam. 22:21-23; Ezek. 9:9, 10) Some may act wickedly and seem to escape punishment, but when Jehovah determines that the time is right, he brings them to justice. ([Prov. 28:13]) And if they do not repent, they soon learn that “it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.”—Heb. 10:30, 31. w19.02 23-24 ¶20-21

^ (Ps. 9:7) But Jehovah is enthroned forever; He has firmly established his throne for justice.

^ (Deut. 19:16-19) If a malicious witness testifies against a man and charges him with some transgression, 17 the two men who have the dispute will stand before Jehovah, before the priests and the judges who will be serving in those days. 18 The judges will thoroughly investigate, and if the man who testified is a false witness and has brought a false charge against his brother, 19 you should do to him just as he had schemed to do to his brother, and you must remove what is bad from your midst.

^ (Deut. 25:1) “When a dispute arises between men, they may present themselves before the judges, and they will judge them and pronounce the righteous one innocent and the wicked one guilty.

^ (Deut. 17:6) On the testimony* of two witnesses or of three witnesses the one who is to die should be put to death. He must not be put to death on the testimony of one witness.

Lit., “mouth.”

^ (Deut. 19:15) “No single witness may convict* another for any error or any sin that he may commit. On the testimony* of two witnesses or on the testimony of three witnesses the matter should be established.

Lit., “rise up against.”

Lit., “mouth.”

^ (2 Sam. 22:21-23) Jehovah rewards me according to my righteousness; He repays me according to the innocence* of my hands. 22 For I have kept the ways of Jehovah, And I have not wickedly abandoned my God. 23 All his judgments are before me; I will not deviate from his statutes.

Lit., “the cleanness.”

^ (Ezek. 9:9, 10) So he said to me: “The error of the house of Israel and Judah is very, very great. The land is filled with bloodshed, and the city is full of corruption. For they say, ‘Jehovah has left the land, and Jehovah is not seeing.’ 10 But as for me, my eye will not feel sorry; nor will I show compassion. The consequences of their way I will bring down on their own head.”

^ (Prov. 28:13) The one covering over his transgressions will not succeed, But whoever confesses and abandons them will be shown mercy.

^ (Heb. 10:30, 31) For we know the One who said: “Vengeance is mine; I will repay.” And again: “Jehovah* will judge his people.” 31 It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.

See App. A5.

Wednesday, August 5

There has never again arisen a prophet in Israel like Moses, whom Jehovah knew face-to-face.—[Deut. 34:10].

Moses certainly looked to Jehovah for direction and guidance. Indeed, “he continued steadfast as seeing the One who is invisible.” (Heb. 11:24-27) Less than two months after the Israelites left Egypt, a serious problem arose—even before they arrived at Mount Sinai. The people started to complain about a lack of water. They began to murmur against Moses, and the situation became so serious that Moses cried out to Jehovah: “What should I do with this people? A little longer and they will stone me!” ([Ex. 17:4]) Jehovah responded by giving Moses clear instructions. He was to take his rod and strike the rock in Horeb, and then water would come gushing out. We read: “Moses did so before the eyes of the elders of Israel.” The Israelites drank their fill, and the problem was solved.—[Ex. 17:5, 6]. w18.07 13 ¶4-5

^ (Deut. 34:10) But there has never again arisen a prophet in Israel like Moses, whom Jehovah knew face-to-face.

^ (Heb. 11:24-27) By faith Moses, when grown up, refused to be called the son of Pharʹaoh’s daughter, 25 choosing to be mistreated with the people of God rather than to have the temporary enjoyment of sin, 26 because he considered the reproach of the Christ to be riches greater than the treasures of Egypt, for he looked intently toward the payment of the reward. 27 By faith he left Egypt, but not fearing the anger of the king, for he continued steadfast as seeing the One who is invisible.

^ (Ex. 17:4) Finally Moses cried out to Jehovah: “What should I do with this people? A little longer and they will stone me!”

^ (Ex. 17:5, 6) Then Jehovah said to Moses: “Go ahead of the people, and take with you some of the elders of Israel and your rod with which you struck the Nile River. Take it in your hand and walk on. 6 Look! I will be standing before you there on the rock in Horʹeb. You must strike the rock, and water will come out of it, and the people will drink it.” Moses did so before the eyes of the elders of Israel.

Thursday, August 6

Love builds up.—[1 Cor. 8:1].

One means by which Jehovah builds us up in love is the Christian congregation. Individually, we can reciprocate his love by loving and building up our spiritual brothers and sisters not only spiritually but also emotionally. (1 John 4:19-21) The apostle Paul urged Christians: “Keep encouraging one another and building one another up, just as you are in fact doing.” (1 Thess. 5:11) Yes, all in the congregation—not just elders—can imitate Jehovah and Jesus in comforting and building up the brothers and sisters. ([Rom. 15:1, 2]) Some in the congregation who have emotional disorders may need professional help and medication. ([Luke 5:31]) Elders and others in the congregation modestly recognize that they are not trained mental-health-care professionals. However, they and others in the congregation have a vital role to play—to “speak consolingly to those who are depressed, support the weak, be patient toward all.”—1 Thess. 5:14. w18.09 14 ¶10-11

^ (1 Cor. 8:1) Now concerning food offered to idols: We know we all have knowledge. Knowledge puffs up, but love builds up.

^ (1 John 4:19-21) We love, because he first loved us. 20 If anyone says, “I love God,” and yet is hating his brother, he is a liar. For the one who does not love his brother, whom he has seen, cannot love God, whom he has not seen. 21 And we have this commandment from him, that whoever loves God must also love his brother.

^ (1 Thess. 5:11) Therefore, keep encouraging* one another and building one another up, just as you are in fact doing.

Or “comforting.”

^ (Rom. 15:1, 2) We, though, who are strong ought to bear the weaknesses of those not strong, and not to be pleasing ourselves. 2 Let each of us please his neighbor for his good, to build him up.

^ (Luke 5:31) In reply Jesus said to them: “Those who are healthy do not need a physician, but those who are ill do.

^ (1 Thess. 5:14) On the other hand, we urge you, brothers, to warn* the disorderly, speak consolingly to those who are depressed,* support the weak, be patient toward all.

Or “admonish.”

Or “those who are discouraged.” Lit., “those of little soul.”

Friday, August 7

Do not be anxious, for I am your God.—[Isa. 41:10].

We deepen our trust in Jehovah by getting to know him better. And the only way we can really know God well is by reading the Bible carefully and then meditating on what we read. The Bible contains a reliable record of how Jehovah protected his people in the past. That record gives us confidence that he will care for us now. Consider an example of the beautiful word picture Isaiah uses to illustrate how Jehovah protects us. He refers to Jehovah as a shepherd and to God’s servants as lambs. Isaiah says of Jehovah: “With his arm he will gather together the lambs, and in his bosom he will carry them.” ([Isa. 40:11]) When we sense Jehovah’s strong arms wrapped around us, we feel protected and calm. To help you remain calm despite the problems you may face, meditate on the reassuring words mentioned in today’s text. They will strengthen you as you face the challenges that lie ahead. w19.01 7 ¶17-18

^ (Isa. 41:10) Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.’

^ (Isa. 40:11) Like a shepherd he will care for* his flock. With his arm he will gather together the lambs, And in his bosom he will carry them. He will gently lead those nursing their young.

Or “will shepherd.”

Saturday, August 8

To do your will, O my God, is my delight.—[Ps. 40:8].

Do you have one or more spiritual goals that you are working toward? Perhaps you are trying to read portions of the Bible each day. Or you may be trying to improve your speaking and teaching abilities. Whatever the case, when you see positive results—or others see them and commend you—how do you feel? No doubt you feel a sense of achievement and joy. And so you should, in no small part because you are putting God’s will ahead of your own, in imitation of Jesus. ([Prov. 27:11]) By focusing on spiritual pursuits, you are also doing a work that is truly satisfying because it is not in the least futile. The apostle Paul wrote: “Be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain in connection with the Lord.” ([1 Cor. 15:58]) By comparison, a life marked by secular ambitions and pursuits—even if these seem very successful—is ultimately a life of futility.—[Luke 9:25]. w18.12 22 ¶12-13

^ (Ps. 40:8) To do your will, O my God, is my delight,* And your law is deep within me.

Or “desire.”

^ (Prov. 27:11) Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice, So that I can make a reply to him who taunts me.

^ (1 Cor. 15:58) Therefore, my beloved brothers, be steadfast, immovable, always having plenty to do in the work of the Lord, knowing that your labor is not in vain in connection with the Lord.

^ (Luke 9:25) Really, what good will it do a man if he gains the whole world but loses his own self or suffers ruin?

Sunday, August 9

The righteous will possess the earth.—[Ps. 37:29].

David was referring to a time when people on earth would live according to God’s righteous ways. ([2 Pet. 3:13]) The prophecy at [Isaiah 65:22] says: “The days of my people will be like the days of a tree.” This implies that people will live for thousands of years. According to Revelation 21:1-4, God will turn his attention to mankind, and one of the promised blessings is that “death will be no more” for people serving God in his righteous new world. Adam and Eve lost Paradise back in Eden, but it was not lost forever. As God promised, people on earth are yet to be blessed. Under inspiration, David said that the meek and righteous will inherit the earth and live on it forever. ([Ps. 37:11]) The prophecies in the book of Isaiah should whet our appetite for the delightful conditions that will prevail. ([Isa. 11:6-9;][35:5-10;][65:21-23]) When? When Jesus’ promise to the Jewish criminal comes to pass. ([Luke 23:43]) You can be in that Paradise. w18.12 7 ¶22-23

^ (Ps. 37:29) The righteous will possess the earth, And they will live forever on it.

^ (2 Pet. 3:13) But there are new heavens and a new earth that we are awaiting according to his promise, and in these righteousness is to dwell.

^ (Isa. 65:22) They will not build for someone else to inhabit, Nor will they plant for others to eat. For the days of my people will be like the days of a tree, And the work of their hands my chosen ones will enjoy to the full.

^ (Rev. 21:1-4) And I saw a new heaven and a new earth; for the former heaven and the former earth had passed away, and the sea is no more. 2 I also saw the holy city, New Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God and prepared as a bride adorned for her husband. 3 With that I heard a loud voice from the throne say: “Look! The tent of God is with mankind, and he will reside with them, and they will be his people. And God himself will be with them. 4 And he will wipe out every tear from their eyes, and death will be no more, neither will mourning nor outcry nor pain be anymore. The former things have passed away.”

^ (Ps. 37:11) But the meek will possess the earth, And they will find exquisite delight in the abundance of peace.

^ (Isa. 11:6-9) The wolf will reside for a while with the lamb, And with the young goat the leopard will lie down, And the calf and the lion* and the fattened animal will all be together;* And a little boy will lead them.  7 The cow and the bear will feed together, And their young will lie down together. The lion will eat straw like the bull.  8 The nursing child will play over the lair of a cobra, And a weaned child will put his hand over the den of a poisonous snake.  9 They will not cause any harm Or any ruin in all my holy mountain, Because the earth will certainly be filled with the knowledge of Jehovah As the waters cover the sea.

Or “the maned young lion.”

Or possibly, “And the calf and the lion will feed together.”

^ (Isa. 35:5-10) At that time the eyes of the blind will be opened, And the ears of the deaf will be unstopped.  6 At that time the lame will leap like the deer, And the tongue of the speechless will shout for joy. For waters will burst forth in the wilderness, And streams in the desert plain.  7 The heat-parched ground will become a reedy pool, And the thirsty ground springs of water. In the lairs where jackals rested, There will be green grass and reeds and papyrus.  8 And a highway will be there, Yes, a way called the Way of Holiness. The unclean one will not travel on it. It is reserved for the one walking on the way; No one foolish will stray onto it.  9 No lion will be there, And no vicious wild beasts will come on it. They will not be found there; Only the repurchased ones will walk there. 10 Those redeemed by Jehovah will return and come to Zion with a joyful cry. Unending joy will crown their heads. Exultation and rejoicing will be theirs, And grief and sighing will flee away.

^ (Isa. 65:21-23) They will build houses and live in them, And they will plant vineyards and eat their fruitage. 22 They will not build for someone else to inhabit, Nor will they plant for others to eat. For the days of my people will be like the days of a tree, And the work of their hands my chosen ones will enjoy to the full. 23 They will not toil* for nothing,* Nor will they bear children for distress, Because they are the offspring* made up of those blessed by Jehovah, And their descendants with them.

Or “work hard.”

Or “in vain.”

Lit., “seed.”

^ (Luke 23:43) And he said to him: “Truly I tell you today, you will be with me in Paradise.”

Monday, August 10

Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart.—[Prov. 4:23].

Can we avoid all contact with the world’s thinking? No, we cannot literally get out of the world. Some exposure to its ideas is inescapable. (1 Cor. 5:9, 10) The preaching work itself will bring us in contact with erroneous beliefs. However, where contact with ungodly views is unavoidable, we certainly need not entertain them or accept them. Like Jesus, we should be quick to reject thoughts that serve Satan’s purpose. Furthermore, we can protect ourselves from unnecessary exposure to the world’s thinking. For example, we should exercise caution when choosing our close friends. The Bible warns that if we keep close company with people who do not worship Jehovah, their thinking will rub off on us. ([Prov. 13:20;] 1 Cor. 15:12,[32, 33]) Also, by rejecting entertainment that promotes the theory of evolution, violence, or immorality, we avoid poisoning our thinking with ideas that are “against the knowledge of God.”—[2 Cor. 10:5]. w18.11 21 ¶16-17

^ (Prov. 4:23) Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart, For out of it are the sources of life.

^ (1 Cor. 5:9, 10) In my letter I wrote you to stop keeping company* with sexually immoral people,* 10 not meaning entirely with the sexually immoral people* of this world or the greedy people or extortioners or idolaters. Otherwise, you would actually have to get out of the world.

Or “stop associating.”

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

^ (Prov. 13:20) The one walking with the wise will become wise, But the one who has dealings with the stupid will fare badly.

^ (1 Cor. 15:12) Now if it is being preached that Christ has been raised from the dead, how is it that some among you say there is no resurrection of the dead?

^ (1 Cor. 15:32, 33) If like other men,* I have fought with wild beasts at Ephʹe·sus, of what good is it to me? If the dead are not to be raised up, “let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we are to die.” 33 Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.*

Or possibly, “from a human viewpoint.”

Or “corrupt good morals.”

^ (2 Cor. 10:5) For we are overturning reasonings and every lofty thing raised up against the knowledge of God, and we are bringing every thought into captivity to make it obedient to the Christ;

Tuesday, August 11

I will walk in your truth.—[Ps. 86:11].

How can we strengthen our determination to go on walking in the truth? One way is to have as full a share as possible in teaching Bible truth to others. In this way you will keep a firm grip on our spiritual sword, which is “God’s word.” ([Eph. 6:17]) All of us can strive to improve our skills as teachers, “handling the word of the truth aright.” ([2 Tim. 2:15]) As we use the Bible to help others to buy truth and reject falsehoods, we embed God’s sayings in our own mind and heart. In this way, we strengthen our determination to go on walking in the truth. The truth is a precious gift from Jehovah. By means of this gift, we have our most prized possession, our intimate relationship with our heavenly Father. What he has taught us until now is only the beginning! God has promised us an eternity to add to the truth we have already bought. Therefore, cherish the truth like a fine pearl. Continue to “buy truth and never sell it.”—[Prov. 23:23]. w18.11 8 ¶2; 12 ¶15-17

^ (Ps. 86:11) Instruct me, O Jehovah, about your way. I will walk in your truth. Unify my heart* to fear your name.

Or “Give me an undivided heart.”

^ (Eph. 6:17) Also, accept the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the spirit, that is, God’s word,

^ (2 Tim. 2:15) Do your utmost to present yourself approved to God, a workman with nothing to be ashamed of, handling the word of the truth aright.

^ (Prov. 23:23) Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding.

Or “Acquire.”

Wednesday, August 12

Noah [was] a preacher of righteousness.—[2 Pet. 2:5].

Noah’s preaching work prior to the Flood evidently included a warning of coming destruction. Note what Jesus stated: “For as they were in those days before the Flood, eating and drinking, men marrying and women being given in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark, and they took no note until the Flood came and swept them all away, so the presence of the Son of man will be.” (Matt. 24:38, 39) Despite the people’s indifference, Noah faithfully proclaimed the warning message that he had been given. Today, we preach the Kingdom message to give people an opportunity to learn about God’s will for mankind. Like Jehovah, we dearly wish that people would respond to the message and “keep living.” ([Ezek. 18:23]) At the same time, when we preach from house to house and in public areas, we warn as many people as possible that God’s Kingdom will come and bring an end to this ungodly world.—Ezek. 3:18, 19;[Dan. 2:44;] Rev. 14:6, 7. w18.05 19 ¶8-9

^ (2 Pet. 2:5) And he did not refrain from punishing an ancient world, but kept Noah, a preacher of righteousness, safe with seven others when he brought a flood upon a world of ungodly people.

^ (Matt. 24:38, 39) For as they were in those days before the Flood, eating and drinking, men marrying and women being given in marriage, until the day that Noah entered into the ark, 39 and they took no note until the Flood came and swept them all away, so the presence of the Son of man will be.

^ (Ezek. 18:23) “‘Do I take any pleasure at all in the death of a wicked person?’ declares the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ‘Do I not prefer that he turn away from his ways and keep living?’

^ (Ezek. 3:18, 19) When I say to someone wicked, ‘You will surely die,’ but you do not warn him, and you fail to speak in order to warn the wicked one to turn from his wicked course so that he may stay alive, he will die for his error because he is wicked, but I will ask his blood back from you.* 19 But if you warn someone wicked and he does not turn back from his wickedness and from his wicked course, he will die for his error, but you will certainly save your own life.*

Or “I will hold you accountable for his blood.”

Or “soul.”

^ (Dan. 2:44) “In the days of those kings the God of heaven will set up a kingdom that will never be destroyed. And this kingdom will not be passed on to any other people. It will crush and put an end to all these kingdoms, and it alone will stand forever,

^ (Rev. 14:6, 7) And I saw another angel flying in midheaven,* and he had everlasting good news to declare to those who dwell on the earth, to every nation and tribe and tongue* and people. 7 He was saying in a loud voice: “Fear God and give him glory, because the hour of judgment by him has arrived, so worship the One who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and the springs* of water.”

Or “in midair; overhead.”

Or “language.”

Or “fountains.”

Thursday, August 13

The one who testifies faithfully will tell the truth.—[Prov. 12:17].

What should you do if the authorities restrict the Kingdom activity in your land and you are called in for questioning about your brothers? Must you tell them everything you know? What did Jesus do when he was interrogated by the Roman governor? In line with the Scriptural principle that there is “a time to be silent and a time to speak,” Jesus at times said nothing at all! ([Eccl. 3:1,][7;] Matt. 27:11-14) In such a setting, discretion is the better course, so that we do not put our brothers at risk. ([Prov. 10:19;][11:12]) What will you do if a close friend or relative has committed a serious sin and you know about the matter? “Tell the truth.” You have a responsibility to tell the elders the whole truth, and you must not distort it. They have a right to know the facts so that they can determine the best way to help the wrongdoer restore his or her relationship with Jehovah.—Jas. 5:14, 15. w18.10 10 ¶17-18

^ (Prov. 12:17) The one who testifies faithfully will tell the truth,* But a false witness speaks deceit.

Lit., “what is righteous.”

^ (Eccl. 3:1) There is an appointed time for everything, A time for every activity under the heavens:

^ (Eccl. 3:7) A time to rip apart and a time to sew together; A time to be silent and a time to speak;

^ (Matt. 27:11-14) Jesus now stood before the governor, and the governor put the question to him: “Are you the King of the Jews?” Jesus replied: “You yourself say it.” 12 But while he was being accused by the chief priests and elders, he made no answer. 13 Then Pilate said to him: “Do you not hear how many things they are testifying against you?” 14 But he did not answer him, no, not a word, so that the governor was very surprised.

^ (Prov. 10:19) When words are many, transgression cannot be avoided, But whoever controls his lips acts discreetly.

^ (Prov. 11:12) Whoever is lacking good sense* shows contempt for* his neighbor, But the man of true discernment remains silent.

Lit., “in want of heart.”

Or “despises.”

^ (Jas. 5:14, 15) Is there anyone sick among you? Let him call the elders of the congregation to him, and let them pray over him, applying oil to him in the name of Jehovah.* 15 And the prayer of faith will make the sick one* well, and Jehovah* will raise him up. Also, if he has committed sins, he will be forgiven.

See App. A5.

Or possibly, “tired one.”

See App. A5.

Friday, August 14

Keep encouraging one another and building one another up.—1 Thess. 5:11.

How can we build up others in love? One way is to be a good listener. ([Jas. 1:19]) To listen with empathy is an act of love. You may ask tactful and sympathetic questions with the aim of understanding the feelings of a sufferer. You will then be able to show empathy and to build up your fellow servant. Let your facial expressions reflect your sincere, loving concern. If the other Christian feels the need to explain things in greater detail, be patient and resist any urge to interrupt. By listening patiently, you will more likely understand the feelings involved. That can help your suffering brother or sister to have confidence in you and thus be more inclined to listen to what you say as you strive to be upbuilding. When you show that you truly care, your loving concern can be very comforting. w18.09 14 ¶10; 15 ¶13

^ (1 Thess. 5:11) Therefore, keep encouraging* one another and building one another up, just as you are in fact doing.

Or “comforting.”

^ (Jas. 1:19) Know this, my beloved brothers: Everyone must be quick to listen, slow to speak, slow to anger,

Saturday, August 15

Buy truth.—[Prov. 23:23].

Time is a price everyone who buys truth must pay. It takes time to listen to the Kingdom message, read the Bible and Bible literature, have a personal Bible study, and prepare for and attend congregation meetings. We must ‘buy out,’ or take, that time from some other less important activity. (Eph. 5:15, 16, ftn.) How much time will it take for us to gain an accurate knowledge of basic Bible teachings? That depends on our circumstances. There is no limit to what we can learn about Jehovah’s wisdom, ways, and works. ([Rom. 11:33]) The first issue of the Watch Tower likened the truth to “a modest little flower” and stated: “Be not content with one flower of truth. Had one been sufficient there would have been no more. Gather ever, seek for more.” Even with an eternity of time, we can always learn more about Jehovah. Today, the important thing is that we use our time wisely so as to buy as much truth as our circumstances allow. w18.11 4 ¶7

^ (Prov. 23:23) Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding.

Or “Acquire.”

^ (Eph. 5:15, 16) So keep strict watch that how you walk is not as unwise but as wise persons, 16 making the best use of your time,* because the days are wicked.

Lit., “buying out the appointed time.”

^ (Rom. 11:33) O the depth of God’s riches and wisdom and knowledge! How unsearchable his judgments are and beyond tracing out his ways are!

Sunday, August 16

Husbands, continue loving your wives.—[Eph. 5:25].

Husbands are exhorted to dwell with their wives “according to knowledge”—an expression that could also be rendered “showing them consideration; understanding them.” ([1 Pet. 3:7]; ftn.) Understanding and consideration go hand in hand. For instance, an understanding husband knows that his wife, as his complement, is different from him in many respects, but she is by no means inferior. ([Gen. 2:18]) He thus shows thoughtful regard for her feelings, treating her with dignity and honor. A thoughtful husband also takes his wife’s feelings into account when he interacts with other women. Never does he flirt with them or show an improper interest in them; nor does he show such interest when using social media or the Internet. ([Job 31:1]) Yes, he remains loyal to his wife, not just because of his love for her but also because of his love for God and his hatred for what is bad.—[Ps. 19:14;][97:10]. w18.09 29 ¶3-4

^ (Eph. 5:25) Husbands, continue loving your wives, just as the Christ also loved the congregation and gave himself up for it,

^ (1 Pet. 3:7) You husbands, in the same way, continue dwelling with them according to knowledge.* Assign them honor as to a weaker vessel, the feminine one, since they are also heirs with you of the undeserved favor of life, in order for your prayers not to be hindered.

Or “showing them consideration; understanding them.”

^ (Gen. 2:18) Then Jehovah God said: “It is not good for the man to continue to be alone. I am going to make a helper for him, as a complement of him.”

^ (Job 31:1) “I have made a covenant with my eyes. So how could I show improper attention to a virgin?

^ (Ps. 19:14) May the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart Be pleasing to you, O Jehovah, my Rock and my Redeemer.

^ (Ps. 97:10) O you who love Jehovah, hate what is bad. He is guarding the lives* of his loyal ones; He rescues them from the hand* of the wicked.

Or “souls.”

Or “power.”

Monday, August 17

The one who conducts himself as a lesser one among all of you is the one who is great.—[Luke 9:48].

Why is it a challenge to apply what we learn from God’s Word? One reason is that it takes humility to do what is right, and our ability to remain humble is under assault. In these “last days,” we are surrounded by people who are “lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty,” and “without self-control.” ([2 Tim. 3:1-3]) When selfish behavior is reported and even celebrated, a servant of God might despise such conduct but envy the results. ([Ps. 37:1;][73:3]) One might even wonder: ‘Is there any point in my putting others’ interests ahead of my own? If I conduct myself “as a lesser one,” might people lose respect for me?’ Allowing the world’s selfish spirit to influence us could harm the loving relationships we enjoy in the congregation and our identity as Christians. But we are rewarded when we study the good examples set out in the Bible and imitate them. w18.09 3 ¶1

^ (Luke 9:48) and said to them: “Whoever receives this young child on the basis of my name receives me also; and whoever receives me also receives the One who sent me. For the one who conducts himself as a lesser one among all of you is the one who is great.”

^ (2 Tim. 3:1-3) But know this, that in the last days critical times hard to deal with will be here. 2 For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal, 3 having no natural affection, not open to any agreement, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, without love of goodness,

^ (Ps. 37:1) Do not be upset* because of evil men Or envious of wrongdoers.

Or “show yourself heated up.”

^ (Ps. 73:3) For I became envious of the arrogant* When I would see the peace of the wicked.

Or “boasters.”

Tuesday, August 18

There is . . . happiness in giving.—[Acts 20:35].

Even though Jehovah was completely alone before he began to create, he was not thinking only of himself. On the contrary, he gave the gift of life to intelligent creatures, both spirit and human. “The happy God,” Jehovah, loves to give good things. ([1 Tim. 1:11;][Jas. 1:17]) And since he also wants us to be happy, he teaches us to be generous. ([Rom. 1:20]) God made man in his image. ([Gen. 1:27]) That is, we were created to reflect his personality. In order to attain happiness and fulfillment, then, we need to follow Jehovah’s example by being interested in others and by being generous givers. (Phil. 2:3, 4;[Jas. 1:5]) Why? Quite simply because Jehovah lovingly designed humans that way. Despite our imperfection, we can succeed in imitating Jehovah’s generosity. Jehovah wants his human creation to imitate him, so it makes him happy when we are generous.—[Eph. 5:1]. w18.08 18 ¶1-2; 19 ¶4

^ (Acts 20:35) I have shown you in all things that by working hard in this way, you must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

^ (1 Tim. 1:11) according to the glorious good news of the happy God, with which I was entrusted.

^ (Jas. 1:17) Every good gift and every perfect present is from above, coming down from the Father of the celestial lights, who does not vary or change like the shifting shadows.*

Or “with whom there is not a variation of the turning of the shadow.”

^ (Rom. 1:20) For his invisible qualities are clearly seen from the world’s creation onward, because they are perceived by the things made, even his eternal power and Godship, so that they are inexcusable.

^ (Gen. 1:27) And God went on to create the man in his image, in God’s image he created him; male and female he created them.

^ (Phil. 2:3, 4) Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you, 4 as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Jas. 1:5) So if any one of you is lacking in wisdom, let him keep asking God, for he gives generously to all and without reproaching,* and it will be given him.

Or “finding fault.”

^ (Eph. 5:1) Therefore, become imitators of God, as beloved children,

Wednesday, August 19

My sheep listen to my voice.—[John 10:27].

Christ’s followers show that they listen to Jesus by not only paying attention to his words but also acting on them. They are not distracted by the “anxieties of life.” ([Luke 21:34]) Rather, they make obeying Jesus’ commands a priority in life, even in the face of challenging circumstances. Through it all, our brothers remain faithful to Jehovah, cost what it may. Another way we can show that we are listening to Jesus is by cooperating with those whom he has appointed to take the lead among us. ([Heb. 13:7,][17]) God’s organization has made many adjustments in recent years, including the use of new tools and methods in our ministry, the format of our midweek meeting, and the way we build, renovate, and maintain our Kingdom Halls. How we appreciate the loving and carefully thought-out guidance! We can be sure that Jehovah will bless our efforts to follow the organization’s timely direction. w19.03 10-11 ¶11-12

^ (John 10:27) My sheep listen to my voice, and I know them, and they follow me.

^ (Luke 21:34) “But pay attention to yourselves that your hearts never become weighed down with overeating and heavy drinking and anxieties of life,* and suddenly that day be instantly upon you

Or “anxieties over livelihood; worries of daily life.”

^ (Heb. 13:7) Remember those who are taking the lead among you, who have spoken the word of God to you, and as you contemplate how their conduct turns out, imitate their faith.

^ (Heb. 13:17) Be obedient to those who are taking the lead among you and be submissive, for they are keeping watch over you* as those who will render an account, so that they may do this with joy and not with sighing, for this would be damaging to you.

Or “your souls.”

Thursday, August 20

We should no longer be . . . carried here and there . . . by means of the trickery of men.—[Eph. 4:14].

A story that is only 10 percent true is 100 percent misleading. Consider what happened to the Israelites dwelling on the western side of the Jordan River in the days of Joshua. (Josh. 22:9-34) They received a report that the Israelites living on the eastern side had constructed a large, impressive altar. That portion of the report was true. Based on this incomplete information, those on the western side concluded that their brothers had rebelled against Jehovah. (Josh. 22:9-12) Thankfully, before attacking, they sent a delegation of trustworthy men to get all the facts. What did the men learn? The altar was built, not for sacrifices, but as a memorial, so that in the future all would know that they too were faithful servants of Jehovah. How thankful those Israelites must have been that they did not massacre their brothers based on incomplete information but took the time to get the facts! w18.08 5 ¶9-10

^ (Eph. 4:14) So we should no longer be children, tossed about as by waves and carried here and there by every wind of teaching by means of the trickery of men, by means of cunning in deceptive schemes.

^ (Josh. 22:9-12) After that the Reuʹben·ites, the Gadʹites, and the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh departed from the other Israelites, from Shiʹloh in the land of Caʹnaan, and they returned to the land of Gilʹe·ad, the land of their possession where they had settled at the order of Jehovah through Moses. 10 When they came to the regions of the Jordan in the land of Caʹnaan, the Reuʹben·ites, the Gadʹites, and the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh built an altar there by the Jordan, a large, impressive altar. 11 Later the other Israelites heard it said: “Look! The Reuʹben·ites, the Gadʹites, and the half tribe of Ma·nasʹseh have built an altar on the frontier of the land of Caʹnaan in the regions of the Jordan on the side belonging to the Israelites.” 12 When the Israelites heard about it, the whole assembly of the Israelites congregated at Shiʹloh to go to war against them.

Friday, August 21

Let the one who thinks he is standing beware that he does not fall.—[1 Cor. 10:12].

As Paul pointed out, even true worshippers could become involved in wrong practices. Those who give in to temptation may think that they still have a good standing with Jehovah. But merely wanting to be Jehovah’s friend or claiming to be loyal to him does not always mean that one is actually approved by Jehovah. (1 Cor. 10:1-5) Just as the Israelites became anxious over Moses’ delay in coming down from Sinai, Christians today may feel anxious over the seeming delay of Jehovah’s day of judgment and the coming of the new world. The fulfillment of these promises may seem too far off in the future or too good to be true. Left unchecked, such thinking can lead us to put fleshly pursuits ahead of Jehovah’s will. In time, we could drift away from Jehovah and eventually engage in practices that we would never have considered being involved in when we were in good spiritual health. w18.07 21 ¶17-18

^ (1 Cor. 10:12) So let the one who thinks he is standing beware that he does not fall.

^ (1 Cor. 10:1-5) Now I want you to know, brothers, that our forefathers were all under the cloud and all passed through the sea 2 and all got baptized into Moses by means of the cloud and of the sea, 3 and all ate the same spiritual food 4 and all drank the same spiritual drink. For they used to drink from the spiritual rock that followed them, and that rock meant* the Christ. 5 Nevertheless, God was not pleased with most of them, for they were struck down in the wilderness.

Or “was.”

Saturday, August 22

I will also do this thing that you request, because you have found favor in my eyes and I know you by name.—[Ex. 33:17].

We can receive wonderful blessings when Jehovah comes to know us personally. But how can we put ourselves in a position to be known by Jehovah? We do that when we come to love him and dedicate our life to him. ([1 Cor. 8:3]) However, we need to maintain our treasured relationship with our heavenly Father. Like the Galatian Christians to whom Paul wrote, we too need to avoid slaving for “the weak and beggarly elementary things” of this world, including seeking its acclaim. ([Gal. 4:9]) Those first-century Christians had progressed to the point of being known by God. However, Paul said that the very same brothers were “turning back again” to empty things. Paul was, in effect, saying: “After you have come so far, why would you return to the foolish, valueless things you left behind?” w18.07 8 ¶5-6

^ (Ex. 33:17) Jehovah went on to say to Moses: “I will also do this thing that you request, because you have found favor in my eyes and I know you by name.”

^ (1 Cor. 8:3) But if anyone loves God, this one is known by him.

^ (Gal. 4:9) But now that you have come to know God or, rather, have come to be known by God, how is it that you are turning back again to the weak and beggarly elementary things and want to slave for them over again?

Sunday, August 23

A wise person listens and takes in more instruction.—[Prov. 1:5].

Thankfully, we do not need to suffer the consequences of breaking God’s laws to learn valuable lessons. We can learn from the mistakes of others whose transgressions are recorded in God’s Word. Indeed, we receive the very best instruction from God, such as when we read and meditate on real-life Bible accounts. For example, think of the pain that King David experienced after he disobeyed Jehovah’s command and committed adultery with Bath-sheba. (2 Sam. 12:7-14) While reading and meditating on this account, we might ask ourselves: ‘How could King David have avoided the heartache he suffered because of his adulterous act with Bath-sheba? If I faced a similar temptation, would I have the strength to turn away? Would I flee like Joseph, or would I give in like David?’ (Gen. 39:11-15) By reflecting on the bad consequences of sin, we can strengthen our heart to “hate what is bad.”—[Amos 5:15]. w18.06 17 ¶5, 7

^ (Prov. 1:5) A wise person listens and takes in more instruction; A man of understanding acquires skillful direction*

Or “wise guidance.”

^ (2 Sam. 12:7-14) Then Nathan said to David: “You are the man! This is what Jehovah the God of Israel says: ‘I myself anointed you as king over Israel, and I rescued you from the hand of Saul. 8 I was willing to give you your master’s house and put your master’s wives in your arms, and I gave you the house of Israel and of Judah. And as if that were not enough, I was willing to do much more for you. 9 Why did you despise the word of Jehovah by doing what is bad in his eyes? You struck down U·riʹah the Hitʹtite with the sword! Then you took his wife as your wife after you killed him by the sword of the Amʹmon·ites. 10 Now a sword will never depart from your own house, because you despised me by taking the wife of U·riʹah the Hitʹtite as your wife.’ 11 This is what Jehovah says: ‘Here I am bringing against you calamity from within your own house; and before your own eyes, I will take your wives and give them to another man,* and he will lie down with your wives in broad daylight.* 12 Although you acted in secret, I will do this in front of all Israel and in broad daylight.’”* 13 David then said to Nathan: “I have sinned against Jehovah.” Nathan replied to David: “Jehovah, in turn, forgives your sin.* You will not die. 14 Nevertheless, because you have treated Jehovah with utter disrespect in this matter, the son just born to you will certainly die.”

Or “to your fellow man.”

Lit., “to the eyes of this sun.”

Lit., “before the sun.”

Or “lets your sin pass by.”

^ (Gen. 39:11-15) But on one of the days when he went into the house to do his work, none of the household servants were in the house. 12 Then she grabbed hold of him by his garment and said: “Lie down with me!” But he left his garment in her hand and fled outside. 13 As soon as she saw that he had left his garment in her hand and had fled outside, 14 she began to cry out to the men of her house and to say to them: “Look! He brought to us this Hebrew man to make us a laughingstock. He came to me to lie down with me, but I began to cry out at the top of my voice. 15 Then as soon as he heard me raising my voice and screaming, he left his garment beside me and fled outside.”

^ (Amos 5:15) Hate what is bad, and love what is good, Let justice prevail in the city gate. It may be that Jehovah the God of armies Will show favor to the remaining ones of Joseph.’

Monday, August 24

Pay back . . . Caesar’s things to Caesar, but God’s things to God.—[Matt. 22:21].

Injustice often inflames political passions. Taxation was a hot political issue in Jesus’ time. Subjects of Rome, including those who listened to Jesus, were required to pay many taxes, such as on goods, land, and houses. And the corruption of the tax collectors increased the sense of being under a heavy burden. Tax collectors might purchase a position of authority at a public auction and then profit from what was collected. Zacchaeus, the chief tax collector in Jericho, had become rich by extorting money from the people. ([Luke 19:2,][8]) His course was probably typical of that of many. Jesus’ enemies tried to trap Jesus by getting him to take sides on a taxation issue. The tax in question was the “head tax,” a tax of one denarius levied on Roman subjects. (Matt. 22:16-18) The Jews especially resented this tax. It represented their subjection to Rome. w18.06 5-6 ¶8-10

^ (Matt. 22:21) They said: “Caesar’s.” Then he said to them: “Pay back, therefore, Caesar’s things to Caesar, but God’s things to God.”

^ (Luke 19:2) Now a man named Zac·chaeʹus was there; he was a chief tax collector, and he was rich.

^ (Luke 19:8) But Zac·chaeʹus stood up and said to the Lord: “Look! The half of my belongings, Lord, I am giving to the poor, and whatever I extorted from anyone, I am restoring four times over.”

^ (Matt. 22:16-18) So they sent their disciples to him, together with party followers of Herod, saying: “Teacher, we know you are truthful and teach the way of God in truth, and you do not seek anyone’s favor, for you do not look at the outward appearance of people. 17 Tell us, then, what do you think? Is it lawful* to pay head tax to Caesar or not?” 18 But Jesus, knowing their wickedness, said: “Why do you put me to the test, hypocrites?

Or “right.”

Tuesday, August 25

Whatever a person is sowing, this he will also reap.—[Gal. 6:7].

The costs of siding with Satan always outweigh any seeming benefits that he may offer. (Job 21:7-17;[Gal. 6:8]) What advantage do we gain from knowing the extent of Satan’s influence? It helps us keep a balanced view of secular authorities and motivates us in our witnessing work. We understand that Jehovah wants us to respect governmental authorities. ([1 Pet. 2:17]) And he expects us to obey the laws of human governments as long as those laws do not conflict with his standards. ([Rom. 13:1-4]) But we realize that we must remain neutral, never favoring one political party or human leader over another. (John 17:15, 16;[18:36]) Because we see what Satan is trying to do to Jehovah’s name and reputation, we feel more compelled to teach others the truth about our God. We proudly bear and use his name, knowing that loving him is far more rewarding than loving money or things.—[Isa. 43:10;] 1 Tim. 6:6-10. w18.05 24 ¶8-9

^ (Gal. 6:7) Do not be misled: God is not one to be mocked. For whatever a person is sowing, this he will also reap;

^ (Gal. 6:8) because the one sowing with a view to his flesh will reap corruption from his flesh, but the one sowing with a view to the spirit will reap everlasting life from the spirit.

^ (1 Pet. 2:17) Honor men of all sorts, have love for the whole association of brothers,* be in fear of God, honor the king.

Lit., “the brotherhood.”

^ (Rom. 13:1-4) Let every person be in subjection to the superior authorities, for there is no authority except by God; the existing authorities stand placed in their relative positions by God. 2 Therefore, whoever opposes* the authority has taken a stand against the arrangement of God; those who have taken a stand against it will bring judgment against themselves. 3 For those rulers are an object of fear, not to the good deed, but to the bad. Do you want to be free of fear of the authority? Keep doing good, and you will have praise from it; 4 for it is God’s minister* to you for your good. But if you are doing what is bad, be in fear, for it is not without purpose that it bears the sword. It is God’s minister, an avenger to express wrath against the one practicing what is bad.

Or “resists.”

Lit., “servant.”

^ (John 17:15, 16) “I do not request that you take them out of the world, but that you watch over them because of the wicked one. 16 They are no part of the world, just as I am no part of the world.

^ (John 18:36) Jesus answered: “My Kingdom is no part of this world. If my Kingdom were part of this world, my attendants would have fought that I should not be handed over to the Jews. But as it is, my Kingdom is not from this source.”

^ (Isa. 43:10) “You are my witnesses,” declares Jehovah, “Yes, my servant whom I have chosen, So that you may know and have faith in me* And understand that I am the same One. Before me no God was formed, And after me there has been none.

Or “and trust me.”

^ (1 Tim. 6:6-10) To be sure, there is great gain in godly devotion along with contentment.* 7 For we have brought nothing into the world, and neither can we carry anything out. 8 So, having food* and clothing,* we will be content with these things. 9 But those who are determined to be rich fall into temptation and a snare and many senseless and harmful desires that plunge men into destruction and ruin. 10 For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

Lit., “along with self-sufficiency.”

Or “sustenance.”

Or “shelter.” Lit., “covering.”

Wednesday, August 26

A wife should not separate from her husband.—[1 Cor. 7:10].

In the event of marital problems, is separation a justifiable solution? The Scriptures do not outline various grounds for separation. Paul wrote: “If a woman has an unbelieving husband and he is agreeable to staying with her, let her not leave her husband.” (1 Cor. 7:12, 13) That applies in our day too. Admittedly, there have been instances where an “unbelieving husband” seems to prove that he is not “agreeable to staying with her.” He might be extremely physically abusive, even to the point that she feels that her health or life is in danger. He might refuse to support her and the family or severely endanger her spirituality. In such cases, some Christians have personally decided that, despite what he might say, the mate is not “agreeable to staying” together and that a separation is necessary. But other Christians in comparably difficult situations have not; they have endured and tried to work at improving matters. w18.12 13 ¶14, 16; 14 ¶17

^ (1 Cor. 7:10) To the married people I give instructions, not I but the Lord, that a wife should not separate from her husband.

^ (1 Cor. 7:12, 13) But to the others I say, yes, I, not the Lord: If any brother has an unbelieving wife and she is agreeable to staying with him, let him not leave her; 13 and if a woman has an unbelieving husband and he is agreeable to staying with her, let her not leave her husband.

Thursday, August 27

These are the ones who . . . bear fruit with endurance.—[Luke 8:15].

In the illustration of the sower found at [Luke 8:5-8,][11-15], the seed is “the word of God,” or the Kingdom message. The soil represents man’s figurative heart. The seed that fell on the fine soil took root, sprouted, and “produced 100 times more fruit.” Just as the fine soil in Jesus’ illustration retained the seed, we accepted the message and held on to it. As a result, the seedlike Kingdom message took root and grew, as it were, into a wheat stalk that, in time, was ready to bear fruit. And just as a wheat stalk produces as fruit, not new stalks, but new seed, we are producing as fruit, not new disciples, but new Kingdom seed. How do we produce new Kingdom seed? Each time we in one way or another proclaim the Kingdom message, we duplicate and scatter, so to speak, the seed that was planted in our heart. ([Luke 6:45;][8:1]) Hence, this illustration teaches us that as long as we keep on proclaiming the Kingdom message, we “bear fruit with endurance.” w18.05 14 ¶10-11

^ (Luke 8:15) As for that on the fine soil, these are the ones who, after hearing the word with a fine and good heart, retain it and bear fruit with endurance.

^ (Luke 8:5-8) “A sower went out to sow his seed. As he was sowing, some of them fell alongside the road and were trampled on, and the birds of heaven ate them up. 6 Some landed on the rock, and after sprouting, they dried up because they had no moisture. 7 Others fell among the thorns, and the thorns that grew up with them choked them. 8 But others fell on the good soil, and after sprouting, they produced 100 times more fruit.” As he said these things, he called out: “Let the one who has ears to listen, listen.”

^ (Luke 8:11-15) Now the illustration means this: The seed is the word of God. 12 Those alongside the road are the ones who have heard, and then the Devil comes and takes the word away from their hearts so that they may not believe and be saved. 13 Those on the rock are the ones who, when they hear the word, receive it with joy, but these have no root. They believe for a while, but in a season of testing, they fall away. 14 As for that which fell among the thorns, these are the ones who have heard, but by being carried away by anxieties, riches, and pleasures of this life, they are completely choked and bring nothing to maturity. 15 As for that on the fine soil, these are the ones who, after hearing the word with a fine and good heart, retain it and bear fruit with endurance.

^ (Luke 6:45) A good man brings good out of the good treasure of his heart, but a wicked man brings what is wicked out of his wicked treasure; for out of the heart’s abundance his mouth speaks.

^ (Luke 8:1) Shortly afterward he traveled from city to city and from village to village, preaching and declaring the good news of the Kingdom of God. And the Twelve were with him,

Friday, August 28

All those for whom I have affection, I reprove and discipline.—[Rev. 3:19].

Paul was willing not only to encourage his brothers but also to “spend and be completely spent for” them. ([2 Cor. 12:15]) Similarly, elders should not only encourage and console their brothers with words but also build them up by showing sincere personal interest. ([1 Cor. 14:3]) Building one another up may involve giving counsel, but here again, elders should follow the example given in the Bible about how to give counsel in an encouraging way. An outstanding example in this respect was given by Jesus himself after his death and resurrection. He had some firm counsel to give to certain congregations in Asia Minor, but notice how he went about it. Before giving them counsel, he gave warm commendation to the congregations in Ephesus, Pergamum, and Thyatira. ([Rev. 2:1-5,][12, 13,][18, 19]) Elders would do well to imitate Christ’s example when they need to give counsel. w18.04 22 ¶8-9

^ (Rev. 3:19) “‘All those for whom I have affection, I reprove and discipline. So be zealous and repent.

^ (2 Cor. 12:15) For my part, I will most gladly spend and be completely spent for you.* If I love you so much more, am I to be loved the less?

Or “your souls.”

^ (1 Cor. 14:3) However, the one who prophesies builds up and encourages and consoles men by his speech.

^ (Rev. 2:1-5) “To the angel of the congregation in Ephʹe·sus write: These are the things that he says who holds the seven stars in his right hand and walks among the seven golden lampstands: 2 ‘I know your deeds, and your labor and endurance, and that you cannot tolerate bad men, and that you put to the test those who say they are apostles, but they are not, and you found them to be liars. 3 You are also showing endurance, and you have persevered for the sake of my name and have not grown weary. 4 Nevertheless, I hold this against you, that you have left the love you had at first. 5 “‘Therefore remember from where you have fallen, and repent and do the deeds you did at first. If you do not, I will come to you, and I will remove your lampstand from its place, unless you repent.

^ (Rev. 2:12, 13) “To the angel of the congregation in Perʹga·mum write: These are the things that he says who has the sharp, long, two-edged sword: 13 ‘I know where you are dwelling, that is, where the throne of Satan is; and yet you keep holding fast to my name, and you did not deny your faith in me even in the days of Anʹti·pas, my faithful witness, who was killed by your side, where Satan is dwelling.

^ (Rev. 2:18, 19) “To the angel of the congregation in Thy·a·tiʹra write: These are the things that the Son of God says, the one who has eyes like a fiery flame and whose feet are like fine copper: 19 ‘I know your deeds, and your love and faith and ministry and endurance, and that your deeds of late are more than those you did at first.

Saturday, August 29

Fathers, . . . go on bringing [your children] up in the discipline and admonition of Jehovah.—[Eph. 6:4].

Parents, you no doubt do all you can to protect your children from literal diseases. You keep your home clean, and you throw out anything that might cause you or your children to get sick. In the same way, you need to protect your children from movies, TV shows, electronic games, and websites that are likely to infect them with Satan’s thinking. Jehovah has given you the authority to care for the spiritual health of your children. ([Prov. 1:8]) So do not be afraid to set household rules that are based on Bible standards. Tell your young children what they can and cannot watch, and help them to understand the reasons for your decisions. ([Matt. 5:37]) As your children get older, train them to discern for themselves what is right and what is wrong according to Jehovah’s standards. ([Heb. 5:14]) And remember, your children will learn even more from what you do.—Deut. 6:6, 7;[Rom. 2:21]. w19.01 16 ¶8

^ (Eph. 6:4) And fathers, do not be irritating your children, but go on bringing them up in the discipline and admonition* of Jehovah.*

Or “instruction; guidance.” Lit., “putting mind in.”

See App. A5.

^ (Prov. 1:8) Listen, my son, to the discipline of your father, And do not forsake the instruction* of your mother.

Or “law.”

^ (Matt. 5:37) Just let your word ‘Yes’ mean yes, your ‘No,’ no, for what goes beyond these is from the wicked one.*

Or possibly, “from what is wicked.”

^ (Heb. 5:14) But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their powers of discernment* trained to distinguish both right and wrong.

Or “their perceptive powers.”

^ (Deut. 6:6, 7) These words that I am commanding you today must be on your heart, 7 and you must inculcate them in* your sons and speak of them when you sit in your house and when you walk on the road and when you lie down and when you get up.

Or “repeat them to; impress them upon.”

^ (Rom. 2:21) do you, however, the one teaching someone else, not teach yourself? You, the one preaching, “Do not steal,” do you steal?

Sunday, August 30

Old men and young together. Let them praise the name of Jehovah.—Ps. 148:12, 13.

If you are a Christian youth, why not make it your aim to take an interest in older ones? You might respectfully ask them to relate an experience from their years of service. You will find this very upbuilding, and both you and they will be even more motivated to let the light of truth shine. And all of us can make it a point to welcome those who attend meetings at the Kingdom Hall. If you are assigned to handle a meeting for field service, you can do much to help older ones to have a share in the ministry. Do they have suitable territory? In some cases, you may choose to assign them to work with a younger companion who can provide physical support. You can also show understanding to those whose health and circumstances limit what they can do. Yes, your consideration and discernment can help young and old, experienced and less experienced, to preach the good news with zeal.—[Lev. 19:32]. w18.06 23-24 ¶10-12

^ (Ps. 148:12, 13) You young men and young women,* Old men and young together.* 13 Let them praise the name of Jehovah, For his name alone is unreachably high. His majesty is above earth and heaven.

Lit., “virgins.”

Or “Old and young together.”

^ (Lev. 19:32) “‘Before gray hair you should rise up, and you must show honor to an older man, and you must be in fear of your God. I am Jehovah.

Monday, August 31

[Use] your freedom, not as a cover for doing wrong, but as slaves of God.—[1 Pet. 2:16].

We should never take for granted that Jehovah liberated us from the bondage of sin and of death. By means of the ransom, we can serve our God with a clean conscience and find real delight in doing so. ([Ps. 40:8]) In addition to expressing gratitude, however, we should be mindful of never misusing our precious freedom. The apostle Peter warned against using our freedom as an excuse for catering to our fleshly desires. Does that warning not remind you of what befell the Israelites in the wilderness? And the danger is still with us, perhaps even more so. Satan and his world offer ever more alluring choices in dress and grooming, food and drink, recreation and entertainment, and a host of other things. Clever advertisers often feature attractive people deceptively promoting as must-haves many things we really do not need. How easy it is to fall prey to these ploys and to misuse our freedom! w18.04 10 ¶7-8

^ (1 Pet. 2:16) Be as free people, using your freedom, not as a cover* for doing wrong, but as slaves of God.

Or “an excuse.”

^ (Ps. 40:8) To do your will, O my God, is my delight,* And your law is deep within me.

Or “desire.”

September

Tuesday, September 1

Though you never saw him, you love him.—[1 Pet. 1:8].

Jesus showed fellow feeling for Martha and Mary. When he saw their grief over the death of their brother, Lazarus, “Jesus gave way to tears.” (John 11:32-35) He did not weep just because he had lost the company of a close friend. After all, he knew that he was going to resurrect Lazarus. Rather, Jesus wept because he understood and was touched by the heartache of his dear friends. We benefit greatly from learning about Jesus’ fellow feeling. Of course, we are not perfect as he was. Yet, we love him for the way he treated others. We are encouraged to know that he is now ruling as King of God’s Kingdom. He will soon eliminate all suffering. He is in the best position to help humanity recover from the wounds inflicted by Satan’s rulership, for Jesus too was once human. Indeed, we are blessed to have a Ruler who can “sympathize with our weaknesses.”—Heb. 2:17, 18;[4:15, 16]. w19.03 17 ¶12-13

^ (1 Pet. 1:8) Though you never saw him, you love him. Though you do not see him now, yet you exercise faith in him and are greatly rejoicing with an indescribable and glorious joy,

^ (John 11:32-35) When Mary arrived where Jesus was and caught sight of him, she fell at his feet and said to him: “Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died.” 33 When Jesus saw her weeping and the Jews who had come with her weeping, he groaned within himself and became troubled. 34 He said: “Where have you laid him?” They said to him: “Lord, come and see.” 35 Jesus gave way to tears.

^ (Heb. 2:17, 18) Consequently, he had to become like his “brothers” in all respects, so that he could become a merciful and faithful high priest in things relating to God, in order to offer a propitiatory sacrifice* for the sins of the people. 18 Since he himself has suffered when being put to the test, he is able to come to the aid of those who are being put to the test.

Or “to offer an atoning sacrifice; to make atonement.”

^ (Heb. 4:15, 16) For we do not have a high priest who cannot sympathize with our weaknesses, but we have one who has been tested in all respects as we have, but without sin. 16 Let us, then, approach the throne of undeserved kindness with freeness of speech, so that we may receive mercy and find undeserved kindness to help us at the right time.

Wednesday, September 2

No man can come to me unless the Father, who sent me, draws him.—[John 6:44].

We can play a part in helping others learn about God, but we do not play the most important part. (1 Cor. 3:6, 7) Jehovah is the one who draws people. In the end, each individual will respond to the good news based on his or her heart condition. ([Matt. 13:4-8]) Remember that most people did not accept Jesus’ message—and he was the greatest Teacher who ever lived! Really, then, we should not become discouraged if many of the people we try to help do not respond favorably. We will see benefits when we show fellow feeling in our ministry. We will enjoy our preaching work more. We will experience the greater happiness that comes from giving. And we make it easier for those who are “rightly disposed for everlasting life” to accept the good news. ([Acts 13:48]) So “as long as we have the opportunity, let us work what is good toward all.” ([Gal. 6:10]) Then we will have the joy of bringing glory to our heavenly Father.—[Matt. 5:16]. w19.03 25 ¶18-19

^ (John 6:44) No man can come to me unless the Father, who sent me, draws him, and I will resurrect him on the last day.

^ (1 Cor. 3:6, 7) I planted, A·polʹlos watered, but God kept making it grow, 7 so that neither is the one who plants anything nor is the one who waters, but God who makes it grow.

^ (Matt. 13:4-8) As he was sowing, some seeds fell alongside the road, and the birds came and ate them up. 5 Others fell on rocky ground where there was not much soil, and they immediately sprang up because the soil was not deep. 6 But when the sun rose, they were scorched, and they withered because they had no root. 7 Others fell among the thorns, and the thorns came up and choked them. 8 Still others fell on the fine soil, and they began to yield fruit, this one 100 times more, that one 60, the other 30.

^ (Acts 13:48) When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.

^ (Gal. 6:10) So, then, as long as we have the opportunity,* let us work what is good toward all, but especially toward those related to us in the faith.

Lit., “appointed time.”

^ (Matt. 5:16) Likewise, let your light shine before men, so that they may see your fine works and give glory to your Father who is in the heavens.

Thursday, September 3

In the midst of the congregation I will praise you.—[Ps. 22:22].

King David wrote: “Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise.” ([Ps. 145:3]) He loved Jehovah, and that love moved him to praise God “in the midst of the congregation.” (1 Chron. 29:10-13;[Ps. 40:5]) Today, one way we praise Jehovah is by commenting during Christian meetings. All of us appreciate hearing a variety of comments at our meetings. We enjoy the simple, sincere words of a young child. We are inspired by the excitement in the voice of someone who is commenting about a truth that he or she has just discovered. And we admire those who “mustered up courage” to give a comment, even though they are shy or are only beginning to learn our language. ([1 Thess. 2:2]; ftn.) How can we show appreciation for their effort? We can thank them for their encouraging comment after the meeting. Another way is by giving a comment ourselves. Then not only do we receive encouragement at our meetings but we also give it.—Rom. 1:11, 12. w19.01 8 ¶1-2; 9 ¶6

^ (Ps. 22:22) I will declare your name to my brothers; In the midst of the congregation I will praise you.

^ (Ps. 145:3) Jehovah is great and most worthy of praise; His greatness is unsearchable.*

Or “beyond understanding.”

^ (1 Chron. 29:10-13) Then David praised Jehovah before the eyes of all the congregation. David said: “May you be praised, O Jehovah the God of Israel our father, throughout all eternity.* 11 Yours, O Jehovah, are the greatness and the mightiness and the beauty and the splendor and the majesty,* for everything in the heavens and on the earth is yours. Yours is the kingdom, O Jehovah. You are the One exalting yourself as head over all. 12 The riches and the glory are from you, and you rule over everything, and in your hand there are power and mightiness, and your hand is able to make great and to give strength to all. 13 And now, O our God, we thank you and praise your beautiful name.

Or “from eternity to eternity.”

Or “dignity.”

^ (Ps. 40:5) How many things you have done, O Jehovah my God, Your wonderful works and your thoughts toward us. None can compare to you; If I were to try to tell and speak of them, They would be too numerous to recount!

^ (1 Thess. 2:2) For although we had first suffered and been insolently treated in Phi·lipʹpi, as you know, we mustered up boldness* by means of our God to tell you the good news of God in the face of much opposition.*

Or “courage.”

Or possibly, “amid much struggling.”

^ (Rom. 1:11, 12) For I am longing to see you, that I may impart some spiritual gift to you for you to be made firm; 12 or, rather, that we may have an interchange of encouragement by one another’s faith, both yours and mine.

Friday, September 4

Show yourselves thankful.—[Col. 3:15].

The ten men were desperate. They had leprosy, and the future looked bleak. But one day, they saw Jesus, the Great Teacher, from a distance. They had heard that Jesus healed all sorts of sicknesses. So they cried out: “Jesus, Instructor, have mercy on us!” The ten men were completely cured. No doubt all of them were grateful for Jesus’ kindness. One of them, however, did more than feel gratitude—he expressed his appreciation to Jesus. That healed man, a Samaritan, felt compelled to glorify God “with a loud voice.” (Luke 17:12-19) Like the Samaritan, we want to express our gratitude to those who are kind. Jehovah sets the example for us in expressing appreciation. One way he does this is by rewarding those who please him. (2 Sam. 22:21;[Ps. 13:6;] Matt. 10:40, 41) And the Scriptures encourage us to “become imitators of God, as beloved children.” ([Eph. 5:1]) So a key reason why we should express appreciation is that we want to follow Jehovah’s example. w19.02 14 ¶1-2; 15 ¶4

^ (Col. 3:15) Also, let the peace of the Christ rule in your hearts,* for you were called to that peace in one body. And show yourselves thankful.

Or “control your hearts.”

^ (Luke 17:12-19) And as he was entering a village, ten men with leprosy met him, but they stood at a distance. 13 And they raised their voices and said: “Jesus, Instructor, have mercy on us!” 14 When he saw them, he said to them: “Go and show yourselves to the priests.” Then as they were going off, they were cleansed. 15 One of them, when he saw that he was healed, turned back, glorifying God with a loud voice. 16 And he fell facedown at Jesus’ feet, thanking him. Furthermore, he was a Sa·marʹi·tan. 17 In reply Jesus said: “All ten were cleansed, were they not? Where, then, are the other nine? 18 Did no one else turn back to give glory to God except this man of another nation?” 19 Then he said to him: “Get up and be on your way; your faith has made you well.”*

Or “has saved you.”

^ (2 Sam. 22:21) Jehovah rewards me according to my righteousness; He repays me according to the innocence* of my hands.

Lit., “the cleanness.”

^ (Ps. 13:6) I will sing to Jehovah, for he has richly rewarded me.*

Or “he has dealt rewardingly with me.”

^ (Matt. 10:40, 41) “Whoever receives you receives me also, and whoever receives me receives also the One who sent me. 41 Whoever receives a prophet because he is a prophet will get a prophet’s reward, and whoever receives a righteous man because he is a righteous man will get a righteous man’s reward.

^ (Eph. 5:1) Therefore, become imitators of God, as beloved children,

Saturday, September 5

I will not renounce my integrity!—[Job 27:5].

A young girl at school respectfully refuses to join in a holiday celebration that does not please God. A shy young man preaching from door to door knocks on the door of a fellow student who has made fun of Jehovah’s Witnesses before. A man working hard to provide for his family is asked by his boss to do something dishonest or illegal. Though he could lose his job, the man explains that he must be honest and obey the law because God requires that of his servants. ([Rom. 13:1-4;][Heb. 13:18]) What quality do you see in those three individuals? You may notice several, such as courage and honesty. But one quality stands out as especially precious—integrity. Each of the three shows loyalty to Jehovah. Each one refuses to compromise on God’s standards. Integrity moves those individuals to act as they do. Jehovah would surely feel proud of each one of them for showing that quality. We likewise want to make our Father in heaven proud. w19.02 2 ¶1-2

^ (Job 27:5) It is unthinkable for me to declare you men righteous! Until I die, I will not renounce* my integrity!

Or “I will not take away from myself; I will maintain.”

^ (Rom. 13:1-4) Let every person be in subjection to the superior authorities, for there is no authority except by God; the existing authorities stand placed in their relative positions by God. 2 Therefore, whoever opposes* the authority has taken a stand against the arrangement of God; those who have taken a stand against it will bring judgment against themselves. 3 For those rulers are an object of fear, not to the good deed, but to the bad. Do you want to be free of fear of the authority? Keep doing good, and you will have praise from it; 4 for it is God’s minister* to you for your good. But if you are doing what is bad, be in fear, for it is not without purpose that it bears the sword. It is God’s minister, an avenger to express wrath against the one practicing what is bad.

Or “resists.”

Lit., “servant.”

^ (Heb. 13:18) Keep praying for us, for we trust we have an honest* conscience, as we wish to conduct ourselves honestly in all things.

Lit., “good.”

Sunday, September 6

The Law has a shadow of the good things to come.—[Heb. 10:1].

The Law specifically protected those who could not protect themselves, such as orphans, widows, and foreign residents. The judges in Israel were told: “You must not pervert the judgment of the foreign resident or of the fatherless child, and you must not seize the garment of a widow as security for a loan.” ([Deut. 24:17]) Jehovah showed tender personal interest in the most vulnerable in the community. And he held those who mistreated them to account. ([Ex. 22:22-24]) Jehovah wants those he places in positions of responsibility to take a loving interest in all whom they oversee. He hates sex crimes and wants to ensure that all, especially the most vulnerable, receive protection and justice. (Lev. 18:6-30) When we are convinced that Jehovah is treating us justly, our love for him grows. And when we love God and love his righteous standards, we feel impelled to love others and treat them justly. w19.02 24-25 ¶22-26

^ (Heb. 10:1) For since the Law has a shadow of the good things to come, but not the very substance of the things, it* can never, by the same sacrifices that are continually offered year after year, make those who approach perfect.

Or possibly, “men.”

^ (Deut. 24:17) “You must not pervert the judgment of the foreign resident or of the fatherless child,* and you must not seize the garment of a widow as security for a loan.*

Or “the orphan.”

Or “as a pledge.”

^ (Ex. 22:22-24) “You must not afflict any widow or fatherless child.* 23 If you afflict him at all, so that he cries out to me, I will unfailingly hear his outcry; 24 and my anger will blaze, and I will kill you with the sword, and your wives will become widows, and your children will be fatherless.

Or “orphan.”

Monday, September 7

Reject ungodliness and worldly desires.—[Titus 2:12].

Consider an example of how we can protect ourselves from being influenced by Satan’s thinking. Jehovah has taught us that “sexual immorality and every sort of uncleanness [should] not even be mentioned among [us].” ([Eph. 5:3]) But what will we do if peers at work or at school start talking about sexually immoral topics? The watchman, our conscience, might sound an alarm. ([Rom. 2:15]) But will we listen to it? We might be tempted, instead, to listen to our peers or to look at pictures they might be sharing. But this is the time to close the city gates, so to speak, by changing the conversation or by walking away. It takes courage to resist pressure from our peers to think about or to do wrong things. We can be sure that Jehovah sees the effort we make, and he will give us the strength and wisdom we need to resist satanic thinking.—2 Chron. 16:9;[Isa. 40:29;][Jas. 1:5]. w19.01 17-18 ¶12-13

^ (Titus 2:12) It trains us to reject ungodliness and worldly desires and to live with soundness of mind and righteousness and godly devotion amid this present system of things,*

Or “this present age.” See Glossary.

^ (Eph. 5:3) Let sexual immorality* and every sort of uncleanness or greediness not even be mentioned among you, just as is proper for holy people;

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ (Rom. 2:15) They are the very ones who demonstrate the matter of the law to be written in their hearts, while their conscience is bearing witness with them, and by* their own thoughts they are being accused or even excused.

Lit., “between.”

^ (2 Chron. 16:9) For the eyes of Jehovah are roving about through all the earth to show his strength* in behalf of those whose heart is complete toward* him. You have acted foolishly in this matter; from now on there will be wars against you.”

Or “support.”

Or “completely devoted to.”

^ (Isa. 40:29) He gives power to the tired one And full might to those lacking strength.*

Or “dynamic energy.”

^ (Jas. 1:5) So if any one of you is lacking in wisdom, let him keep asking God, for he gives generously to all and without reproaching,* and it will be given him.

Or “finding fault.”

Tuesday, September 8

When I reflected on all the works that my own hands had done . . . , I saw that everything was futile . . . There was nothing of real value.—[Eccl. 2:11].

Fabulously rich and powerful, Solomon embarked on an experiment to “try out pleasure and see what good [would come].” ([Eccl. 2:1-10]) He built houses, designed gardens and parks, and pursued whatever he desired. How did he feel afterward? Contented? Fulfilled? Satisfied? We need not guess. Solomon himself told us in today’s text. What a powerful lesson! Will you wisely take it to heart? Jehovah wants to spare you the pain of learning life’s lessons the hard way. Granted, you need faith in order to obey God and put his will first in your life. That faith is invaluable, and it never disappoints. Yes, Jehovah will never forget “the love you showed for his name.” ([Heb. 6:10]) So work hard to build a strong faith, and thus see for yourself that your heavenly Father has your best interests at heart.—[Ps. 32:8]. w18.12 22 ¶14-15

^ (Eccl. 2:11) But when I reflected on all the works that my own hands had done and on all the hard work that I had toiled to accomplish, I saw that everything was futile, a chasing after the wind; there was nothing of real value* under the sun.

Or “of advantage.”

^ (Eccl. 2:1-10) Then I said in my heart: “Come and let me try out pleasure* and see what good comes.” But look! that too was futility.  2 I said about laughter, “It is madness!” And about pleasure,* “What use is it?” 3 I explored with my heart by indulging myself with wine, all the while maintaining my own wisdom; I even embraced foolishness to find out what was the best thing for humans to do during their few days of life under the heavens. 4 I undertook great works. I built houses for myself; I planted vineyards for myself. 5 I made gardens and parks for myself, and I planted in them all sorts of fruit trees. 6 I made pools of water for myself, to irrigate a grove* of flourishing trees. 7 I acquired male and female servants, and I had servants born in my household.* I also acquired much livestock—cattle and flocks—more than any of my predecessors in Jerusalem. 8 I accumulated silver and gold for myself, the treasures of* kings and of provinces. I gathered male and female singers for myself, as well as what brings great pleasure to the sons of men—a woman, yes, many women.* 9 So I grew great and surpassed anyone prior to me in Jerusalem. And my wisdom remained with me. 10 I did not deny myself anything that I desired.* I did not withhold from my heart any sort of pleasure,* for my heart was joyful because of all my hard work, and this was my reward* for all my hard work.

Or “rejoicing.”

Or “rejoicing.”

Or “forest.”

Lit., “sons of the house.”

Or “property peculiar to.”

Or “a lady, yes, ladies.”

Lit., “that my eyes asked for.”

Or “rejoicing.”

Or “portion.”

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (Ps. 32:8) “I will give you insight and instruct you in the way you should go. I will give you advice with my eye upon you.

Wednesday, September 9

God recommends his own love to us in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.—[Rom. 5:8].

A spiritual person has faith in God and has God’s mind on matters. He looks to God for guidance and is determined to obey him. (1 Cor. 2:12, 13) David is a good example. He sang: “Jehovah is my portion, my allotted share, and my cup.” ([Ps. 16:5]) That “portion” included David’s approved relationship with God, in whom he took refuge. ([Ps. 16:1]) The result? “My whole being is joyful,” he wrote. Yes, nothing gave David more joy than intimacy with God. ([Ps. 16:9,][11]) The joy that David experienced does not come to those who center their lives on pleasures and riches. (1 Tim. 6:9, 10) Developing faith in Jehovah and serving him will give your life meaning and provide you with satisfaction. How can you grow in faith? You must spend time with him, as it were, by reading his Word, observing his creation, and thinking about his qualities, including his love for you.—[Rom. 1:20]. w18.12 25 ¶7-8

^ (Rom. 5:8) But God recommends his own love to us* in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ died for us.

Or “demonstrates (shows) his own love for us.”

^ (1 Cor. 2:12, 13) Now we received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit that is from God, so that we might know the things that have been kindly given us by God. 13 These things we also speak, not with words taught by human wisdom, but with those taught by the spirit, as we explain* spiritual matters with spiritual words.

Or “combine.”

^ (Ps. 16:5) Jehovah is my portion, my allotted share, and my cup. You safeguard my inheritance.

^ (Ps. 16:1) Protect me, O God, for I have taken refuge in you.

^ (Ps. 16:9) So my heart rejoices, my whole being* is joyful. And I reside* in security.

Lit., “my glory.”

Or “my flesh resides.”

^ (Ps. 16:11) You make known to me the path of life. In your presence* is abundant joy; There is happiness* at your right hand forever.

Lit., “With your face.”

Or “pleasantness.”

^ (1 Tim. 6:9, 10) But those who are determined to be rich fall into temptation and a snare and many senseless and harmful desires that plunge men into destruction and ruin. 10 For the love of money is a root of all sorts of injurious things, and by reaching out for this love some have been led astray from the faith and have stabbed themselves all over with many pains.

^ (Rom. 1:20) For his invisible qualities are clearly seen from the world’s creation onward, because they are perceived by the things made, even his eternal power and Godship, so that they are inexcusable.

Thursday, September 10

Let marriage be honorable among all.—[Heb. 13:4].

Paul was not making a mere casual observation. Rather, that text was directing, yes urging, Christians personally to esteem marriage, to view it as precious. Is that your view of marriage in general and particularly of your own marriage if you have a mate? In honoring marriage, you are in the best of company. Jesus honored marriage. When the Pharisees asked Jesus about divorce, he referred to what God had said regarding the first marriage: “For this reason a man will leave his father and his mother, and the two will be one flesh.” Jesus added: “What God has yoked together, let no man put apart.” (Mark 10:2-12;[Gen. 2:24]) Jesus thus agreed that marriage is of divine origin and stressed its permanence. God did not tell Adam and Eve that marriage could be ended by divorce. The standard set in that Edenic marriage was monogamy, “the two” being joined together in a lasting union. w18.12 10-11 ¶2-4

^ (Heb. 13:4) Let marriage be honorable among all, and let the marriage bed be without defilement, for God will judge sexually immoral people* and adulterers.

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

^ (Gen. 2:24) That is why a man will leave his father and his mother and he will stick to* his wife, and they will become one flesh.

Or “remain with.”

Friday, September 11

Be transformed by making your mind over.—[Rom. 12:2].

When we first came to a knowledge of the truth, we learned the importance of obedience to Jehovah’s basic requirements. But as we continue to grow spiritually, we learn more about Jehovah’s thinking—his likes, his dislikes, and his way of viewing various matters—and this influences our actions and personal choices. While learning to think like Jehovah is a delight, it can also be a challenge. At times, our imperfect reasoning might get in the way. For example, we might have difficulty understanding Jehovah’s view of moral cleanness, materialism, the preaching work, the misuse of blood, or something else. What can we do? How can we continue to make progress in making God’s thoughts our own? The answer lies in making our mind over by studying God’s Word with a view to grasping his thoughts, meditating on them, and bringing our thinking into alignment with God’s thinking. w18.11 23-24 ¶2-4

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

Saturday, September 12

How long must I ask for help from violence, but you do not intervene?—[Hab. 1:2].

Habakkuk lived during a very difficult and challenging time. He was deeply saddened because he was surrounded by wicked, violent people. When would their wickedness end? Why did Jehovah take so long before acting? All Habakkuk saw was injustice and oppression practiced by his own countrymen. He felt helpless. So in the midst of this dark period, he called on Jehovah to intervene. Habakkuk may have started to imagine that Jehovah was not concerned. It seemed that God would not act soon enough. Can you identify with the feelings of this dear servant of God? Had Habakkuk lost trust in Jehovah? Did he fail to maintain his faith in God’s promises? By no means! The mere fact that he entrusted his problems and concerns to Jehovah and not to humans shows that he had not given up in despair. He was obviously troubled because he could not understand God’s timing or the reason why Jehovah allowed him to be in such a painful situation. w18.11 14 ¶4-5

^ (Hab. 1:2) How long, O Jehovah, must I cry for help, but you do not hear? How long must I ask for help from violence, but you do not intervene?*

Or “save.”

Sunday, September 13

Stop storing up for yourselves treasures on the earth.—[Matt. 6:19].

When the fishermen Peter and Andrew were invited by Jesus to become “fishers of men,” they “abandoned their nets.” (Matt. 4:18-20) Of course, most of those who learn the truth today cannot simply walk away from their jobs. They have Scriptural obligations. ([1 Tim. 5:8]) However, individuals who learn the truth must often change their attitude toward material things and adjust their priorities. Consider the example of Maria. Golf was her life, and her goal was to enjoy a lucrative career as a professional golfer. Then Maria started to study the Bible, and she was pleased with the changes that the truth helped her make in her life. Maria realized that it would be difficult for her to pursue both spiritual and material riches. ([Matt. 6:24]) She gave up her lifelong goal of becoming a professional golfer. She now serves as a pioneer and enjoys what she describes as “the happiest, most meaningful life possible.” w18.11 5 ¶9-10

^ (Matt. 6:19) “Stop storing up for yourselves treasures on the earth, where moth and rust consume and where thieves break in and steal.

^ (Matt. 4:18-20) Walking alongside the Sea of Galʹi·lee, he saw two brothers, Simon, who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother, casting a net into the sea, for they were fishermen. 19 And he said to them: “Come after me, and I will make you fishers of men.”* 20 At once they abandoned their nets and followed him.

Or “people.”

^ (1 Tim. 5:8) Certainly if anyone does not provide for those who are his own, and especially for those who are members of his household, he has disowned the faith and is worse than a person without faith.

^ (Matt. 6:24) “No one can slave for two masters; for either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will stick to the one and despise the other. You cannot slave for God and for Riches.

Monday, September 14

This is the carpenter, the son of Mary.—[Mark 6:3].

At 30 years of age, Jesus laid aside his carpenter’s tools because he knew that being a minister was the more important occupation. He said that the work of declaring the good news of the Kingdom of God was one reason why God sent him to the earth. ([Matt. 20:28;][Luke 3:23;][4:43]) Jesus made the ministry the primary focus of his life, and he wanted others to join him in that work. (Matt. 9:35-38) We may not be carpenters, but we certainly are ministers of the good news. That occupation is so important that God is involved; we are called “God’s fellow workers.” ([1 Cor. 3:9;][2 Cor. 6:4]) We acknowledge that “the very essence of [Jehovah’s] word is truth.” (Ps. 119:159, 160) That is why we want to be sure that we are “handling the word of the truth aright” in our ministry. ([2 Tim. 2:15]) To that end, we keep honing our skills in using the Bible, the principal tool that we use to teach the truth about Jehovah, Jesus, and the Kingdom. w18.10 11 ¶1-2

^ (Mark 6:3) This is the carpenter, the son of Mary and the brother of James, Joseph, Judas, and Simon, is it not? And his sisters are here with us, are they not?” So they began to stumble because of him.

^ (Matt. 20:28) Just as the Son of man came, not to be ministered to, but to minister and to give his life as a ransom in exchange for many.”

^ (Luke 3:23) When Jesus began his work, he was about 30 years old, being the son, as the opinion was, of Joseph, son of Heʹli,

^ (Luke 4:43) But he said to them: “I must also declare the good news of the Kingdom of God to other cities, because for this I was sent.”

^ (Matt. 9:35-38) And Jesus set out on a tour of all the cities and villages, teaching in their synagogues and preaching the good news of the Kingdom and curing every sort of disease and every sort of infirmity. 36 On seeing the crowds, he felt pity for them, because they were skinned and thrown about like sheep without a shepherd. 37 Then he said to his disciples: “Yes, the harvest is great, but the workers are few. 38 Therefore, beg the Master of the harvest to send out workers into his harvest.”

^ (1 Cor. 3:9) For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

^ (2 Cor. 6:4) but in every way we recommend ourselves as God’s ministers, by the endurance of much, by tribulations, by times of need, by difficulties,

^ (Ps. 119:159, 160) See how I love your orders! O Jehovah, preserve me alive because of your loyal love. 160 The very essence of your word is truth, And all your righteous judgments endure forever.

^ (2 Tim. 2:15) Do your utmost to present yourself approved to God, a workman with nothing to be ashamed of, handling the word of the truth aright.

Tuesday, September 15

Assist those who are weak and . . . keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus.—[Acts 20:35].

When a husband looks to his head, Jesus Christ, as a role model, he helps his wife to cultivate “deep respect” for him. (Eph. 5:22-25,[33]) Her respect, in turn, will move her to be considerate of her husband. When parents show consideration for each other, they set a fine example for their children. Parents, of course, have the primary responsibility to teach their children how to be considerate of others. For example, parents can teach them not to run around in the Kingdom Hall. At a social gathering, parents might tell their children to let older ones go ahead of them when lining up for food. When a child performs a thoughtful deed for us—perhaps opening a door—we should commend the child. Doing so can have a good effect on the young one, impressing on his heart that “there is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.” w18.09 29 ¶5-6

^ (Acts 20:35) I have shown you in all things that by working hard in this way, you must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

^ (Eph. 5:22-25) Let wives be in subjection to their husbands as to the Lord, 23 because a husband is head of his wife just as the Christ is head of the congregation, he being a savior of this body. 24 In fact, as the congregation is in subjection to the Christ, wives should also be to their husbands in everything. 25 Husbands, continue loving your wives, just as the Christ also loved the congregation and gave himself up for it,

^ (Eph. 5:33) Nevertheless, each one of you must love his wife as he does himself; on the other hand, the wife should have deep respect for her husband.

Wednesday, September 16

Your Leader is one, the Christ.—[Matt. 23:10].

As shown by his active direction, our enthroned King, Jesus Christ, is definitely looking to the future. Therefore, let us rejoice over the benefits we derive from adjusting to recent changes. You might find it encouraging during your family worship to discuss how you have benefited from changes in the weekly meetings or in the ministry. If we perceive the spirit behind the instructions we receive from Jehovah’s organization and their beneficial effect on us, we will likely follow that guidance with joy. We certainly appreciate that reducing the amount of literature being printed saves money; using new technologies allows us to further the Kingdom work throughout the earth. So use electronic publications and media more extensively if possible. In this way, we will reflect Christ’s concern to use the organization’s resources wisely. When we earnestly uphold Christ’s direction, we strengthen the faith of others and contribute to unity. w18.10 25-26 ¶17-19

^ (Matt. 23:10) Neither be called leaders, for your Leader is one, the Christ.

Thursday, September 17

Having tender affection for you, we were determined to impart to you, not only the good news of God but also our very selves.—[1 Thess. 2:8].

When we display godlike tenderness, we can be the answer to a distressed person’s prayers. ([2 Cor. 1:3-6]) However, do not expect perfection from your spiritual brothers and sisters. Keep a balanced view of them. To expect faultless behavior is unrealistic and will bring disappointment. (Eccl. 7:21, 22) Remember, Jehovah is realistic in what he requires of his servants. If we imitate his example, we will be prepared to put up with the imperfections of others. ([Eph. 4:2,][32]) Instead of giving them the impression that they are not doing enough, make it a point to commend them for what they are doing. That can encourage them. Sincere commendation can build others up in love and help them to find “cause for rejoicing” in their own sacred service. How much better when we do so rather than express frustrating comparisons with others.—[Gal. 6:4]. w18.09 16 ¶16-17

^ (1 Thess. 2:8) So having tender affection for you, we were determined* to impart to you, not only the good news of God but also our very selves,* because you became so beloved to us.

Lit., “well-pleased.”

Or “souls.”

^ (2 Cor. 1:3-6) Praised be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of tender mercies and the God of all comfort, 4 who comforts* us in all our trials* so that we may be able to comfort others in any sort of trial* with the comfort that we receive from God. 5 For just as the sufferings for the Christ abound in us, so the comfort we receive through the Christ also abounds. 6 Now if we face trials,* it is for your comfort and salvation; and if we are being comforted, it is for your comfort, which acts to help you to endure the same sufferings that we also suffer.

Or “encourages.”

Or “tribulation.”

Or “tribulation.”

Or “tribulation.”

^ (Eccl. 7:21, 22) Also, do not take to heart every word that people say; otherwise, you may hear your servant calling down evil on* you; 22 for you well know in your heart that many times you yourself have called down evil on others.

Lit., “cursing.”

^ (Eph. 4:2) with all humility* and mildness, with patience, putting up with one another in love,

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (Eph. 4:32) But become kind to one another, tenderly compassionate, freely forgiving one another just as God also by Christ freely forgave you.

^ (Gal. 6:4) But let each one examine his own actions, and then he will have cause for rejoicing in regard to himself alone, and not in comparison with the other person.

Friday, September 18

My food is to do the will of him who sent me and to finish his work.—[John 4:34].

To Jesus, spiritual food included acting on God’s direction. In what sense is this like food? Just as our bodies are contented and nourished when we eat a good meal, our hearts are strengthened and our faith is nourished for everlasting life when we participate in doing God’s will. Putting divine instruction into practice is essentially what wisdom means. ([Ps. 107:43]) The reward for wisdom is worth the effort. “Nothing you desire can compare to it. . . . It is a tree of life to those who take hold of it, and those who keep firm hold of it will be called happy.” (Prov. 3:13-18) Jesus said: “If you know these things, happy you are if you do them.” ([John 13:17]) The disciples’ happiness would last if they kept doing what Jesus instructed them to do. They did not embrace his teachings and example simply as an immediate response on that one occasion. It became their way of life. w18.09 4 ¶4-5

^ (John 4:34) Jesus said to them: “My food is to do the will of him who sent me and to finish his work.

^ (Ps. 107:43) Whoever is wise will observe these things And will carefully consider Jehovah’s acts of loyal love.

^ (Prov. 3:13-18) Happy is the man who finds wisdom And the man who acquires discernment; 14 To gain it is better than gaining silver, And having it as profit is better than having gold. 15 It is more precious than corals;* Nothing you desire can compare to it. 16 Long life is in its right hand; Riches and glory are in its left hand. 17 Its ways are pleasant, And all its paths are peaceful. 18 It is a tree of life to those who take hold of it, And those who keep firm hold of it will be called happy.

See Glossary.

^ (John 13:17) If you know these things, happy you are if you do them.

Saturday, September 19

God went on to create the man in his image.—[Gen. 1:27].

God gave the first human couple instructions that should have made them think about the welfare of others, even though they were alone in the garden of Eden. Jehovah blessed Adam and Eve and encouraged them to multiply, fill the earth, and subdue it. ([Gen. 1:28]) Just as the Creator was keenly interested in the welfare of his creation, the first human parents should have been interested in the happiness of their unborn children. Paradise was to be extended earth wide for the benefit of Adam’s offspring. That huge project would require the cooperation of his ever-growing family. For perfect men and women, working to extend Paradise would have meant cooperating to the full with Jehovah to achieve his purposes, thereby entering into his rest. ([Heb. 4:11]) Imagine how fulfilling and rewarding that project would have been! Giving of themselves for the welfare of others would have brought them great blessings and immense satisfaction. w18.08 18 ¶2; 19-20 ¶8-9

^ (Gen. 1:27) And God went on to create the man in his image, in God’s image he created him; male and female he created them.

^ (Gen. 1:28) Further, God blessed them, and God said to them: “Be fruitful and become many, fill the earth and subdue it, and have in subjection the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and every living creature that is moving on the earth.”

^ (Heb. 4:11) Let us therefore do our utmost to enter into that rest, so that no one may fall into the same pattern of disobedience.

Sunday, September 20

He slandered your servant to my lord the king.—[2 Sam. 19:27].

What if you are a victim of a slanderous accusation? Jesus and John the Baptizer experienced such a challenge. (Matt. 11:18, 19) How did Jesus deal with false information? He did not spend all his time and energy defending himself. Instead he encouraged people to look at the facts—what he did and what he taught. As Jesus said, “wisdom is vindicated by its works.” ([Matt. 11:19]; ftn.) There is a valuable lesson here that we do well to learn. At times, people may say unfair or critical things about us. We may long for justice and wish that we could do something to undo the damage to our reputation. Yet, there is something we can do. If someone spreads a lie about us, we can live in such a way that no one will believe that lie. Indeed, as Jesus’ example shows, our personal record of upright Christian conduct can wipe out half-truths and false accusations. w18.08 6 ¶11-13

^ (2 Sam. 19:27) But he slandered your servant to my lord the king. However, my lord the king is like an angel of the true God, so do whatever seems good to you.

^ (Matt. 11:18, 19) Likewise, John came neither eating nor drinking, but people say, ‘He has a demon.’ 19 The Son of man did come eating and drinking, but people say, ‘Look! A man who is a glutton and is given to drinking wine, a friend of tax collectors and sinners.’ All the same, wisdom is proved righteous* by its works.”*

Or “is vindicated.”

Or “by its results.”

^ (Matt. 11:19) The Son of man did come eating and drinking, but people say, ‘Look! A man who is a glutton and is given to drinking wine, a friend of tax collectors and sinners.’ All the same, wisdom is proved righteous* by its works.”*

Or “is vindicated.”

Or “by its results.”

Monday, September 21

Jehovah your God you should fear, him you should serve, to him you should cling.—[Deut. 10:20].

The Bible accounts about the disobedience of Cain, Solomon, and the Israelites at Mount Sinai have a noteworthy element in common. These individuals had opportunity to “repent . . . and turn around.” ([Acts 3:19]) Clearly, Jehovah is not quick to give up on those who take a false step. In Aaron’s case, Jehovah extended forgiveness. Today, warnings from Jehovah may come in the form of a Bible account, Bible-based publications, or kind advice from a fellow Christian. When we heed the warnings, we are assured of Jehovah’s mercy. Jehovah’s undeserved kindness has a purpose. ([2 Cor. 6:1]) It gives us an opportunity “to reject ungodliness and worldly desires.” (Titus 2:11-14) As long as we live “amid this present system of things,” we will face situations that will put our exclusive devotion to Jehovah to the test. May we always be ready to take a firm stand on his side! w18.07 21 ¶20-21

^ (Deut. 10:20) “Jehovah your God you should fear, him you should serve, to him you should cling, and by his name you should swear.

^ (Acts 3:19) “Repent, therefore, and turn around so as to get your sins blotted out, so that seasons of refreshing may come from Jehovah himself

^ (2 Cor. 6:1) Working together with him, we also urge you not to accept the undeserved kindness of God and miss its purpose.

^ (Titus 2:11-14) For the undeserved kindness of God has been manifested, bringing salvation to all sorts of people. 12 It trains us to reject ungodliness and worldly desires and to live with soundness of mind and righteousness and godly devotion amid this present system of things,* 13 while we wait for the happy hope and glorious manifestation of the great God and of our Savior, Jesus Christ, 14 who gave himself for us to set us free* from every sort of lawlessness and to cleanse for himself a people who are his own special possession, zealous for fine works.

Or “this present age.” See Glossary.

Lit., “to ransom us; to redeem us.”

Tuesday, September 22

Jehovah knows those who belong to him.—[2 Tim. 2:19].

How can we strengthen our resolve to seek Jehovah’s recognition and not that of the world? To do so, we need to remember two important facts. First, Jehovah always gives recognition to those who serve him faithfully. ([Heb. 6:10;][11:6]) He deeply appreciates every one of his servants, and he views it as “unrighteous” to ignore those who are faithful to him. He is “aware of the way of the righteous” and knows how to rescue them out of trial. ([Ps. 1:6;][2 Pet. 2:9]) Second, Jehovah may give us recognition in ways we may never expect. Those who do good deeds purely to be seen by men are told that they will have no reward at all from Jehovah. Why? Their reward has already been paid in full. ([Matt. 6:1-5]) However, Jesus said that his Father “looks on in secret” at those who do not receive due credit for the good they do to others. He notices those acts and repays each person accordingly. w18.07 9 ¶8, 10

^ (2 Tim. 2:19) Despite that, the solid foundation of God remains standing, having this seal, “Jehovah* knows those who belong to him,” and, “Let everyone calling on the name of Jehovah* renounce unrighteousness.”

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (Heb. 11:6) Moreover, without faith it is impossible to please God well, for whoever approaches God must believe that he is* and that he becomes the rewarder of those earnestly seeking him.

Or “exists.”

^ (Ps. 1:6) For Jehovah is aware of the way of the righteous, But the way of the wicked will perish.

^ (2 Pet. 2:9) So, then, Jehovah* knows how to rescue people of godly devotion out of trial, but to reserve unrighteous people to be destroyed* on the day of judgment,

See App. A5.

Lit., “cut off.”

^ (Matt. 6:1-5) “Take care not to practice your righteousness in front of men to be noticed by them; otherwise you will have no reward with your Father who is in the heavens. 2 So when you make gifts of mercy, do not blow a trumpet ahead of you, as the hypocrites do in the synagogues and in the streets, so that they may be glorified by men. Truly I say to you, they have their reward in full. 3 But you, when making gifts of mercy, do not let your left hand know what your right hand is doing, 4 so that your gifts of mercy may be in secret. Then your Father who looks on in secret will repay you. 5 “Also, when you pray, do not act like the hypocrites, for they like to pray standing in the synagogues and on the corners of the main streets to be seen by men. Truly I say to you, they have their reward in full.

Wednesday, September 23

Stop calling defiled the things God has cleansed.—[Acts 10:15].

Peter was perplexed as to what the voice was trying to tell him. Just then, the messengers from Cornelius arrived. After receiving direction from the holy spirit, Peter pressed forward and accompanied the messengers to the home of Cornelius. If Peter had judged matters solely on outward appearance, he would never have entered the home of Cornelius. Jews simply did not enter the homes of Gentiles. Why did Peter move forward despite deep-seated prejudices? Peter was profoundly affected by the vision he had seen and by the reassurance he received from the holy spirit. After he listened to what Cornelius related, Peter, no doubt moved by the account, declared under inspiration: “Now I truly understand that God is not partial, but in every nation the man who fears him and does what is right is acceptable to him.” (Acts 10:34, 35) What a thrilling new understanding for Peter—one with far-reaching implications! w18.08 9 ¶3-4

^ (Acts 10:15) And the voice spoke again to him, the second time: “Stop calling defiled the things God has cleansed.”

^ (Acts 10:34, 35) At this Peter began to speak, and he said: “Now I truly understand that God is not partial, 35 but in every nation the man who fears him and does what is right is acceptable to him.

Thursday, September 24

Hate what is bad.—[Amos 5:15].

We may well stay far away from practices that God hates. Yet, there are other activities or aspects of life about which the Scriptures provide no specific command. In such areas, how can we determine what is acceptable and pleasing to God? That is where our Bible-trained conscience comes into play. Jehovah has lovingly given us principles that work in conjunction with our Bible-trained conscience. He himself says: “I, Jehovah, am your God, the One teaching you to benefit yourself, the One guiding you in the way you should walk.” (Isa. 48:17, 18) By using our mind and heart to reason on Bible principles, we correct, direct, and mold our conscience. That, in turn, helps us to make wise decisions. A principle is a fundamental truth or doctrine that is used as a basis of reasoning or action. To understand a principle includes understanding the thinking of the Lawgiver and the reasons why he gave certain laws. w18.06 17 ¶5; 18 ¶8-10

^ (Amos 5:15) Hate what is bad, and love what is good, Let justice prevail in the city gate. It may be that Jehovah the God of armies Will show favor to the remaining ones of Joseph.’

^ (Isa. 48:17, 18) This is what Jehovah says, your Repurchaser, the Holy One of Israel: “I, Jehovah, am your God, The One teaching you to benefit yourself,* The One guiding you in the way you should walk. 18 If only you would pay attention to my commandments! Then your peace would become just like a river And your righteousness like the waves of the sea.

Or “for your own good.”

Friday, September 25

Is it lawful to pay head tax to Caesar or not?—[Matt. 22:17].

The party followers of Herod who raised this issue hoped that if Jesus denounced the tax, he might be accused of sedition. If Jesus said that taxation was a necessary burden, he could lose the support of his followers. Jesus was careful to remain neutral on the taxation issue. Of course, Jesus knew that corruption was common among tax collectors. But Jesus did not want to get sidetracked, diverted from the much more important issue. That was God’s Kingdom, which would be the real solution. He thereby set the example for all his followers. They should avoid becoming involved in political issues, no matter how right or just a certain cause might seem. Christians seek the Kingdom of God and his righteousness. They do that instead of forming strong opinions about, or speaking out against, certain unjust practices. ([Matt. 6:33]) Many of Jehovah’s Witnesses have succeeded in moving away from strong political views that they once held. w18.06 6 ¶9-11

^ (Matt. 22:17) Tell us, then, what do you think? Is it lawful* to pay head tax to Caesar or not?”

Or “right.”

^ (Matt. 6:33) “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

Saturday, September 26

The sons of the true God began to notice that the daughters of men were beautiful.—[Gen. 6:2].

Perhaps Satan tempted the disloyal angels not only with the opportunity for immoral sex but also with the promise of seizing power over mankind. His purpose may have been to disrupt the arrival of the promised ‘offspring of the woman.’ ([Gen. 3:15]) In any case, Jehovah ended all such plots by bringing the Flood—a move that thwarted the efforts of Satan and the rebellious angels at that time. So, never underestimate the lure of immorality or the danger of egotism. For aeons, the angels who joined Satan served in the very presence of God. Yet, many allowed bad desires to take root and grow. Similarly, we may have served for decades in the earthly part of God’s organization. Yet, even in this spiritually clean environment, unclean desires can take root. ([1 Cor. 10:12]) How important it is that we constantly search our heart, reject immoral thoughts, and suppress unhealthy pride!—[Gal. 5:26;][Col. 3:5]. w18.05 25 ¶11-12

^ (Gen. 6:2) the sons of the true God* began to notice that the daughters of men were beautiful. So they began taking as wives all whom they chose.

A Hebrew idiom that refers to angelic sons of God.

^ (Gen. 3:15) And I will put enmity* between you and the woman and between your offspring* and her offspring.* He will crush* your head, and you will strike* him in the heel.”

Or “hostility.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “bruise; strike.”

Or “bruise; crush.”

^ (1 Cor. 10:12) So let the one who thinks he is standing beware that he does not fall.

^ (Gal. 5:26) Let us not become egotistical, stirring up competition with one another, envying one another.

^ (Col. 3:5) Deaden, therefore, your body members that are on the earth as respects sexual immorality,* uncleanness, uncontrolled sexual passion, hurtful desire, and greediness, which is idolatry.

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

Sunday, September 27

I have great grief and unceasing pain in my heart.—[Rom. 9:2].

Paul felt discouraged by the Jews’ negative reaction to the Kingdom message. Even so, he did not give up on them. Note what he further said in his letter to the Christians in Rome about his feelings toward those Jews: “The goodwill of my heart and my supplication to God for them are indeed for their salvation. For I bear them witness that they have a zeal for God, but not according to accurate knowledge.” ([Rom. 10:1, 2]) Paul stated why he kept on preaching to the Jews. He was moved by “the goodwill of [his] heart.” It was his heart’s desire that some Jews would find salvation. (Rom. 11:13, 14) He implored God in prayer to help individual Jews to accept the Kingdom message. Paul added: “They have a zeal for God.” He saw a potential for good in people. Zeal, if properly directed, can transform sincere individuals into zealous disciples of Christ, as Paul well knew. w18.05 13 ¶4; 15-16 ¶13-14

^ (Rom. 9:2) that I have great grief and unceasing pain in my heart.

^ (Rom. 10:1, 2) Brothers, the goodwill of my heart and my supplication to God for them are indeed for their salvation. 2 For I bear them witness that they have a zeal for God, but not according to accurate knowledge.

^ (Rom. 11:13, 14) Now I speak to you who are people of the nations. Seeing that I am an apostle to the nations, I glorify my ministry 14 to see if I may in some way incite my own people to jealousy and save some from among them.

Monday, September 28

[Speak] what is good for building up as the need may be, to impart what is beneficial to the hearers.—[Eph. 4:29].

Each of us should be alert to observe “the need” that others have. Paul counseled Hebrew Christians: “Strengthen the hands that hang down and the feeble knees, and keep making straight paths for your feet, so that what is lame may not be put out of joint but, rather, may be healed.” (Heb. 12:12, 13) All of us, including young ones, can build one another up by words of encouragement. Paul gave this advice: “If, then, there is any encouragement in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any spiritual fellowship, if any tender affection and compassion, make my joy full by being of the same mind and having the same love, being completely united, having the one thought in mind. Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility consider others superior to you, as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.”—[Phil. 2:1-4]. w18.04 22 ¶10; 23 ¶12

^ (Eph. 4:29) Let a rotten word not come out of your mouth, but only what is good for building up as the need may be, to impart what is beneficial to the hearers.

^ (Heb. 12:12, 13) Therefore, strengthen the hands that hang down and the feeble knees, 13 and keep making straight paths for your feet, so that what is lame may not be put out of joint but, rather, may be healed.

^ (Phil. 2:1-4) If, then, there is any encouragement in Christ, if any consolation of love, if any spiritual fellowship,* if any tender affection and compassion, 2 make my joy full by being of the same mind and having the same love, being completely united,* having the one thought in mind. 3 Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you, 4 as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

Lit., “any sharing of spirit.”

Or “being joined together in soul.”

Or “lowliness of mind.”

Tuesday, September 29

Be as free people, using your freedom . . . as slaves of God.—[1 Pet. 2:16].

The real purpose for which Jehovah, through Jesus, has freed us from the law of sin and of death is for us to live a life of dedication “as slaves of God.” The best way to protect ourselves from misusing our freedom and thus becoming enslaved again by worldly ambitions and desires is to be fully absorbed in spiritual pursuits. ([Gal. 5:16]) Consider, for example, the patriarch Noah and his family. They lived in a violent and immoral world. Yet, they kept free from being entangled in the desires and pursuits of the people around them. How did they manage to do that? They chose to keep busy in all that Jehovah had assigned them to do—build the ark, store up food for themselves and the animals, and sound the warning to others. “Noah did according to all that God had commanded him. He did just so.” ([Gen. 6:22]) The result? Noah and his family survived the end of that world.—[Heb. 11:7]. w18.04 10 ¶8; 11 ¶11-12

^ (1 Pet. 2:16) Be as free people, using your freedom, not as a cover* for doing wrong, but as slaves of God.

Or “an excuse.”

^ (Gal. 5:16) But I say, Keep walking by spirit and you will carry out no fleshly desire at all.

^ (Gen. 6:22) And Noah did according to all that God had commanded him. He did just so.

^ (Heb. 11:7) By faith Noah, after receiving divine warning of things not yet seen, showed godly fear and constructed an ark for the saving of his household; and through this faith he condemned the world, and he became an heir of the righteousness that results from faith.

Wednesday, September 30

I will give you all this authority and their glory, because it has been handed over to me, and I give it to whomever I wish.—[Luke 4:6].

Satan and the demons use not only governments but also false religion and the commercial system to mislead “the entire inhabited earth.” ([Rev. 12:9]) Through false religion, Satan promotes lies about Jehovah. In addition, the Devil seems determined to make as many people as possible forget God’s name. (Jer. 23:26, 27) As a result, sincere individuals who think that they are worshipping God are deceived into worshipping demons. (1 Cor. 10:20; 2 Cor. 11:13-15) Satan also promotes lies through the commercial system. For example, this system often teaches people that the best way to be happy is to pursue money and gather many possessions. ([Prov. 18:11]) Those who believe this lie spend their lives serving “Riches” rather than God. ([Matt. 6:24]) Eventually, their love of material things can choke any love they had for God.—[Matt. 13:22;] 1 John 2:15, 16. w18.05 23 ¶6-7

^ (Luke 4:6) Then the Devil said to him: “I will give you all this authority and their glory, because it has been handed over to me, and I give it to whomever I wish.

^ (Rev. 12:9) So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.

^ (Jer. 23:26, 27) How long will this continue in the heart of the prophets, to prophesy lies? They are prophets of the deceit of their own heart. 27 They intend to make my people forget my name by the dreams they relate to one another, just as their fathers forgot my name because of Baʹal.

^ (1 Cor. 10:20) No; but I say that what the nations sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons and not to God; and I do not want you to become sharers with the demons.

^ (2 Cor. 11:13-15) For such men are false apostles, deceitful workers, disguising themselves as apostles of Christ. 14 And no wonder, for Satan himself keeps disguising himself as an angel of light. 15 It is therefore nothing extraordinary if his ministers also keep disguising themselves as ministers of righteousness. But their end will be according to their works.

^ (Prov. 18:11) The wealth of the rich is his fortified city; It is like a protective wall in his imagination.

^ (Matt. 6:24) “No one can slave for two masters; for either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will stick to the one and despise the other. You cannot slave for God and for Riches.

^ (Matt. 13:22) As for the one sown among the thorns, this is the one hearing the word, but the anxiety of this system of things and the deceptive power of riches* choke the word, and it* becomes unfruitful.

Or “the seductiveness (deceptive pleasure) of being wealthy.”

Or possibly, “he,” that is, “the one hearing the word.”

^ (1 John 2:15, 16) Do not love either the world or the things in the world. If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him; 16 because everything in the world—the desire of the flesh and the desire of the eyes and the showy display of one’s means of life*—does not originate with the Father, but originates with the world.

Or “the bragging about one’s possessions.”

October

Thursday, October 1

Weep with those who weep.—[Rom. 12:15].

We cannot read hearts as Jehovah and Jesus do. Even so, we can try to understand the emotions and needs of others. ([2 Cor. 11:29]) Unlike the selfish world around us, we strive to “look out not only for [our] own interests, but also for the interests of others.” ([Phil. 2:4]) Congregation elders in particular need to show fellow feeling. They know that they are accountable for the sheep entrusted to their care. ([Heb. 13:17]) To help their fellow believers, elders need to be understanding. How can elders demonstrate fellow feeling? A sympathetic elder spends time with his Christian brothers and sisters. He asks questions and then listens attentively and patiently. That is especially important if one of these dear sheep wants to pour out his heart but struggles to find the right words. ([Prov. 20:5]) By willingly giving of his time, an elder forms strong bonds of trust, friendship, and love with his brothers.—[Acts 20:37]. w19.03 17 ¶14-17

^ (Rom. 12:15) Rejoice with those who rejoice; weep with those who weep.

^ (2 Cor. 11:29) Who is weak, and I am not weak? Who is stumbled, and I am not incensed?

^ (Phil. 2:4) as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

^ (Heb. 13:17) Be obedient to those who are taking the lead among you and be submissive, for they are keeping watch over you* as those who will render an account, so that they may do this with joy and not with sighing, for this would be damaging to you.

Or “your souls.”

^ (Prov. 20:5) The thoughts* of a man’s heart are like deep waters, But the discerning man draws them out.

Or “intentions.” Lit., “counsel.”

^ (Acts 20:37) Indeed, quite a bit of weeping broke out among them all, and they embraced Paul and affectionately kissed him,

Friday, October 2

Like apples of gold in silver carvings is a word spoken at the right time.—[Prov. 25:11].

Appreciation is like a good meal—it is more enjoyable when shared. When we feel appreciated, we are happy. When we express our appreciation, we make others happy. The person who receives our gratitude knows that his efforts to help us, or to give us something we need, were worthwhile. As a result, the bonds of friendship between us and that person are strengthened. Our expressions of gratitude are valuable, as mentioned in today’s text. Imagine how beautiful an apple made of gold and set in silver would look! And just think how valuable it would be! How would you feel if you received such a gift? Well, the words of gratitude you express to others can be just as valuable. And consider this fact: An apple made of gold could last indefinitely. Likewise, your expressions of appreciation may be remembered and treasured by the recipient for the rest of his life. w19.02 15 ¶5-6

^ (Prov. 25:11) Like apples of gold in silver carvings* Is a word spoken at the right time.

Or “settings.”

Saturday, October 3

The man has become like one of us in knowing good and bad.—[Gen. 3:22].

When Adam and Eve ate the fruit from the tree of the knowledge of good and bad, they sent a clear message: They did not trust Jehovah and his standards. They chose to set their own standards of good and bad. But look at what they lost. They lost their friendship with Jehovah. They also lost the opportunity to live forever, and they passed sin and death on to their children. ([Rom. 5:12]) Compare the way Adam and Eve behaved with the way that the Ethiopian eunuch responded when Philip preached to him. The eunuch appreciated so much what Jehovah and Jesus had done for him that he immediately got baptized. ([Acts 8:34-38]) When we dedicate ourselves to God and, like that eunuch, get baptized, we send a clear message. We show that we appreciate what Jehovah and Jesus have done for us. We also show that we trust Jehovah and recognize that he is the one who should set the standard of good and bad. w19.03 2 ¶1-2

^ (Gen. 3:22) Jehovah God then said: “Here the man has become like one of us in knowing good and bad. Now in order that he may not put his hand out and take fruit also from the tree of life and eat and live forever,*—”

Or “to time indefinite.”

^ (Rom. 5:12) That is why, just as through one man sin entered into the world and death through sin, and so death spread to all men because they had all sinned—.

^ (Acts 8:34-38) The eunuch then said to Philip: “I beg you, about whom does the prophet say this? About himself or about some other man?” 35 Philip began to speak, and starting with this scripture, he declared to him the good news about Jesus. 36 Now as they were going along the road, they came to a body of water, and the eunuch said: “Look! Here is water; what prevents me from getting baptized?” 37 —— 38 With that he commanded the chariot to halt, and both Philip and the eunuch went down into the water, and he baptized him.

Sunday, October 4

I will not renounce my integrity!—[Job 27:5].

When applied to us as servants of God, integrity means wholehearted love for and unbreakable devotion to Jehovah as a Person, so that his will comes first in all our decisions. One basic meaning of the Bible word for “integrity” is this: complete, sound, or whole. For example, the animals sacrificed to Jehovah had to be sound. (Lev. 22:21, 22) God’s people were not allowed to offer up an animal that was missing a leg, an ear, or an eye; nor could they offer one full of disease. It was important to Jehovah that the animal be complete, sound, or whole. ([Mal. 1:6-9]) We can understand why Jehovah cares about soundness or completeness. When we purchase something, whether a piece of fruit, a book, or a tool, we do not want one that has gaping holes or parts missing. We want one that is complete, sound, or whole. Jehovah feels similarly when it comes to our love for him, our loyalty. It must be complete, sound, or whole. w19.02 3 ¶3

^ (Job 27:5) It is unthinkable for me to declare you men righteous! Until I die, I will not renounce* my integrity!

Or “I will not take away from myself; I will maintain.”

^ (Lev. 22:21, 22) “‘If a man presents a communion sacrifice to Jehovah to pay a vow or as a voluntary offering, it should be a sound animal from the herd or the flock, in order to gain approval. No defect at all should be in it. 22 No offering should be blind, have a fracture, a cut, a wart, scabbiness, or ringworm; you must not present any of these to Jehovah or make such an offering on the altar for Jehovah.

^ (Mal. 1:6-9) “‘A son honors a father, and a servant his master. So if I am a father, where is the honor due me? And if I am a master,* where is the fear* due me?’ Jehovah of armies says to you priests who are despising my name. “‘But you say: “How have we despised your name?”’ 7 “‘By presenting polluted food* on my altar.’ “‘And you say: “How have we polluted you?”’ “‘By saying: “The table of Jehovah is something to be despised.” 8 And when you present a blind animal as a sacrifice, you say: “It is nothing bad.” And when you present a lame animal or a sick one: “It is nothing bad.”’” “Try presenting them, please, to your governor. Will he be pleased with you or receive you with favor?” says Jehovah of armies. 9 “And now, please, appeal to* God, that he may show us favor. With such offerings from your own hand, will he receive any of you with favor?” says Jehovah of armies.

Or “grand master.”

Or “respect.”

Lit., “bread.”

Or “soften the face of.”

Monday, October 5

How I do love your law! I ponder over it all day long.—[Ps. 119:97].

To safeguard our heart, we must not only close it to wrong influences but also open it to positive influences. In ancient walled cities, a gatekeeper closed the gates of the city to stop an enemy invasion, but at other times he opened the gates to allow food and other supplies to be brought in. If the gates were never open, the inhabitants of the city would starve. Similarly, we need to open our heart regularly to the influence of God’s thinking. The Bible contains Jehovah’s thinking, so each time we read it, we allow Jehovah’s thoughts to affect the way we think, feel, and act. How can we get the most from our Bible reading? Prayer is vital to help us “see clearly the wonderful things” in his Word. ([Ps. 119:18]) We also need to meditate on what we read. When we pray, read, and meditate, God’s Word reaches “deep within [our] heart,” and we come to love Jehovah’s thinking.—Prov. 4:20-22. w19.01 18 ¶14-15

^ (Ps. 119:97) How I do love your law! I ponder over* it all day long.

Or “study.”

^ (Ps. 119:18) Open my eyes so that I may see clearly The wonderful things from your law.

^ (Prov. 4:20-22) My son, pay attention to my words; Listen carefully* to my sayings. 21 Do not lose sight of them; Keep them deep within your heart, 22 For they are life to those who find them And health to their whole body.*

Lit., “Incline your ear.”

Lit., “to all their flesh.”

Tuesday, October 6

Let us always offer to God a sacrifice of praise.—[Heb. 13:15].

Jehovah knows that we have different abilities and circumstances, and he deeply appreciates the sacrifices we are able to offer to him. Think of the type of sacrifices that he accepted from the Israelites. Some Israelites were able to offer a lamb or a goat. But a poor Israelite might offer “two turtledoves or two young pigeons.” And if an Israelite could not afford two birds, Jehovah accepted “a tenth of an ephah of fine flour.” ([Lev. 5:7,][11]) Flour was less expensive, but Jehovah still appreciated that sacrifice, as long as it was “fine flour.” Our kind God feels the same way today. When we give comments, he does not demand that all of us be as eloquent as Apollos or as persuasive as Paul. ([Acts 18:24;][26:28]) All Jehovah wants is that we give the best comments we can—within our limits. Remember the widow who offered the two small coins. She was precious to Jehovah because she gave the best she could.—[Luke 21:1-4]. w19.01 8-9 ¶3-5

^ (Heb. 13:15) Through him let us always offer to God a sacrifice of praise, that is, the fruit of our lips that make public declaration to his name.

^ (Lev. 5:7) “‘If, though, he cannot afford a sheep, he must bring to Jehovah two turtledoves or two young pigeons as his guilt offering for the sin, one for a sin offering and one for a burnt offering.

^ (Lev. 5:11) “‘Now if he cannot afford two turtledoves or two young pigeons, he must bring as his offering for his sin a tenth of an eʹphah* of fine flour for a sin offering. He should not add oil to it or place frankincense on it, for it is a sin offering.

A tenth of an ephah equaled 2.2 L (2 dry qt). See App. B14.

^ (Acts 18:24) Now a Jew named A·polʹlos, a native of Alexandria, arrived in Ephʹe·sus; he was an eloquent man who was well-versed in the Scriptures.

^ (Acts 26:28) But A·gripʹpa said to Paul: “In a short time you would persuade me to become a Christian.”

^ (Luke 21:1-4) Now as he looked up, he saw the rich dropping their gifts into the treasury chests. 2 Then he saw a needy widow drop in two small coins of very little value, 3 and he said: “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than they all did. 4 For all of these put in gifts* out of their surplus, but she, out of her want,* put in all the means of living she had.”

Or “contributed to the gifts.”

Or “poverty.”

Wednesday, October 7

You will be hated by all people on account of my name.—[Matt. 10:22].

As Christ’s followers, we expect to be hated. Jesus foretold that his disciples would be severely persecuted during the last days. ([Matt. 24:9;][John 15:20]) Isaiah’s prophecy forewarns us that our enemies will do more than hate us; they will use various weapons against us. Those weapons have included subtle deception, blatant lies, and brutal persecution. ([Matt. 5:11]) Jehovah will not stop our enemies from using these weapons to wage war against us. ([Eph. 6:12;][Rev. 12:17]) But we do not need to be afraid. Jehovah said that “no weapon” used against us would “have any success.” ([Isa. 54:17]) Just as a wall protects us from the force of a destructive rainstorm, so Jehovah protects us against “the blast of the tyrants.” ([Isa. 25:4, 5]) Our enemies will never succeed in causing us any lasting harm. ([Isa. 65:17]) All enemies of God’s people “will be brought to nothing and perish.”—Isa. 41:11, 12. w19.01 6-7 ¶13-16

^ (Matt. 10:22) And you will be hated by all people on account of my name, but the one who has endured* to the end will be saved.

Or “who endures.”

^ (Matt. 24:9) “Then people will hand you over to tribulation and will kill you, and you will be hated by all the nations on account of my name.

^ (John 15:20) Keep in mind the word I said to you: A slave is not greater than his master. If they have persecuted me, they will also persecute you; if they have observed my word, they will also observe yours.

^ (Matt. 5:11) “Happy are you when people reproach* you and persecute you and lyingly say every sort of wicked thing against you for my sake.

Or “insult.”

^ (Eph. 6:12) because we have a struggle,* not against blood and flesh, but against the governments, against the authorities, against the world rulers of this darkness, against the wicked spirit forces in the heavenly places.

Lit., “wrestling.”

^ (Rev. 12:17) So the dragon became enraged at the woman and went off to wage war with the remaining ones of her offspring,* who observe the commandments of God and have the work of bearing witness concerning Jesus.

Lit., “seed.”

^ (Isa. 54:17) No weapon formed against you will have any success, And you will condemn any tongue that rises up against you in the judgment. This is the heritage* of the servants of Jehovah, And their righteousness is from me,” declares Jehovah.

Or “inheritance.”

^ (Isa. 25:4, 5) For you have become a stronghold to the lowly, A stronghold to the poor in his distress, A refuge from the rainstorm, And a shade from the heat. When the blast of the tyrants is like a rainstorm against a wall,  5 As the heat in a parched land, You subdue the uproar of strangers. Like heat is subdued by the shadow of a cloud, So the song of the tyrants is silenced.

^ (Isa. 65:17) For look! I am creating new heavens and a new earth; And the former things will not be called to mind,* Nor will they come up into the heart.

Or “be remembered.”

^ (Isa. 41:11, 12) Look! All those getting enraged against you will be put to shame and humiliated. Those who fight with you will be brought to nothing and perish. 12 You will search for men who struggle with you, but you will not find them; The men at war with you will become as something nonexistent, as nothing at all.

Thursday, October 8

Where the spirit of Jehovah is, there is freedom.—[2 Cor. 3:17].

Young ones, Jehovah loves freedom, and he put that love in your heart. At the same time, however, he wants you to use your freedom responsibly, which is a protection for you. Perhaps you know others who view pornography or who engage in sexual immorality, high-risk sports, or drug and alcohol abuse. To be sure, they may enjoy a few moments of excitement or pleasure. But often that comes at great cost, perhaps in the form of disease, addiction, or even death. ([Gal. 6:7, 8]) Yes, their “freedom” is a cruel self-deception. ([Titus 3:3]) By comparison, how many people do you know who became sick because they adhered to Bible standards? Clearly, obedience to Jehovah is both healthful and liberating. ([Ps. 19:7-11]) What is more, when you use your freedom wisely—that is, within the bounds of God’s perfect laws and principles—you show God, as well as your parents, that you can be trusted with more freedom.—[Rom. 8:21]. w18.12 22-23 ¶16-17

^ (2 Cor. 3:17) Now Jehovah* is the Spirit, and where the spirit of Jehovah* is, there is freedom.

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

^ (Gal. 6:7, 8) Do not be misled: God is not one to be mocked. For whatever a person is sowing, this he will also reap; 8 because the one sowing with a view to his flesh will reap corruption from his flesh, but the one sowing with a view to the spirit will reap everlasting life from the spirit.

^ (Titus 3:3) For we too were once senseless, disobedient, led astray, being slaves to various desires and pleasures, carrying on in badness and envy, detestable, hating one another.

^ (Ps. 19:7-11) The law of Jehovah is perfect, restoring strength.* The reminder of Jehovah is trustworthy, making the inexperienced one wise.  8 The orders from Jehovah are righteous, causing the heart to rejoice; The commandment of Jehovah is clean, making the eyes shine.  9 The fear of Jehovah is pure, lasting forever. The judgments of Jehovah are true, altogether righteous. 10 They are more desirable than gold, Than much fine* gold, And sweeter than honey, the honey that drips from the combs. 11 By them your servant has been warned; In keeping them, there is a large reward.

Or “restoring (bringing back) the soul.”

Or “refined.”

^ (Rom. 8:21) that* the creation itself will also be set free from enslavement to corruption and have the glorious freedom of the children of God.

Or “because.”

Friday, October 9

A man will leave his father and his mother and he will stick to his wife, and they will become one flesh.—[Gen. 2:24].

Adam’s sin brought changes. One was death, which would affect marriage. We can see that from what the apostle Paul wrote when explaining that Christians are not under the Mosaic Law. He revealed that death ends a marriage and that the surviving mate can thereafter remarry. ([Rom. 7:1-3]) The Law that God gave to the nation of Israel provided details about marriage. It allowed for polygamy, a practice that existed even before God gave Israel the Law. However, polygamy was regulated, prohibiting abuses. For example, if an Israelite married a slave and later took a second wife, he could not diminish his first wife’s food, clothing, and marital due. God required that he protect and care for her. ([Ex. 21:9, 10]) We are not under the Law, but we can still see from it Jehovah’s interest in marriage. Does that not help you to esteem marriage? w18.12 10 ¶3; 11 ¶5-6

^ (Gen. 2:24) That is why a man will leave his father and his mother and he will stick to* his wife, and they will become one flesh.

Or “remain with.”

^ (Rom. 7:1-3) Can it be that you do not know, brothers, (for I am speaking to those who know law) that the Law is master over a man as long as he lives? 2 For instance, a married woman* is bound by law to her husband while he is alive; but if her husband dies, she is released from the law of her husband. 3 So, then, while her husband is living, she would be called an adulteress if she became another man’s. But if her husband dies, she is free from his law, so that she is not an adulteress if she becomes another man’s.

Or “a woman subject to a husband.”

^ (Ex. 21:9, 10) If he selects her for his son, he is to grant her the rights of a daughter. 10 If he takes another wife for himself, the sustenance, the clothing, and the marriage due of the first wife are not to be diminished.

Saturday, October 10

You will not believe even if it is told to you.—[Hab. 1:5].

After leaving his worries and concerns in Jehovah’s hands, Habakkuk may have wondered how Jehovah would react. As an empathetic and understanding Father, Jehovah did not rebuke him for his sincere complaint. God knew that it was a desperate cry of pain and sorrow. In words really aimed at the wayward Jews, Jehovah informed Habakkuk of what would happen in the near future. It could well be that Habakkuk was the first to whom Jehovah revealed that the end of that violent era was very near. Jehovah showed Habakkuk that He was ready to act. The punishment of that violent and wicked generation was imminent. By the expression “in your days,” Jehovah indicated that this judgment would definitely occur during the lifetime of the prophet or that of his contemporaries. Jehovah’s reply was not at all what Habakkuk expected. Was this the answer to his impatient cry? What Jehovah told him surely meant that suffering would increase for all of Judah. w18.11 15 ¶7-8

^ (Hab. 1:5) “Look among the nations and pay attention! Stare in amazement and be astounded; For something will happen in your days That you will not believe even if it is told to you.

Sunday, October 11

[God’s] will is that all sorts of people should be saved and come to an accurate knowledge of truth.—[1 Tim. 2:4].

What is your view of the many sorts of people who have yet to learn the truth? Although the apostle Paul searched in synagogues for those who already knew something about God, he certainly did not restrict his efforts to Jewish people. On Paul’s first missionary journey, for instance, the Lycaonian people mistook him and Barnabas for superheroes—as incarnations of their false gods Zeus and Hermes. Were Paul and Barnabas tempted to ride the wave of popularity? Would that seem to be a refreshing break from all the persecution they had experienced in the last two cities they visited? Did they imagine that the publicity could help to advance the good news? Not at all! They immediately protested by ripping their garments and leaping into the crowd, crying out: “Why are you doing these things? We too are humans having the same infirmities as you have.”—[Acts 14:8-15]. w18.09 4-5 ¶8-9

^ (1 Tim. 2:4) whose will is that all sorts of people should be saved and come to an accurate knowledge of truth.

^ (Acts 14:8-15) Now in Lysʹtra there was a man sitting down whose feet were crippled. He was lame from birth and had never walked. 9 This man was listening to Paul as he was speaking. Paul, looking intently at him and seeing that he had faith to be made well,* 10 said with a loud voice: “Stand up on your feet.” So the man leaped up and began walking. 11 When the crowds saw what Paul had done, they cried out in the Lyc·a·oʹni·an language: “The gods have become like humans and have come down to us!” 12 And they started calling Barʹna·bas Zeus, but Paul Herʹmes, since he was taking the lead in speaking. 13 And the priest of Zeus, whose temple was at the entrance of the city,* brought bulls and garlands to the gates and wanted to offer sacrifices with the crowds. 14 However, when the apostles Barʹna·bas and Paul heard of it, they ripped their garments and leaped out into the crowd and cried out: 15 “Men, why are you doing these things? We too are humans having the same infirmities as you have. And we are declaring the good news to you, for you to turn from these vain things to the living God, who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and all the things in them.

Or “to be saved.”

Or “whose temple was located just outside the city.” Lit., “the (one) being before the city.”

Monday, October 12

Do you not know that unrighteous people will not inherit God’s Kingdom? . . . And yet that is what some of you were. But you have been washed clean; . . . you have been declared righteous.—[1 Cor. 6:9,][11].

To accept the truth and live by the Bible’s moral standards, we must be willing to make changes in our thinking and conduct. Note what Peter wrote regarding these adjustments: “As obedient children, stop being molded by the desires you formerly had in your ignorance, but . . . become holy yourselves in all your conduct.” (1 Pet. 1:14, 15) For people in the morally corrupt city of Corinth, buying truth meant making major changes in their lifestyle. Likewise, to be able to buy truth, many today have turned their back on ungodly conduct. Peter further reminded Christians in his day: “The time that has passed by is sufficient for you to have done the will of the nations when you carried on in acts of brazen conduct, unbridled passions, overdrinking, wild parties, drinking bouts, and lawless idolatries.”—[1 Pet. 4:3]. w18.11 6 ¶13

^ (1 Cor. 6:9) Or do you not know that unrighteous people will not inherit God’s Kingdom? Do not be misled.* Those who are sexually immoral,* idolaters, adulterers, men who submit to homosexual acts, men who practice homosexuality,*

Or “deceived.”

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

Or “men who have sex with men.” Lit., “men who lie with men.”

^ (1 Cor. 6:11) And yet that is what some of you were. But you have been washed clean; you have been sanctified; you have been declared righteous in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ and with the spirit of our God.

^ (1 Pet. 1:14, 15) As obedient children, stop being molded by* the desires you formerly had in your ignorance, 15 but like the Holy One who called you, become holy yourselves in all your conduct,

Or “fashioned after.”

^ (1 Pet. 4:3) For the time that has passed by is sufficient for you to have done the will of the nations when you carried on in acts of brazen conduct,* unbridled passions, overdrinking, wild parties,* drinking bouts, and lawless idolatries.

Or “acts of shameless conduct.” Plural of the Greek a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

Or “revelries.”

Tuesday, October 13

All those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.—[Acts 13:48].

How can we know who are “rightly disposed for everlasting life”? As in the first century, the only way to find those people is to give a witness. Thus, we need to do just as Jesus instructed: “Into whatever city or village you enter, search out who in it is deserving.” ([Matt. 10:11]) We do not expect insincere people, haughty individuals, or those with no spiritual inclination to respond favorably to the good news. We are looking for people who are honest, humble, and hungry for the truth. We can liken this search to what Jesus as a carpenter might have done in looking for just the right wood for making furniture, doors, yokes, or other things. Once he found suitable material, he could get his toolbox, use his skill, and make the item. We must do likewise as we endeavor to make disciples of honesthearted people.—Matt. 28:19, 20. w18.10 12 ¶3-4

^ (Acts 13:48) When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.

^ (Matt. 10:11) “Into whatever city or village you enter, search out who in it is deserving, and stay there until you leave.

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

Wednesday, October 14

Philip went down to the city of Samaria and began to preach the Christ to them.—[Acts 8:5].

Philip the evangelizer provides a fine example of one who stayed focused on his ministry despite changing circumstances. In Jerusalem, a wave of persecution arose following the martyrdom of Stephen. At the time, Philip was enjoying a new privilege of service. ([Acts 6:1-6]) But when Christ’s followers were scattered, Philip could not just watch and do nothing. He went to preach in Samaria, a city that was largely untouched by the good news at that time. ([Matt. 10:5;][Acts 8:1]) Philip was willing to go wherever God’s spirit would lead him, so Jehovah used him to open up new territories. His impartial approach was likely refreshing to the Samaritans, who were used to being treated with disdain by the Jews. Little wonder that crowds listened to him “with one accord”! ([Acts 8:6-8]) Philip stayed focused on his ministry, and as a result, he and his family were richly blessed by Jehovah.—[Acts 21:8, 9]. w18.10 30 ¶14-16

^ (Acts 8:5) Now Philip went down to the city of Sa·marʹi·a and began to preach the Christ to them.

^ (Acts 6:1-6) Now in those days when the disciples were increasing, the Greek-speaking Jews began complaining against the Hebrew-speaking Jews, because their widows were being overlooked in the daily distribution. 2 So the Twelve called the multitude of the disciples together and said: “It is not right for us to leave the word of God to distribute food to tables. 3 So, brothers, select for yourselves seven reputable men from among you, full of spirit and wisdom, that we may appoint them over this necessary matter; 4 but we will devote ourselves to prayer and to the ministry of the word.” 5 What they said was pleasing to the whole multitude, and they selected Stephen, a man full of faith and holy spirit, as well as Philip, Prochʹo·rus, Ni·caʹnor, Tiʹmon, Parʹme·nas, and Nic·o·laʹus, a proselyte of Antioch. 6 They brought them to the apostles, and after praying, they laid their hands on them.

^ (Matt. 10:5) These 12 Jesus sent out, giving them these instructions: “Do not go off into the road of the nations, and do not enter any Sa·marʹi·tan city;

^ (Acts 8:1) Saul, for his part, approved of his murder. On that day great persecution arose against the congregation that was in Jerusalem; all except the apostles were scattered throughout the regions of Ju·deʹa and Sa·marʹi·a.

^ (Acts 8:6-8) The crowds with one accord were paying attention to what Philip said while they listened and observed the signs he was performing. 7 For many had unclean spirits, and these would cry out with a loud voice and come out. Moreover, many who were paralyzed and lame were cured. 8 So there came to be a great deal of joy in that city.

^ (Acts 21:8, 9) The next day we left and came to Caes·a·reʹa, and we entered the house of Philip the evangelizer, who was one of the seven men, and we stayed with him. 9 This man had four unmarried daughters who prophesied.

Thursday, October 15

Let us consider one another so as to incite to love and fine works.—[Heb. 10:24].

One time when Jesus was in the Decapolis region, people “brought him a deaf man with a speech impediment.” ([Mark 7:31-35]) Instead of healing him in public, Jesus “took him aside” and healed him. Why? The man’s disabilities may have made him feel uncomfortable in a crowd. Perhaps sensing this, Jesus healed him in private. Of course, we cannot perform miraculous cures. But we can—and should—show thoughtful regard for the needs and feelings of our fellow worshippers. Jesus understood how the deaf man felt and treated him thoughtfully. Likewise, we should show consideration for the elderly and the infirm. The Christian congregation is marked, not by mere efficiency, but by love. (John 13:34, 35) That love moves us to go out of our way to help older ones and those with disabilities to attend Christian meetings and to preach the good news. That is so even if what they can do is limited.—[Matt. 13:23]. w18.09 29-30 ¶7-8

^ (Heb. 10:24) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works,

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Mark 7:31-35) When Jesus returned from the region of Tyre, he went through Siʹdon to the Sea of Galʹi·lee, through the region of De·capʹo·lis. 32 Here they brought him a deaf man with a speech impediment, and they pleaded with him to lay his hand on him. 33 And he took him aside privately, away from the crowd. Then he put his fingers into the man’s ears, and after spitting, he touched his tongue. 34 And looking up into heaven, he sighed deeply and said to him: “Ephʹpha·tha,” that is, “Be opened.” 35 At this his ears were opened, and his speech impediment was removed, and he began speaking normally.

^ (John 13:34, 35) I am giving you a new commandment, that you love one another; just as I have loved you, you also love one another. 35 By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (Matt. 13:23) As for the one sown upon the fine soil, this is the one hearing the word and getting the sense of it, who really does bear fruit and produces, this one 100 times more, that one 60, the other 30.”

Friday, October 16

Let each of us please his neighbor for his good, to build him up.—[Rom. 15:2].

Every one of Jehovah’s sheep is extremely precious to him and to Jesus, who provided the ransom sacrifice. ([Gal. 2:20]) We love our spiritual brothers and sisters dearly. And we want to care for them in a tender and loving way. In order to be a source of refreshment, “let us pursue the things making for peace and the things that build one another up.” ([Rom. 14:19]) How we all look forward to the time when, in the coming Paradise, we will never have reason to be discouraged! There will be no more sickness, wars, inherited death, persecution, domestic strife, and disappointments. When the Millennium is past, mankind will have reached perfection. Those who pass the final test will then be adopted as earthly sons of Jehovah God and have “the glorious freedom of the children of God.” ([Rom. 8:21]) May we all keep displaying the love that builds up and helping one another to attain that joyful and rewarding goal. w18.09 14 ¶10; 16 ¶18

^ (Rom. 15:2) Let each of us please his neighbor for his good, to build him up.

^ (Gal. 2:20) I am nailed to the stake along with Christ. It is no longer I who live, but it is Christ who is living in union with me. Indeed, the life that I now live in the flesh I live by faith in the Son of God, who loved me and handed himself over for me.

^ (Rom. 14:19) So, then, let us pursue the things making for peace and the things that build one another up.

^ (Rom. 8:21) that* the creation itself will also be set free from enslavement to corruption and have the glorious freedom of the children of God.

Or “because.”

Saturday, October 17

How I do love your law! I ponder over it all day long.—[Ps. 119:97].

Studying God’s Word involves more than superficial reading and merely highlighting the answers to study questions. When we study, we consider what the material tells us about Jehovah, his ways, and his thinking. We try to understand why God commands one thing and condemns another. We also give thought to what changes we need to make in our life and in our thinking. Although all these aspects might not be considered in every session of study, we profit by spending time—perhaps half of each study period—meditating appreciatively on what we read. ([1 Tim. 4:15]) As we meditate regularly on God’s Word, we ‘prove to ourselves’ that Jehovah’s reasoning on matters is perfect. We begin to see things from his point of view, and we come to agree with that viewpoint. Our minds are ‘made over,’ and we develop a new pattern of thinking. ([Rom. 12:2]) Progressively, we make Jehovah’s thoughts our own. w18.11 24 ¶5-6

^ (Ps. 119:97) How I do love your law! I ponder over* it all day long.

Or “study.”

^ (1 Tim. 4:15) Ponder over* these things; be absorbed in them, so that your advancement may be plainly seen by all people.

Or “Meditate on.”

^ (Rom. 12:2) And stop being molded by this system of things, but be transformed by making your mind over, so that you may prove to yourselves the good and acceptable and perfect will of God.

Sunday, October 18

We are God’s fellow workers.—[1 Cor. 3:9].

In the first century C.E., Paul referred to himself and certain close associates as “God’s fellow workers” because of their role in planting and watering the seed of Kingdom truth. ([1 Cor. 3:6]) Today, we too can be “God’s fellow workers” by generously giving of our time, resources, and energy to the divinely commissioned preaching work. What a tremendous privilege this is! Being generous with our time and energy in the preaching and disciple-making work brings great joy. Many who have had the privilege of conducting progressive Bible studies will tell you that few things are more rewarding. Great happiness comes from seeing appreciative individuals light up when they grasp spiritual truths, grow in faith, make changes, and start sharing the truth with others. Jesus also experienced great happiness when the 70 preachers whom he had sent out to the field “returned with joy” because of the favorable results they had experienced.—Luke 10:17-21. w18.08 20 ¶11-12

^ (1 Cor. 3:9) For we are God’s fellow workers. You are God’s field under cultivation, God’s building.

^ (1 Cor. 3:6) I planted, A·polʹlos watered, but God kept making it grow,

^ (Luke 10:17-21) Then the 70 returned with joy, saying: “Lord,* even the demons are made subject to us by the use of your name.” 18 At that he said to them: “I see Satan already fallen like lightning from heaven. 19 Look! I have given you the authority to trample underfoot serpents and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy, and nothing at all will harm you. 20 Nevertheless, do not rejoice because the spirits are made subject to you, but rejoice because your names have been written in the heavens.” 21 In that very hour he became overjoyed in the holy spirit and said: “I publicly praise you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have carefully hidden these things from wise and intellectual ones and have revealed them to young children. Yes, O Father, because this is the way you approved.

Or “Master.”

Monday, October 19

Whoever trusts in his own heart is stupid.—[Prov. 28:26].

Leaning too heavily on our own understanding can become a snare. We may begin to feel that we can look at a situation and understand it even though we do not have all the facts. Also, a challenge to evaluating matters accurately may be faced when we have a personality conflict with a brother in the congregation. If we constantly dwell on our differences, we may begin to look at our brother with a measure of suspicion. Thus, if we hear a negative report about this brother, we may be eager to believe it. What is the lesson? Harboring ill feelings toward our brothers can lead to distorted judgments that are not based on the facts. (1 Tim. 6:4, 5) We can prevent our judgment from becoming clouded by refusing to allow envy and jealousy to take root in our hearts. Instead of giving in to such bad feelings, may we recognize our obligation to love our brothers and freely forgive them from the heart.—[Col. 3:12-14]. w18.08 6 ¶15; 7 ¶18

^ (Prov. 28:26) Whoever trusts in his own heart is stupid, But the one who walks in wisdom will escape.

^ (1 Tim. 6:4, 5) he is puffed up with pride and does not understand anything. He is obsessed* with arguments and debates about words. These things give rise to envy, strife, slander,* wicked suspicions, 5 constant disputes about minor matters by men who are corrupted in mind and deprived of the truth, thinking that godly devotion is a means of gain.

Or “has an unhealthy fascination.”

Or “abusive speeches.”

^ (Col. 3:12-14) Accordingly, as God’s chosen ones, holy and loved, clothe yourselves with the tender affections of compassion, kindness, humility,* mildness, and patience. 13 Continue putting up with one another and forgiving one another freely even if anyone has a cause for complaint against another. Just as Jehovah* freely forgave you, you must also do the same. 14 But besides all these things, clothe yourselves with love, for it is a perfect bond of union.

Or “lowliness of mind.”

See App. A5.

Tuesday, October 20

To Jehovah . . . belong the heavens . . . and the earth with all that is in it.—[Deut. 10:14].

By reason of their very existence, all humans belong to Jehovah. ([Ps. 100:3;][Rev. 4:11]) Yet, throughout human history, God has designated specific groups of people as belonging to him in a special way. For example, Psalm 135 refers to faithful worshippers of Jehovah in ancient Israel as “his special property.” ([Ps. 135:4]) Also, the book of Hosea foretold that some non-Israelites would become Jehovah’s people. ([Hos. 2:23]) Hosea’s prophecy was fulfilled when Jehovah included non-Jews in his selection of prospective corulers with Christ. ([Acts 10:45;] Rom. 9:23-26) This “holy nation” is Jehovah’s “special possession” in an outstanding way, its members having been anointed with holy spirit and chosen for life in heaven. (1 Pet. 2:9, 10) What about the majority of faithful Christians today who have an earthly hope? Jehovah also calls them his “people” and his “chosen ones.”—[Isa. 65:22]. w18.07 22 ¶1-2

^ (Deut. 10:14) Look, to Jehovah your God belong the heavens, even the heavens of the heavens,* and the earth with all that is in it.

Or “the highest heavens.”

^ (Ps. 100:3) Know* that Jehovah is God. He is the one who made us, and we belong to him.* We are his people and the sheep of his pasture.

Or “Acknowledge.”

Or possibly, “and not we ourselves.”

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ (Ps. 135:4) For Jah has chosen Jacob for himself, Israel for his special property.*

Or “treasured possession.”

^ (Hos. 2:23) I will sow her like seed for myself in the earth, And I will show mercy to her who was not shown mercy;* I will say to those not my people:* “You are my people,” And they will say: “You are my God.”’”

See Ho 1:6 ftn.

See Ho 1:9 ftn.

^ (Acts 10:45) And the circumcised believers who had come with Peter were amazed, because the free gift of the holy spirit was being poured out also on people of the nations.

^ (Rom. 9:23-26) And if this was done to make known the riches of his glory on vessels of mercy, which he prepared beforehand for glory, 24 namely, us, whom he called not only from among Jews but also from among nations, what of it? 25 It is as he says also in Ho·seʹa: “Those not my people I will call ‘my people,’ and her who was not loved, ‘beloved’; 26 and in the place where it was said to them, ‘You are not my people,’ there they will be called ‘sons of the living God.’”

^ (1 Pet. 2:9, 10) But you are “a chosen race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for special possession, that you should declare abroad the excellencies”* of the One who called you out of darkness into his wonderful light. 10 For you were once not a people, but now you are God’s people; once you had not been shown mercy, but now you have received mercy.

Lit., “the virtues,” that is, his praiseworthy qualities and deeds.

^ (Isa. 65:22) They will not build for someone else to inhabit, Nor will they plant for others to eat. For the days of my people will be like the days of a tree, And the work of their hands my chosen ones will enjoy to the full.

Wednesday, October 21

Keep this mental attitude in you that was also in Christ Jesus . . . He emptied himself and took a slave’s form.—[Phil. 2:5,][7].

True Christians imitate the Christ, who provided us with the perfect example of how a human can be generous. ([Matt. 20:28]) Each of us would do well to ask, ‘Can I follow Jesus’ example even more closely than I am already doing?’ ([1 Pet. 2:21]) We can enjoy Jehovah’s favor by imitating his and Christ’s perfect examples, by being interested in the welfare of others, and by looking for ways to care for their needs. Indeed, in the parable of the neighborly Samaritan, Jesus made clear that he expected his followers to go out of their way to help others, even those of a different background. (Luke 10:29-37) Do you recall the question that moved Jesus to recount the parable of the neighborly Samaritan? A Jew asked him: “Who really is my neighbor?” Jesus’ answer shows that like the Samaritan we must be willing to give generously if we are to enjoy God’s favor. w18.08 19 ¶5-6

^ (Phil. 2:5) Keep this mental attitude in you that was also in Christ Jesus,

^ (Phil. 2:7) No, but he emptied himself and took a slave’s form and became human.*

Lit., “came to be in the likeness of men.”

^ (Matt. 20:28) Just as the Son of man came, not to be ministered to, but to minister and to give his life as a ransom in exchange for many.”

^ (1 Pet. 2:21) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

^ (Luke 10:29-37) But wanting to prove himself righteous, the man said to Jesus: “Who really is my neighbor?” 30 In reply Jesus said: “A man was going down from Jerusalem to Jerʹi·cho and fell victim to robbers, who stripped him, beat him, and went off, leaving him half-dead. 31 Now by coincidence a priest was going down on that road, but when he saw him, he passed by on the opposite side. 32 Likewise, a Levite, when he came to the place and saw him, passed by on the opposite side. 33 But a certain Sa·marʹi·tan traveling the road came upon him, and at seeing him, he was moved with pity. 34 So he approached him and bandaged his wounds, pouring oil and wine on them. Then he mounted him on his own animal and brought him to an inn and took care of him. 35 The next day he took out two de·narʹi·i, gave them to the innkeeper, and said: ‘Take care of him, and whatever you spend besides this, I will repay you when I return.’ 36 Who of these three seems to you to have made himself neighbor to the man who fell victim to the robbers?” 37 He said: “The one who acted mercifully toward him.” Jesus then said to him: “Go and do the same yourself.”

Thursday, October 22

The angel said to her: “Greetings, you highly favored one, Jehovah is with you.”—[Luke 1:28].

Did Jehovah continue to show Mary due recognition for faithfully caring for and raising his Son? Yes, he did. God had her actions and words recorded in the Bible. Apparently, Mary was not in a position to travel with Jesus during the three and a half years of his ministry. Perhaps as a widow, Mary had to stay in Nazareth. But even though she missed out on many privileges, she was able to be with Jesus at the time of his death. ([John 19:26]) Later, though, Mary was in Jerusalem along with the disciples during the days leading up to Pentecost when holy spirit was poured out. (Acts 1:13, 14) She was likely anointed along with the others present. If so, this would mean that she was given the opportunity to be in heaven with Jesus for all eternity. What a beautiful reward for her faithful service! w18.07 9 ¶11; 10 ¶14

^ (Luke 1:28) And coming in, the angel said to her: “Greetings, you highly favored one, Jehovah is with you.”

^ (John 19:26) So when Jesus saw his mother and the disciple whom he loved standing nearby, he said to his mother: “Woman, see! Your son!”

^ (Acts 1:13, 14) When they arrived, they went up into the upper room where they were staying. There were Peter as well as John and James and Andrew, Philip and Thomas, Bar·tholʹo·mew and Matthew, James the son of Al·phaeʹus, and Simon the zealous one, and Judas the son of James. 14 With one purpose all of these were persisting in prayer, together with some women and Mary the mother of Jesus and with his brothers.

Friday, October 23

Do all things for God’s glory.—[1 Cor. 10:31].

Throughout his ministry, Jesus taught basic truths to help his disciples recognize the consequences of certain attitudes or actions. For example, he taught that resentment can lead to violence and that lust can lead to adultery. (Matt. 5:21, 22,[27, 28]) To help us have a conscience that is properly trained, we should let godly principles guide us and thus bring glory to God. On certain matters, two different Christians with Bible-trained consciences might come to opposite conclusions. Consider the use of alcoholic beverages. The Bible does not condemn the moderate use of alcohol. It does, however, warn against the excessive use of alcohol, as well as drunkenness. ([Prov. 20:1;][1 Tim. 3:8]) Does this mean that a Christian has no other factors to consider as long as his use of alcohol is moderate? Not at all. While he may be at peace with his own conscience, the Christian must also consider the conscience of others. w18.06 18 ¶10-11

^ (1 Cor. 10:31) Therefore, whether you are eating or drinking or doing anything else, do all things for God’s glory.

^ (Matt. 5:21, 22) “You heard that it was said to those of ancient times: ‘You must not murder, but whoever commits a murder will be accountable to the court of justice.’ 22 However, I say to you that everyone who continues wrathful with his brother will be accountable to the court of justice; and whoever addresses his brother with an unspeakable word of contempt will be accountable to the Supreme Court; whereas whoever says, ‘You despicable fool!’ will be liable to the fiery Ge·henʹna.

^ (Matt. 5:27, 28) “You heard that it was said: ‘You must not commit adultery.’ 28 But I say to you that everyone who keeps on looking at a woman so as to have a passion for her has already committed adultery with her in his heart.

^ (Prov. 20:1) Wine is a ridiculer, alcohol is unruly; Whoever goes astray by them is not wise.

^ (1 Tim. 3:8) Ministerial servants should likewise be serious, not double-tongued,* not indulging in a lot of wine, not greedy of dishonest gain,

Or “not deceitful in speech.”

Saturday, October 24

Look out for the leaven of the Pharisees and the leaven of Herod.—[Mark 8:15].

Jesus emphatically warned his disciples to stay clear of the teachings, or leaven, that the Pharisees, Sadducees, and party followers of Herod advocated. ([Matt. 16:6,][12]) Interestingly, this conversation took place not long after the occasion when the people wanted to make Jesus king. When religion is mixed with politics, violence can easily erupt. Jesus taught his disciples that they must maintain neutrality in these circumstances. That is related to the reason why the chief priests and the Pharisees planned to kill Jesus. They saw him as a political and religious rival who threatened their position. “If we let him go on this way, they will all put faith in him, and the Romans will come and take away both our place and our nation,” they said. ([John 11:48]) Thus, High Priest Caiaphas took the lead in plotting Jesus’ death.—John 11:49-53;[18:14]. w18.06 6-7 ¶12-13

^ (Mark 8:15) And he warned them in no uncertain terms: “Keep your eyes open; look out for the leaven of the Pharisees and the leaven of Herod.”

^ (Matt. 16:6) Jesus said to them: “Keep your eyes open and watch out for the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees.”

^ (Matt. 16:12) Then they grasped that he said to watch out, not for the leaven of bread, but for the teaching of the Pharisees and Sadducees.

^ (John 11:48) If we let him go on this way, they will all put faith in him, and the Romans will come and take away both our place and our nation.”

^ (John 11:49-53) But one of them, Caʹia·phas, who was high priest that year, said to them: “You do not know anything at all, 50 and you have not reasoned that it is to your benefit for one man to die in behalf of the people rather than for the whole nation to be destroyed.” 51 He did not say this, however, of his own originality, but because he was high priest that year, he prophesied that Jesus was to die for the nation, 52 and not only for the nation but also to gather together into one the children of God who were scattered about. 53 So from that day on they conspired to kill him.

^ (John 18:14) Caʹia·phas was, in fact, the one who had advised the Jews that it was to their benefit for one man to die in behalf of the people.

Sunday, October 25

Let your love be without hypocrisy.—[Rom. 12:9].

An effective bait that Satan uses is curiosity about the occult. Today, he promotes interest in the demons not only through false religion but also through the entertainment industry. Movies, electronic games, and other media make spiritism seem exciting. How can we avoid being caught in this trap? We should not expect God’s organization to supply a list of acceptable and unacceptable entertainment. Each of us needs to train his own conscience to be in harmony with God’s standards. ([Heb. 5:14]) However, we will make wise choices if we apply the apostle Paul’s inspired counsel above. We could ask ourselves: ‘Will my choice of entertainment make me seem hypocritical? If my Bible students or return visits saw the entertainment I choose, would they think that I practice what I preach?’ The more our speech and actions harmonize, the less likely we are to be caught in Satan’s snares.—[1 John 3:18]. w18.05 25 ¶13

^ (Rom. 12:9) Let your love be without hypocrisy. Abhor what is wicked; cling to what is good.

^ (Heb. 5:14) But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their powers of discernment* trained to distinguish both right and wrong.

Or “their perceptive powers.”

^ (1 John 3:18) Little children, we should love, not in word or with the tongue, but in deed and truth.

Monday, October 26

The goodwill of my heart and my supplication to God for them are indeed for their salvation.—[Rom. 10:1].

How can we imitate Paul? First, we strive to maintain a heartfelt desire to find any who might be “rightly disposed for everlasting life.” Second, we supplicate Jehovah in prayer to open the heart of sincere ones. ([Acts 13:48;][16:14]) Silvana, a pioneer for nearly 30 years, says, “Before I go to a house in my territory, I pray to Jehovah, asking him to give me a positive attitude.” We also pray to God that angels may direct us to find honesthearted ones. (Matt. 10:11-13;[Rev. 14:6]) Notes Robert, a pioneer for over 30 years, “To work along with angels who know what is going on in the householders’ lives is exciting.” Third, we try to see a potential for good in people. Says Carl, an elder, “I look for any small sign that may reveal a person’s sincerity, perhaps a smile, a kind look, or an honest question.” Yes, like Paul, we can endure in bearing fruit. w18.05 15 ¶13; 16 ¶15

^ (Rom. 10:1) Brothers, the goodwill of my heart and my supplication to God for them are indeed for their salvation.

^ (Acts 13:48) When those of the nations heard this, they began to rejoice and to glorify the word of Jehovah, and all those who were rightly disposed for everlasting life became believers.

^ (Acts 16:14) And a woman named Lydʹi·a, a seller of purple from the city of Thy·a·tiʹra and a worshipper of God, was listening, and Jehovah opened her heart wide to pay attention to the things Paul was saying.

^ (Matt. 10:11-13) “Into whatever city or village you enter, search out who in it is deserving, and stay there until you leave. 12 When you enter the house, greet the household. 13 If the house is deserving, let the peace you wish it come upon it; but if it is not deserving, let the peace from you return upon you.

^ (Rev. 14:6) And I saw another angel flying in midheaven,* and he had everlasting good news to declare to those who dwell on the earth, to every nation and tribe and tongue* and people.

Or “in midair; overhead.”

Or “language.”

Tuesday, October 27

Let us consider one another . . . , encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.—Heb. 10:24, 25.

News of faithfulness on the part of those we have helped in the past can be a real source of encouragement, as it was for the apostle John, who wrote: “No greater joy do I have than this: that I should hear that my children go on walking in the truth.” ([3 John 4]) Many pioneers can attest to how encouraging it is for them to learn that some of those they helped into the truth years ago are staying faithful and perhaps are even serving as pioneers. Simply reminding a discouraged pioneer of past joys can be a real source of comfort. Many circuit overseers have stated how encouraged they and their wives felt after receiving even a short note of gratitude for their visit to a congregation. The same can be true of elders, missionaries, pioneers, and Bethel family members who receive a word of appreciation for their faithful service. w18.04 23 ¶14-15

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (3 John 4) No greater joy* do I have than this: that I should hear that my children go on walking in the truth.

Or possibly, “cause for thankfulness.”

Wednesday, October 28

[The king] should [not] take many wives for himself, so that his heart [might] not go astray.—[Deut. 17:17].

Solomon disobeyed, eventually marrying 700 women. He brought into his household an additional 300 concubines. ([1 Ki. 11:3]) Many of his wives were non-Israelites, who worshipped false gods. Hence, Solomon also disobeyed God’s law against marrying foreign women. ([Deut. 7:3, 4]) Solomon’s gradual departure from Jehovah’s requirements led him in time to extreme wrongdoing. Solomon built an altar to the idol goddess Ashtoreth and at least one other altar to the false god Chemosh. There he joined his wives in pagan worship. He built those altars on, of all places, a mountain located directly in front of Jerusalem, where he had built Jehovah’s temple! (1 Ki. 11:5-8;[2 Ki. 23:13]) Perhaps Solomon fooled himself into thinking that Jehovah would overlook his disobedience as long as he also continued to offer sacrifices at the temple. But Jehovah never overlooks wrongdoing. w18.07 18-19 ¶7-9

^ (Deut. 17:17) Neither should he take many wives for himself, so that his heart may not go astray; nor should he acquire vast amounts of silver and gold for himself.

^ (1 Ki. 11:3) And he had 700 wives who were princesses and 300 concubines, and his wives gradually inclined his heart.*

Or “his wives had a powerful influence over him.”

^ (Deut. 7:3, 4) You must not form any marriage alliances* with them. Do not give your daughters to their sons or take their daughters for your sons. 4 For they will turn your sons away from following me to serve other gods; then Jehovah’s anger will blaze against you, and he will swiftly annihilate you.

Or “not intermarry.”

^ (1 Ki. 11:5-8) And Solʹo·mon followed after Ashʹto·reth, the goddess of the Si·doʹni·ans, and Milʹcom, the disgusting god of the Amʹmon·ites. 6 And Solʹo·mon did what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, and he did not follow Jehovah completely* as David his father had done. 7 It was then that Solʹo·mon built a high place to Cheʹmosh, the disgusting god of Moʹab, on the mountain in front of Jerusalem and to Moʹlech, the disgusting god of the Amʹmon·ites. 8 That was what he did for all his foreign wives who were making sacrificial smoke and sacrificing to their gods.

Lit., “fully.”

^ (2 Ki. 23:13) And the king made unfit for worship the high places in front of Jerusalem that were to the south* of the Mount of Ruination,* which Solʹo·mon the king of Israel had built to Ashʹto·reth the disgusting goddess of the Si·doʹni·ans; and to Cheʹmosh the disgusting god of Moʹab; and to Milʹcom the detestable god of the Amʹmon·ites.

Lit., “right.” That is, south, when one faces east.

That is, the Mount of Olives, particularly the southern extremity also known as the Mount of Offense.

Thursday, October 29

Take up the large shield of faith, with which you will be able to extinguish all the wicked one’s burning arrows.—[Eph. 6:16].

Some of the “burning arrows” that Satan might fire at you are lies about Jehovah—that He does not care about you and that you are unlovable. Nineteen-year-old Ida struggles with feelings of unworthiness. She says, “I have often felt that Jehovah isn’t close to me and that he doesn’t want to be my Friend.” How does she deal with this attack? “The meetings are a giant boost to my faith,” says Ida. “I used to sit there and never comment, thinking that nobody would want to hear what I had to say. Now, though, I prepare for the meetings and try to answer two or three times.” Ida’s experience highlights an important truth: The literal shield given to a soldier had fixed dimensions, but the size of our shield of faith can either shrink or grow. It is up to us. ([Matt. 14:31;] 2 Thess. 1:3) How important it is that we build up our faith! w18.05 29-30 ¶12-14

^ (Eph. 6:16) Besides all of this, take up the large shield of faith, with which you will be able to extinguish all the wicked one’s burning arrows.*

Or “missiles; darts.”

^ (Matt. 14:31) Immediately stretching out his hand, Jesus caught hold of him and said to him: “You with little faith, why did you give way to doubt?”

^ (2 Thess. 1:3) We are obligated always to give thanks to God for you, brothers. This is fitting, because your faith is growing exceedingly and the love of each and every one of you is increasing toward one another.

Friday, October 30

What must I do to get saved?—[Acts 16:30].

The jailer had a change of heart and asked for help only after the earthquake struck. (Acts 16:25-34) Similarly, some individuals today who have not responded to the Bible’s message before may have a change of heart and look for help when their world is suddenly shaken by a seismic event. Perhaps they may have lost their longtime job unexpectedly and are left in shock. Others may be at a loss after being diagnosed with a serious illness, or they may be heartbroken after losing a loved one in death. They may ask questions about the meaning of life that at one time they ignored. Perhaps they even wonder, ‘What must I do to get saved?’ When we meet them, they may want to listen to our message of hope for the first time in their life. Therefore, by faithfully continuing in our preaching work, we make sure that we will be available to give comfort to people at a time when they may be ready to accept it.—[Isa. 61:1]. w18.05 19-20 ¶10-12

^ (Acts 16:30) He brought them outside and said: “Sirs, what must I do to get saved?”

^ (Acts 16:25-34) But about the middle of the night, Paul and Silas were praying and praising God with song, and the prisoners were listening to them. 26 Suddenly a great earthquake occurred, so that the foundations of the jail were shaken. Moreover, all the doors were instantly opened, and everyone’s bonds came loose. 27 When the jailer woke up and saw that the prison doors were open, he drew his sword and was about to kill himself, assuming that the prisoners had escaped. 28 But Paul called out with a loud voice: “Do not hurt yourself, for we are all here!” 29 So he asked for lights and rushed in, and seized with trembling, he fell down before Paul and Silas. 30 He brought them outside and said: “Sirs, what must I do to get saved?” 31 They said: “Believe in the Lord Jesus, and you will get saved, you and your household.” 32 Then they spoke the word of Jehovah to him together with all those in his house. 33 And he took them along in that hour of the night and washed their wounds. Then he and his entire household were baptized without delay. 34 He brought them into his house and set a table before them, and he rejoiced greatly with all his household now that he had believed in God.

^ (Isa. 61:1) The spirit of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah is upon me, Because Jehovah anointed me to declare good news to the meek. He sent me to bind up the brokenhearted, To proclaim liberty to the captives And the wide opening of the eyes to the prisoners,

Saturday, October 31

Jehovah’s spirit is upon me, because he anointed me to declare good news.—[Luke 4:18].

Today, the vast majority of people are still blinded by the god of this system of things and are in bondage—religious, economic, and social. ([2 Cor. 4:4]) It is our privilege to follow Jesus’ example of helping people to come to know and worship Jehovah, the God of freedom. (Matt. 28:19, 20) That is not an easy work, and there are many challenges. In some lands, people are becoming more indifferent, some even hostile. The question that each of us should consider is, ‘Can I use my freedom to give greater support to the Kingdom work?’ It is most encouraging to see that many have sensed the urgency of our times and have simplified their lives so as to share in the full-time ministry. ([1 Cor. 9:19,][23]) Some of them serve within their local territories; others move to where the need is greater. What a splendid result of making wise use of the freedom to serve Jehovah!—[Ps. 110:3]. w18.04 11-12 ¶13-14

^ (Luke 4:18) “Jehovah’s spirit is upon me, because he anointed me to declare good news to the poor. He sent me to proclaim liberty to the captives and a recovery of sight to the blind, to send the crushed ones away free,

^ (2 Cor. 4:4) among whom the god of this system of things* has blinded the minds of the unbelievers, so that the illumination* of the glorious good news about the Christ, who is the image of God, might not shine through.

Or “this age.” See Glossary.

Or “light.”

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”

^ (1 Cor. 9:19) For though I am free from all people, I have made myself the slave to all, so that I may gain as many people as possible.

^ (1 Cor. 9:23) But I do all things for the sake of the good news, in order to share it with others.

^ (Ps. 110:3) Your people will offer themselves willingly on the day of your military force.* In splendid holiness, from the womb of the dawn, You have your company of young men just like dewdrops.

Or “on the day your army mobilizes.”

November

Sunday, November 1

Whoever feeds on this bread will live forever.—[John 6:58].

When we serve Jehovah, we have the prospect of eventually gaining all that Adam and Eve lost, including the opportunity to live forever. Adam and Eve chose not to serve Jehovah because they failed to develop a strong love for him. Even so, Jehovah allowed them to live long enough to have children and to set their own standards for raising those children. The results of Adam and Eve’s decision to be independent of Jehovah soon made it clear how foolish they had been. Their oldest son murdered his innocent brother, and in time violence and selfishness dominated the human family. ([Gen. 4:8;][6:11-13]) All the while, Jehovah had a means to save all of Adam and Eve’s children who want to serve him. (John 6:38-40,[57]) As you learn more about how patient and loving Jehovah is, your love for him will likely grow. You will want to reject the course that Adam and Eve chose and dedicate yourself to Jehovah. w19.03 2 ¶3; 4 ¶9

^ (John 6:58) This is the bread that came down from heaven. It is not as when your forefathers ate and yet died. Whoever feeds on this bread will live forever.”

^ (Gen. 4:8) After that Cain said to his brother Abel: “Let us go over into the field.” So while they were in the field, Cain assaulted his brother Abel and killed him.

^ (Gen. 6:11-13) But the earth had become ruined in the sight of the true God, and the earth was filled with violence. 12 Yes, God looked upon the earth, and it was ruined; all flesh* had ruined its way on the earth. 13 After that God said to Noah: “I have decided to put an end to all flesh, because the earth is full of violence on account of them, so I am bringing them to ruin together with the earth.

Or “people.”

^ (John 6:38-40) for I have come down from heaven to do, not my own will, but the will of him who sent me. 39 This is the will of him who sent me, that I should lose none out of all those whom he has given me, but that I should resurrect them on the last day. 40 For this is the will of my Father, that everyone who recognizes the Son and exercises faith in him should have everlasting life, and I will resurrect him on the last day.”

^ (John 6:57) Just as the living Father sent me and I live because of the Father, so also the one who feeds on me will live because of me.

Monday, November 2

All of you have . . . fellow feeling.—[1 Pet. 3:8].

To develop fellow feeling, try to understand what family members and fellow believers are going through. Take an interest in the teenagers in the congregation as well as in the sick, the elderly, and those who have lost loved ones in death. Ask how they are doing. Really listen as they express themselves. Help them sense that you truly understand what they are dealing with. Offer to help in whatever way you can. When we do this, we show genuine love in action. ([1 John 3:18]) We need to be flexible when trying to help others. Why? Because people react to hardship in different ways. Some are eager to talk, while others are more reserved. So we want to offer help, but we should avoid asking questions that are too personal. (1 Thess. 4:11) Even when others do open up, we may find that we do not always share their point of view. Yet, we need to recognize that this is how they feel. We want to be quick to listen and slow to speak.—[Matt. 7:1;][Jas. 1:19]. w19.03 19 ¶18-19

^ (1 Pet. 3:8) Finally, all of you have unity of mind,* fellow feeling, brotherly affection, tender compassion, and humility.

Or “think in agreement.”

^ (1 John 3:18) Little children, we should love, not in word or with the tongue, but in deed and truth.

^ (1 Thess. 4:11) Make it your aim to live quietly and to mind your own business and to work with your hands, just as we instructed you,

^ (Matt. 7:1) “Stop judging that you may not be judged;

^ (Jas. 1:19) Know this, my beloved brothers: Everyone must be quick to listen, slow to speak, slow to anger,

Tuesday, November 3

I became very frightened.—[Neh. 2:2].

Do you have fears when speaking publicly about the truth? Remember Nehemiah. He served in the court of a powerful king. Nehemiah was gloomy because he had heard that the walls and gates of Jerusalem were in ruins. ([Neh. 1:1-4]) Imagine the knot he might have had in his stomach when the king asked him to explain why he was looking so unhappy! Nehemiah quickly prayed and then gave his answer. In response, the king did much to help God’s people. ([Neh. 2:1-8]) Think, too, of Jonah. When Jehovah asked him to speak to the inhabitants of Nineveh, Jonah was so scared that he ran in the opposite direction. ([Jonah 1:1-3]) But with Jehovah’s help, Jonah carried out his assignment. And the words he spoke did much good for those in Nineveh. ([Jonah 3:5-10]) From Nehemiah we learn the importance of praying before we answer. And from Jonah we learn that Jehovah can help us to serve him despite our greatest fears. w19.01 11 ¶12

^ (Neh. 2:2) So the king said to me: “Why do you look so gloomy when you are not sick? This can be nothing but gloominess of heart.” At this I became very frightened.

^ (Neh. 1:1-4) The words of Ne·he·miʹah* the son of Hac·a·liʹah: Now in the month of Chisʹlev,* in the 20th year, I was in Shuʹshan* the citadel.* 2 At that time Ha·naʹni, one of my brothers, arrived with other men from Judah, and I asked them about the remaining Jews who had escaped the captivity, and also about Jerusalem. 3 They replied: “Those remaining there in the province* who have survived the captivity are in a terrible situation and in disgrace. The walls of Jerusalem are broken down, and its gates have been burned with fire.” 4 As soon as I heard these words, I sat down and began to weep and mourn for days, and I kept fasting and praying before the God of the heavens.

Meaning “Jah Comforts.”

See App. B15.

Or “Susa.”

Or “palace; fortress.”

Or “jurisdictional district.”

^ (Neh. 2:1-8) In the month of Niʹsan,* in the 20th year of King Ar·ta·xerxʹes, wine was set before him, and as usual I took up the wine and gave it to the king. But I had never been gloomy in his presence. 2 So the king said to me: “Why do you look so gloomy when you are not sick? This can be nothing but gloominess of heart.” At this I became very frightened. 3 Then I said to the king: “Long live the king! Why should I not look gloomy when the city, the place where my forefathers are buried, lies in ruins, and its gates have been consumed by fire?” 4 The king then said to me: “What is it that you are seeking?” At once I prayed to the God of the heavens. 5 I then said to the king: “If it pleases the king and if your servant has found favor with you, send me to Judah, to the city where my forefathers are buried, so that I may rebuild it.” 6 Then the king, with his royal consort* sitting beside him, said to me: “How long will your journey be, and when will you return?” So it pleased the king to send me, and I gave him a set time. 7 Then I said to the king: “If it pleases the king, let letters be given me for the governors of the region Beyond the River,* granting me safe passage until I reach Judah, 8 as well as a letter to Aʹsaph the keeper of the Royal Park,* so that he may give me timber for beams for the gates of the Fortress of the House* and for the walls of the city and for the house where I will go.” So the king gave them to me, for the good hand of my God was upon me.

See App. B15.

Or “his queen.”

Or “of Trans-Euphrates.”

Or “the king’s forest.”

Or “Temple.”

^ (Jonah 1:1-3) The word of Jehovah came to Joʹnah* the son of A·mitʹtai, saying: 2 “Get up, go to Ninʹe·veh the great city, and proclaim judgment against her, for their wickedness has come to my attention.” 3 But Joʹnah got up to run away from Jehovah to Tarʹshish; he went down to Jopʹpa and found a ship going to Tarʹshish. So he paid the fare and went aboard to go with them to Tarʹshish, away from Jehovah.

Meaning “Dove.”

^ (Jonah 3:5-10) And the men of Ninʹe·veh put faith in God, and they proclaimed a fast and put on sackcloth, from the greatest to the least of them. 6 When the message reached the king of Ninʹe·veh, he rose up from his throne and took off his royal garment and covered himself with sackcloth and sat down in the ashes. 7 Furthermore, he issued a proclamation throughout Ninʹe·veh, “By the decree of the king and his nobles: No man or beast, herd or flock, should eat anything at all. They should not take food, nor should they drink any water. 8 Let them be covered with sackcloth, both man and beast; and let them call out earnestly to God and turn from their evil ways and from the violence they practice. 9 Who knows whether the true God may reconsider* what he intends to do and turn from his burning anger, so that we may not perish?” 10 When the true God saw what they did, how they had turned back from their evil ways, he reconsidered* the calamity that he said he would bring on them, and he did not bring it.

Or “feel regret over.”

Or “felt regret over.”

Wednesday, November 4

No one has left house or [family] for my sake and for the sake of the good news who will not get 100 times more now . . . and in the coming system of things, everlasting life.—Mark 10:29, 30.

When we choose to live according to Bible truth, our ties with friends and relatives may change. Why? Jesus prayed regarding his followers: “Sanctify them by means of the truth; your word is truth.” ([John 17:17]; ftn.) “Sanctify them” can also mean “set them apart.” When we accept the truth, we are set apart from the world because we no longer fit into its mold. People view us differently because our values have changed. We live by the standards of Bible truth. Though we do not want to cause division, some friends and close family members may distance themselves from us or even oppose our newfound faith. This does not surprise us. Jesus acknowledged: “Indeed, a man’s enemies will be those of his own household.” ([Matt. 10:36]) He also gave assurance that the rewards for buying truth far exceed any price we may pay. w18.11 6 ¶11

^ (Mark 10:29, 30) Jesus said: “Truly I say to you, no one has left house or brothers or sisters or mother or father or children or fields for my sake and for the sake of the good news 30 who will not get 100 times more now in this period of time*—houses, brothers, sisters, mothers, children, and fields, with persecutions—and in the coming system of things, everlasting life.

Or “in the present time.”

^ (John 17:17) Sanctify them by means of the truth; your word is truth.

^ (Matt. 10:36) Indeed, a man’s enemies will be those of his own household.

Thursday, November 5

All the congregations of the nations give thanks.—[Rom. 16:4].

The apostle Paul appreciated his brothers and sisters and showed it in the way he talked about them. He always thanked God for them in his private prayers. He also expressed his appreciation when writing to them. In the first 15 verses of Romans 16, Paul mentions 27 fellow Christians by name. Paul specifically recalled that Prisca and Aquila “risked their own necks” for him, and he described Phoebe as “a defender of many,” including Paul. He commended those beloved, hardworking brothers and sisters. (Rom. 16:1-15) Paul was aware that his brothers and sisters were imperfect, but he chose to focus on their good qualities. Imagine how encouraged those brothers and sisters must have been to hear Paul’s comments read aloud to the congregation! As a result, their bond of friendship with Paul no doubt grew stronger. Do you regularly express appreciation for the good things that members of your congregation say and do? w19.02 16 ¶8-9

^ (Rom. 16:4) who have risked their own necks for me and to whom not only I but also all the congregations of the nations give thanks.

Friday, November 6

I will not renounce my integrity!—[Job 27:5].

Must we be perfect in order to have integrity? After all, we may feel that we are less than sound, or even very flawed. We need not fear, for Jehovah does not focus on our flaws. His Word tells us: “If errors were what you watch, O Jah, then who, O Jehovah, could stand?” ([Ps. 130:3]) He knows that we are imperfect, sinful humans, and he forgives us generously. ([Ps. 86:5]) Also, Jehovah knows our limitations, and he does not expect more of us than we can do. (Ps. 103:12-14) For servants of Jehovah, the key to integrity is love. Our love for God, our loyal devotion to him as our heavenly Father, must remain complete, sound, or whole. If our love remains like that even when we are tested, then we have integrity. (1 Chron. 28:9;[Matt. 22:37]) We know that Jehovah has righteous standards, and our minds are focused on what pleases our heavenly Father. Our love for him moves us to put him first in the decisions we make and thus display our integrity. w19.02 3 ¶4-5

^ (Job 27:5) It is unthinkable for me to declare you men righteous! Until I die, I will not renounce* my integrity!

Or “I will not take away from myself; I will maintain.”

^ (Ps. 130:3) If errors were what you watch,* O Jah,* Then who, O Jehovah, could stand?

Or “keep track of.”

“Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ (Ps. 86:5) For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive; You abound in loyal love for all those who call on you.

^ (Ps. 103:12-14) As far off as the sunrise is from the sunset, So far off from us he has put our transgressions. 13 As a father shows mercy to his sons, Jehovah has shown mercy to those who fear him. 14 For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust.

^ (1 Chron. 28:9) “And you, Solʹo·mon my son, know the God of your father and serve him with a complete* heart and with a delightful* soul,* for Jehovah searches through all hearts, and he discerns every inclination of the thoughts. If you search for him, he will let himself be found by you, but if you leave him, he will reject you forever.

Or “completely devoted.”

Or “willing.”

See Glossary.

^ (Matt. 22:37) He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind.’

Saturday, November 7

Safeguard your heart.—[Prov. 4:23].

Each time we see the benefits of doing what is right, our faith grows stronger. ([Jas. 1:2, 3]) We feel good because we have made Jehovah proud to call us one of his children, and our desire to please him becomes stronger. ([Prov. 27:11]) Each test becomes an opportunity to show that we are not halfhearted about serving our caring Father. ([Ps. 119:113]) Instead, we prove that we love Jehovah with a complete heart, one that is fully resolved to obey his commandments and to do his will. ([1 Ki. 8:61]) Will we make mistakes? Yes; we are imperfect. If we do stumble, remember King Hezekiah’s example. He made mistakes. But he repented and kept on serving Jehovah “with a complete heart.” ([Isa. 38:3-6;] 2 Chron. 29:1, 2;[32:25, 26]) Let us, then, reject Satan’s attempts to infect us with his thinking. Let us pray that we develop “an obedient heart” and remain faithful to Jehovah.—[1 Ki. 3:9;] Ps. 139:23, 24. w19.01 18-19 ¶17-18

^ (Prov. 4:23) Above all the things that you guard, safeguard your heart, For out of it are the sources of life.

^ (Jas. 1:2, 3) Consider it all joy, my brothers, when you meet with various trials, 3 knowing as you do that this tested quality of your faith produces endurance.

^ (Prov. 27:11) Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice, So that I can make a reply to him who taunts me.

^ (Ps. 119:113) I hate the halfhearted ones,* But I love your law.

Or “men of divided heart.”

^ (1 Ki. 8:61) So let your heart be complete with* Jehovah our God by walking in his regulations and by keeping his commandments as on this day.”

Or “completely devoted to.”

^ (Isa. 38:3-6) “I beg you, O Jehovah, remember, please, how I have walked before you faithfully and with a complete heart, and I have done what was good in your eyes.” And Hez·e·kiʹah began to weep profusely. 4 Then the word of Jehovah came to Isaiah, saying: 5 “Go back and say to Hez·e·kiʹah, ‘This is what Jehovah the God of David your forefather says: “I have heard your prayer. I have seen your tears. Here I am adding 15 years to your life,* 6 and I will rescue you and this city out of the hand of the king of As·syrʹi·a, and I will defend this city.

Lit., “days.”

^ (2 Chron. 29:1, 2) Hez·e·kiʹah became king at the age of 25, and he reigned for 29 years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was A·biʹjah the daughter of Zech·a·riʹah. 2 He kept doing what was right in Jehovah’s eyes, just as David his forefather had done.

^ (2 Chron. 32:25, 26) But Hez·e·kiʹah did not respond appreciatively to the good done to him, for his heart became haughty, bringing indignation against him and against Judah and Jerusalem. 26 However, Hez·e·kiʹah humbled himself for the haughtiness of his heart, he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and Jehovah’s indignation did not come upon them in the days of Hez·e·kiʹah.

^ (1 Ki. 3:9) So grant your servant an obedient heart to judge your people, to discern between good and bad, for who is able to judge this numerous* people of yours?”

Or possibly, “difficult.” Lit., “heavy.”

^ (Ps. 139:23, 24) Search through me, O God, and know my heart. Examine me, and know my anxious* thoughts. 24 See whether there is in me any harmful way, And lead me in the way of eternity.

Or “disquieting.”

Sunday, November 8

Let us always offer to God a sacrifice of praise, that is, the fruit of our lips that make public declaration to his name.—[Heb. 13:15].

We benefit ourselves when we comment at meetings. ([Isa. 48:17]) How so? First, if we plan to give a comment, we are especially motivated to prepare well for the meeting. When we prepare well, we gain a deeper understanding of God’s Word. And the deeper our understanding, the better we can apply the things we learn. Second, we will likely enjoy the meeting more because we are involved in the discussion. Third, because it takes effort to comment, we often remember the points we spoke about long after the meeting ends. Also, we please Jehovah when we express our faith. We can be sure that Jehovah listens to us and deeply appreciates the effort we make to comment at meetings. ([Mal. 3:16]) He shows his appreciation by blessing us when we try hard to please him. ([Mal. 3:10]) Clearly, we have good reasons to comment at meetings. w19.01 8 ¶3; 9-10 ¶7-9

^ (Heb. 13:15) Through him let us always offer to God a sacrifice of praise, that is, the fruit of our lips that make public declaration to his name.

^ (Isa. 48:17) This is what Jehovah says, your Repurchaser, the Holy One of Israel: “I, Jehovah, am your God, The One teaching you to benefit yourself,* The One guiding you in the way you should walk.

Or “for your own good.”

^ (Mal. 3:16) At that time those who fear Jehovah spoke with one another, each one with his companion, and Jehovah kept paying attention and listening. And a book of remembrance was written before him for those fearing Jehovah and for those meditating on* his name.

Or “thinking on.” Or possibly, “treasuring.”

^ (Mal. 3:10) Bring the entire tithe* into the storehouse, so that there may be food in my house; and test me out, please, in this regard,” Jehovah of armies says, “to see whether I will not open to you the floodgates of the heavens and pour out* on you a blessing until there is nothing lacking.”

Or “all the tenth parts.”

Lit., “empty out.”

Monday, November 9

Abhor what is wicked; cling to what is good.—[Rom. 12:9].

Jehovah takes a very wise approach to his servants. Instead of giving us endless laws, he patiently teaches us to follow the law of love. He wants us to live by godly principles and to hate what is bad. Jesus’ Sermon on the Mount is a fine example of that teaching, for it addresses the root causes of wrongdoing. (Matt. 5:27, 28) As King of God’s Kingdom, Christ will continue to educate us in the new world so that our attitude toward righteousness and lawlessness will perfectly mirror his. ([Heb. 1:9]) He will also elevate us to physical and mental perfection. Imagine, you will no longer feel the tug of sin or experience the horrible effects of sin. Then, at last, you will enjoy “the glorious freedom” that Jehovah promised you. ([Rom. 8:21]) Of course, our freedom will never be absolute. Our freedom will have its fullest expression only when it is guided by godlike love.—1 John 4:7, 8. w18.12 23 ¶19-20

^ (Rom. 12:9) Let your love be without hypocrisy. Abhor what is wicked; cling to what is good.

^ (Matt. 5:27, 28) “You heard that it was said: ‘You must not commit adultery.’ 28 But I say to you that everyone who keeps on looking at a woman so as to have a passion for her has already committed adultery with her in his heart.

^ (Heb. 1:9) You loved righteousness, and you hated lawlessness. That is why God, your God, anointed you with the oil of exultation more than your companions.”

^ (Rom. 8:21) that* the creation itself will also be set free from enslavement to corruption and have the glorious freedom of the children of God.

Or “because.”

^ (1 John 4:7, 8) Beloved ones, let us continue loving one another, because love is from God, and everyone who loves has been born from God and knows God. 8 Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.

Tuesday, November 10

He must write out a certificate of divorce for her . . . and dismiss her from his house.—[Deut. 24:1].

An Israelite man could divorce his wife if “he found something indecent about her.” The Law did not describe what was meant by “indecent.” It must have been something shameful or serious, not some petty offense. ([Deut. 23:14]) Sadly, by Jesus’ day many Jews divorced “on every sort of grounds.” ([Matt. 19:3]) We would surely not want to adopt their attitude. The prophet Malachi revealed God’s view of divorce. That was at a time when it was common for a man treacherously to divorce ‘the wife of his youth,’ maybe to marry a younger, pagan woman. Regarding God’s view, Malachi wrote: “I hate divorce.” ([Mal. 2:14-16]) That was in line with what God’s Word says about the first marriage: “[A man] will stick to his wife, and they will become one flesh.” ([Gen. 2:24]) Jesus upheld his Father’s view of marriage, saying: “What God has yoked together, let no man put apart.”—[Matt. 19:6]. w18.12 11 ¶7-8

^ (Deut. 24:1) “If a man marries a woman but she does not please him because he found something indecent about her, he must write out a certificate of divorce for her, hand it to her, and dismiss her from his house.

^ (Deut. 23:14) For Jehovah your God is walking about within your camp to deliver you and to hand over your enemies to you, and your camp must be holy, so that he does not see anything indecent in you and turn away from accompanying you.

^ (Matt. 19:3) And Pharisees came to him intent on testing him, and they asked: “Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife on every sort of grounds?”

^ (Mal. 2:14-16) And you say, ‘For what reason?’ It is because Jehovah has acted as a witness between you and the wife of your youth, with whom you have dealt treacherously, although she is your partner and your wife by covenant.* 15 But there was one who did not do it, for he had what remained of the spirit. And what was that one seeking? The offspring* of God. So guard yourselves respecting your spirit, and do not deal treacherously with the wife of your youth. 16 For I hate* divorce,” says Jehovah the God of Israel, “and the one who covers his garment with violence,”* says Jehovah of armies. “And guard yourselves respecting your spirit, and you must not deal treacherously.

Or “your legal wife.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “he hates.”

Or “who engages in violence.”

^ (Gen. 2:24) That is why a man will leave his father and his mother and he will stick to* his wife, and they will become one flesh.

Or “remain with.”

^ (Matt. 19:6) So that they are no longer two, but one flesh. Therefore, what God has yoked together, let no man put apart.”

Wednesday, November 11

The harvest is great, but the workers are few.—[Matt. 9:37].

The circumstances of some brothers and sisters allow them to make themselves available farther afield. Their attitude is similar to that of the prophet Isaiah. In response to Jehovah’s question, “Whom shall I send, and who will go for us?” he replied: “Here I am! Send me!” ([Isa. 6:8]) Do you have the desire and circumstances to respond in a similar way to theocratic needs? Concerning the preaching and disciple-making work, Jesus said: “Therefore, beg the Master of the harvest to send out workers into his harvest.” ([Matt. 9:38]) Can you serve in a field where the need is greater, perhaps as a pioneer? Or can you help someone else to do so? Many brothers and sisters have felt that the best way to show love for God and neighbor is to pioneer in areas or in territories in which there is a greater need for harvest workers. Can you think of other ways to expand or increase your service? Great joy comes from doing so. w18.08 27 ¶14-15

^ (Matt. 9:37) Then he said to his disciples: “Yes, the harvest is great, but the workers are few.

^ (Isa. 6:8) Then I heard the voice of Jehovah saying: “Whom shall I send, and who will go for us?” And I said: “Here I am! Send me!”

^ (Matt. 9:38) Therefore, beg the Master of the harvest to send out workers into his harvest.”

Thursday, November 12

Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things.—[Heb. 13:5].

The Gospels give us clear indications of Jehovah’s thinking with regard to material things. God handpicked the human parents who would raise his Son—a couple who were of modest material means. ([Lev. 12:8;][Luke 2:24]) When Jesus was born, Mary “laid him in a manger, because there was no room for them in the lodging place.” ([Luke 2:7]) Had Jehovah wanted to, he could in any number of ways have provided better accommodations for the birth of his Son. What mattered to Him, though, was the spiritual environment in which Jesus would be cared for and raised. From this Bible account, we can appreciate Jehovah’s view of material things. Some parents insist on the best for their children materially, even at the expense of their children’s spiritual health. Clearly, though, Jehovah considers spiritual matters to be of supreme importance. Have you adopted Jehovah’s view? What do your actions reveal? w18.11 24 ¶7-8

^ (Heb. 13:5) Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things. For he has said: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.”

^ (Lev. 12:8) But if she cannot afford a sheep, she must then take two turtledoves or two young pigeons, one for a burnt offering and one for a sin offering, and the priest will make atonement for her, and she will be clean.’”

^ (Luke 2:24) And they offered a sacrifice according to what is said in the Law of Jehovah: “a pair of turtledoves or two young pigeons.”

^ (Luke 2:7) And she gave birth to her son, the firstborn, and she wrapped him in strips of cloth and laid him in a manger, because there was no room for them in the lodging place.

Friday, November 13

Happy is the people whose God is Jehovah!—[Ps. 144:15].

Being the Source of happiness, God wants us to be happy, and he gives us many reasons to rejoice. ([Deut. 12:7;] Eccl. 3:12, 13) In today’s world, though, being happy may be a challenge. Why? Stressful events—such as when a loved one dies or is disfellowshipped or when faced with a divorce or the loss of a job—can rob us of happiness. Domestic strife and a breakdown in peaceful communication can erode our sense of well-being. Ridicule by workmates or classmates, religious persecution, or imprisonment can undermine our happiness. So can deteriorating health, chronic illness, or depression. Nevertheless, Jesus Christ, “the happy and only Potentate,” delighted in bringing comfort and happiness to people. ([1 Tim. 6:15;] Matt. 11:28-30) In his Sermon on the Mount, Jesus identified a number of qualities that can contribute to our happiness despite distressing trials in Satan’s world. w18.09 17-18 ¶1-3

^ (Ps. 144:15) Happy is the people for whom it is this way! Happy is the people whose God is Jehovah!

^ (Deut. 12:7) You and your households must eat there before Jehovah your God and rejoice in all your undertakings, because Jehovah your God has blessed you.

^ (Eccl. 3:12, 13) I have concluded that there is nothing better for them than to rejoice and to do good during their life, 13 also that everyone should eat and drink and find enjoyment for all his hard work. It is the gift of God.

^ (1 Tim. 6:15) which the happy and only Potentate will show in its own appointed times. He is the King of those who rule as kings and Lord of those who rule as lords,

^ (Matt. 11:28-30) Come to me, all you who are toiling* and loaded down, and I will refresh you. 29 Take my yoke upon you and learn from me,* for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and you will find refreshment for yourselves. 30 For my yoke is kindly,* and my load is light.”

Or “struggling hard.” Or possibly, “weary; tired.”

Or “become my disciples (learners).”

Or “easy to bear; pleasant.”

Saturday, November 14

Do not cut yourselves or shave your foreheads bald for a dead person.—[Deut. 14:1].

Giving up unscriptural customs and practices can be one of the most difficult prices to pay for truth. ([Prov. 23:23]) Although some may find it easy to accept the Scriptural basis for abandoning these practices, others may hesitate to pay the price because of pressure from family members, workmates, and close friends. The situation may become emotionally charged, especially if a custom involves rites in honor of dead relatives. The courageous example of others can help us to make the necessary changes. What did newly converted Christians in Ephesus who had been practicing magical arts do in order to put away those unscriptural practices and buy truth? The Bible explains: “[They] brought their books together and burned them up before everybody. And they calculated their value and found them worth 50,000 pieces of silver.” (Acts 19:19, 20) The faithful Christians made this costly sacrifice and gained priceless blessings. w18.11 7 ¶15-16

^ (Deut. 14:1) “You are sons of Jehovah your God. Do not cut yourselves or shave your foreheads bald* for a dead person.

Lit., “put (make) baldness between your eyes.”

^ (Prov. 23:23) Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding.

Or “Acquire.”

^ (Acts 19:19, 20) Indeed, quite a number of those who practiced magical arts brought their books together and burned them up before everybody. And they calculated their value and found them worth 50,000 pieces of silver. 20 Thus in a mighty way, the word of Jehovah kept growing and prevailing.

Sunday, November 15

When they finished circumcising the entire nation, they remained where they were in the camp until they recovered.—[Josh. 5:8].

Soon after Israel crossed the Jordan, Joshua met a man carrying a drawn sword. He was none other than the “chief of Jehovah’s army,” who was ready to defend God’s people. (Josh. 5:13-15; ftn.) Joshua received clear instructions from the angelic Leader on how to take the city of Jericho. At first, some of the instructions may not have appeared to be a good strategy. For instance, Jehovah commanded that all the men be circumcised, which would leave them indisposed for several days. (Gen. 34:24, 25;[Josh. 5:2]) Likely, those defenseless Israelite soldiers wondered how they would protect their family if enemy warriors raided their camp. But suddenly, the news broke that Jericho was “tightly shut up because of the Israelites.” ([Josh. 6:1]) Would their trust in God’s direction not have been strengthened by such an unexpected turn of events? w18.10 23 ¶5-7

^ (Josh. 5:8) When they finished circumcising the entire nation, they remained where they were in the camp until they recovered.

^ (Josh. 5:13-15) When Joshua was near Jerʹi·cho, he looked up and saw a man standing in front of him with a drawn sword in his hand. Joshua walked up to him and asked: “Are you on our side or on the side of our adversaries?” 14 To this he said: “No, but I have come as prince* of Jehovah’s army.” With that Joshua fell with his face to the ground and prostrated himself and said to him: “What does my lord have to say to his servant?” 15 The prince of Jehovah’s army replied to Joshua: “Remove your sandals from your feet, because the place where you are standing is holy.” At once Joshua did so.

Or “chief.”

^ (Gen. 34:24, 25) All those going out by the gate of his city listened to Haʹmor and to his son Sheʹchem, and all the males got circumcised, all those going out of the city gate. 25 However, on the third day, when they were still in pain, two sons of Jacob, Simʹe·on and Leʹvi, Diʹnah’s brothers, each took his sword and went into the unsuspecting city and killed every male.

^ (Josh. 5:2) At that time Jehovah said to Joshua: “Make for yourself flint knives and circumcise the men of Israel again, a second time.”

^ (Josh. 6:1) Now Jerʹi·cho was tightly shut up because of the Israelites; no one was leaving and no one was entering.

Monday, November 16

Why are you doing these things? We too are humans having the same infirmities as you have.—[Acts 14:15].

How might we imitate Paul’s exemplary humility? First, we must resist any temptation to expect or accept adulation for what we accomplish in Jehovah’s strength. Each of us does well to ask himself: ‘How do I view the people to whom I preach? Might I unwittingly harbor toward certain people a bias that is common in my community?’ Commendably, Jehovah’s Witnesses around the world have been analyzing their territories to determine whether there are yet more who might respond to the good news. At times, this may require learning the languages and customs of those whom society in general has marginalized. In no way should Witnesses who reach out to such ones view themselves as superior. Rather, they seek to understand each individual in order to reach his heart with the Kingdom message. w18.09 5 ¶9, 11

^ (Acts 14:15) “Men, why are you doing these things? We too are humans having the same infirmities as you have. And we are declaring the good news to you, for you to turn from these vain things to the living God, who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and all the things in them.

Tuesday, November 17

Judas the Galilean rose up . . . , and he drew followers after himself.—[Acts 5:37].

The Romans had Judas executed. Apart from Judas and the other extremists, ordinary Jews were keenly awaiting the arrival of a political Messiah. That is, they expected that when the Messiah appeared, he would bring glory to their nation and freedom from the yoke of Rome. ([Luke 2:38;][3:15]) Many believed that the Messiah would establish a kingdom on earth in Israel. When that occurred, millions of Jews scattered abroad would return to their homeland. Recall that John the Baptist once asked Jesus: “Are you the Coming One, or are we to expect a different one?” (Matt. 11:2, 3) John may have wanted to know whether someone else would fulfill all the hopes of the Jews. The two disciples who met the resurrected Jesus on the road to Emmaus also had unfulfilled hopes about the Messiah. ([Luke 24:21]) Soon thereafter, Jesus’ apostles asked him: “Lord, are you restoring the kingdom to Israel at this time?”—[Acts 1:6]. w18.06 4 ¶3-4

^ (Acts 5:37) After him, Judas the Gal·i·leʹan rose up in the days of the registration, and he drew followers after himself. That man also perished, and all those who were following him were scattered.

^ (Luke 2:38) In that very hour she came near and began giving thanks to God and speaking about the child to all who were waiting for Jerusalem’s deliverance.

^ (Luke 3:15) Now the people were in expectation and all of them were reasoning in their hearts about John, “May he perhaps be the Christ?”

^ (Matt. 11:2, 3) But John, having heard in jail about the works of the Christ, sent his disciples 3 to ask him: “Are you the Coming One, or are we to expect a different one?”

^ (Luke 24:21) But we were hoping that this man was the one who was going to deliver Israel. Yes, and besides all these things, this is the third day since these things occurred.

^ (Acts 1:6) So when they had assembled, they asked him: “Lord, are you restoring the kingdom to Israel at this time?”

Wednesday, November 18

The naive person believes every word.—[Prov. 14:15].

We need to be especially cautious when we come across reports regarding Jehovah’s people. Never forget that Satan is the accuser of God’s faithful servants. ([Rev. 12:10]) Therefore, Jesus warned that opposers would “lyingly say every sort of wicked thing” against us. ([Matt. 5:11]) If we take that warning seriously, we will not be shocked when we hear outrageous statements about Jehovah’s people. Do you enjoy sending e-mails and text messages to your friends and acquaintances? If so, when you see a newly published story in the news media or hear an experience, you might feel like a news reporter who wants to be the first to break an exciting story. However, before you send that text message or e-mail, ask yourself: ‘Am I certain that the information I am about to spread is true? Do I really have the facts?’ If you are not certain, you could unwittingly circulate false information among our brotherhood. If in doubt, hit the delete key, not the send button. w18.08 3 ¶3; 4 ¶6-7

^ (Prov. 14:15) The naive* person believes every word, But the shrewd one ponders each step.

Or “inexperienced.”

^ (Rev. 12:10) I heard a loud voice in heaven say: “Now have come to pass the salvation and the power and the Kingdom of our God and the authority of his Christ, because the accuser of our brothers has been hurled down, who accuses them day and night before our God!

^ (Matt. 5:11) “Happy are you when people reproach* you and persecute you and lyingly say every sort of wicked thing against you for my sake.

Or “insult.”

Thursday, November 19

Practice giving, and people will give to you.—[Luke 6:38].

Jesus wants us to find happiness by being generous. Many people react favorably to generosity. Of course, not all respond positively, but when they do, their gratitude can start a chain reaction. So practice giving whether people seem to appreciate it or not. You never know how much good you can do with just one act of generosity. Truly generous people do not give in order to get something in return. Jesus had this in mind when he taught: “When you spread a feast, invite the poor, the crippled, the lame, the blind; and you will be happy, because they have nothing with which to repay you.” (Luke 14:13, 14) “The generous person will be blessed,” said one inspired writer. Another said: “Happy is anyone who shows consideration to the lowly one.” ([Prov. 22:9;][Ps. 41:1]) Indeed, we should give because we derive pleasure from helping others. w18.08 21-22 ¶15-16

^ (Luke 6:38) Practice giving, and people will give to you. They will pour into your laps a fine measure, pressed down, shaken together, and overflowing. For with the measure that you are measuring out, they will measure out to you in return.”

^ (Luke 14:13, 14) But when you spread a feast, invite the poor, the crippled, the lame, the blind; 14 and you will be happy, because they have nothing with which to repay you. For you will be repaid in the resurrection of the righteous ones.”

^ (Prov. 22:9) The generous person* will be blessed, For he shares his food with the poor.

Lit., “He with a good eye.”

^ (Ps. 41:1) Happy is anyone who shows consideration to the lowly one; Jehovah will rescue him in the day of calamity.

Friday, November 20

Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, and do not rely on your own understanding. In all your ways take notice of him, and he will make your paths straight.—[Prov. 3:5, 6].

Obtaining the facts and evaluating them accurately present a challenge today because of the abundance of low-quality information, reports filled with half-truths, and our own imperfection. What will help us with this challenging task? We must know and apply Bible principles. One such principle is that it is foolish and humiliating to reply to a matter before hearing the facts. ([Prov. 18:13]) Another Bible principle reminds us not to accept every word without question. ([Prov. 14:15]) And finally, no matter how much experience we have in Christian living, we must be careful not to lean on our own understanding. Bible principles will safeguard us if we are certain to use facts from reliable sources to draw good conclusions and to make wise decisions. w18.08 7 ¶19

^ (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

^ (Prov. 18:13) When anyone replies to a matter before he hears the facts, It is foolish and humiliating.

^ (Prov. 14:15) The naive* person believes every word, But the shrewd one ponders each step.

Or “inexperienced.”

Saturday, November 21

Should we not . . . submit ourselves to the Father of our spiritual life?—[Heb. 12:9].

By water baptism, we formally and publicly acknowledge Jehovah’s ownership of us and our willingness to subject ourselves to him. Jesus did something similar when at his baptism he, in effect, said to Jehovah: “To do your will, O my God, is my desire.” ([Ps. 40:7, 8], ftn.) How did Jehovah respond to Jesus’ baptism? The Bible account says: “After being baptized, Jesus immediately came up from the water; and look! the heavens were opened up, and he saw God’s spirit descending like a dove and coming upon him. Look! Also, a voice from the heavens said: ‘This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved.’” (Matt. 3:16, 17) Although Jesus already belonged to his heavenly Father, Jehovah was delighted to see his Son’s willingness to do His will exclusively. Jehovah is likewise pleased to accept our dedication, and he will honor us with his blessing.—[Ps. 149:4]. w18.07 23 ¶4-5

^ (Heb. 12:9) Furthermore, our human fathers* used to discipline us, and we gave them respect. Should we not more readily submit ourselves to the Father of our spiritual life and live?

Lit., “the fathers of our flesh.”

^ (Ps. 40:7, 8) Then I said: “Look, I have come. In the scroll* it is written about me.  8 To do your will, O my God, is my delight,* And your law is deep within me.

Lit., “the scroll of the book.”

Or “desire.”

^ (Matt. 3:16, 17) After being baptized, Jesus immediately came up from the water; and look! the heavens were opened up, and he saw God’s spirit descending like a dove and coming upon him. 17 Look! Also, a voice from the heavens said: “This is my Son, the beloved, whom I have approved.”

^ (Ps. 149:4) For Jehovah takes pleasure in his people. He adorns the meek with salvation.

Sunday, November 22

Must we bring out water for you from this crag?—[Num. 20:10].

By using the word “we,” Moses was likely referring to himself and Aaron. Those words indicated a gross lack of respect for Jehovah as the true Source of that miracle. This possibility seems to be confirmed by what we read at Psalm 106:32, 33: “They provoked Him at the waters of Meribah, and it went badly for Moses because of them. They embittered his spirit, and he spoke rashly with his lips.” ([Num. 27:14]) Whatever the case, Moses’ actions detracted from the honor due Jehovah. Speaking to Moses and Aaron, Jehovah said: “You both rebelled against my order.” ([Num. 20:24]) A serious sin indeed! Previously, Jehovah had denied a whole generation of Israelites entrance into the land of Canaan because of their rebelliousness. (Num. 14:26-30,[34]) So it was both appropriate and consistent for Jehovah to make the same judgment with regard to Moses because of his rebellious act. He was not allowed to enter the Promised Land. w18.07 14 ¶9, 12; 15 ¶13

^ (Num. 20:10) Then Moses and Aaron called the congregation together before the crag, and he said to them: “Hear, now, you rebels! Must we bring out water for you from this crag?”

^ (Ps. 106:32, 33) They provoked Him at the waters of Merʹi·bah,* And it went badly for Moses because of them. 33 They embittered his spirit, And he spoke rashly with his lips.

Meaning “Quarreling.”

^ (Num. 27:14) because when the assembly was quarreling with me in the wilderness of Zin, you rebelled against my order to sanctify me before them by means of the waters. These are the waters of Merʹi·bah at Kaʹdesh in the wilderness of Zin.”

^ (Num. 20:24) “Aaron will be gathered to his people.* He will not enter the land that I will give to the Israelites, because you both rebelled against my order regarding the waters of Merʹi·bah.

This is a poetic expression for death.

^ (Num. 14:26-30) Jehovah then said to Moses and Aaron: 27 “How much longer will this evil assembly keep up this murmuring against me? I have heard what the Israelites are murmuring against me. 28 Say to them, ‘“As surely as I live,” declares Jehovah, “I will do to you just what I have heard you speak! 29 In this wilderness your corpses will fall, yes, the whole number of you from 20 years old and up who were registered, all of you who have murmured against me. 30 None of you will enter into the land that I swore* to have you reside in except Caʹleb the son of Je·phunʹneh and Joshua the son of Nun.

Lit., “I lifted my hand.”

^ (Num. 14:34) According to the number of the days that you spied out the land, 40 days, a day for a year, a day for a year, you will answer for your errors 40 years, for you will know what it means to oppose me.*

Or “to have me as an enemy.”

Monday, November 23

It is best not to eat meat or drink wine or do anything over which your brother stumbles.—[Rom. 14:21].

Would you be willing to forgo things that are within your right if you could thus avoid stumbling a brother whose conscience differs from yours? No doubt you would. Before they came to a knowledge of the truth, some of our brothers abused alcohol, but now they are determined to abstain from it. Surely, none of us would want to contribute to a brother’s falling back into a course that would cause him great harm! (1 Cor. 6:9, 10) Therefore, it would be unloving for a host to pressure a brother to drink alcohol if he has declined to do so. While likely in his late teens or early 20’s, the young man Timothy submitted to painful circumcision in order to avoid stumbling Jews to whom he was going to preach. His attitude was similar to that of the apostle Paul. ([Acts 16:3;] 1 Cor. 9:19-23) Like Timothy, are you willing to make personal sacrifices for the good of others? w18.06 18-19 ¶12-13

^ (Rom. 14:21) It is best not to eat meat or drink wine or do anything over which your brother stumbles.

^ (1 Cor. 6:9, 10) Or do you not know that unrighteous people will not inherit God’s Kingdom? Do not be misled.* Those who are sexually immoral,* idolaters, adulterers, men who submit to homosexual acts, men who practice homosexuality,* 10 thieves, greedy people, drunkards, revilers,* and extortioners will not inherit God’s Kingdom.

Or “deceived.”

See Glossary, “Sexual immorality.”

Or “men who have sex with men.” Lit., “men who lie with men.”

Or “the verbally abusive.”

^ (Acts 16:3) Paul expressed the desire for Timothy to accompany him, and he took him and circumcised him because of the Jews in those places, for they all knew that his father was a Greek.

^ (1 Cor. 9:19-23) For though I am free from all people, I have made myself the slave to all, so that I may gain as many people as possible. 20 To the Jews I became as a Jew in order to gain Jews; to those under law I became as under law, though I myself am not under law, in order to gain those under law. 21 To those without law I became as without law, although I am not without law toward God but under law toward Christ, in order to gain those without law. 22 To the weak I became weak, in order to gain the weak. I have become all things to people of all sorts, so that I might by all possible means save some. 23 But I do all things for the sake of the good news, in order to share it with others.

Tuesday, November 24

I will change the language of the peoples to a pure language.—[Zeph. 3:9].

Jehovah draws those whom he allows to become members of his spiritual family, gently attracting honesthearted ones to true worship. ([John 6:44]) When you first meet someone who is not in the truth, what do you know about that person? Other than his name and physical appearance, probably very little. That is not the case when you first meet someone who knows and loves Jehovah. Even if that person is from a different background, country, tribe, or culture, you already know much about him—and he about you! For example, you quickly recognize each other’s “language”—the “pure language” of truth. As a result, you each know what the other believes about God, moral standards, and the hope for the future, to name just a few. Moreover, those are the most important things to know about a person, the things that build confidence and trust. They also form the basis for wholesome and enduring friendships. w18.12 21 ¶9-10

^ (Zeph. 3:9) For then I will change the language of the peoples to a pure language, So that all of them may call on the name of Jehovah, To serve him shoulder to shoulder.’*

Or “worship him in unity.”

^ (John 6:44) No man can come to me unless the Father, who sent me, draws him, and I will resurrect him on the last day.

Wednesday, November 25

Unless you get circumcised . . . , you cannot be saved.—[Acts 15:1].

Under Christ’s direction, the governing body made it clear that non-Jewish Christians did not need to be circumcised. (Acts 15:19, 20) But years after this decision, many Jewish believers continued to circumcise their children. We may wonder, though, ‘Why did Jesus allow this issue to remain unsettled for such a long time when his death had abolished the Mosaic Law?’ (Col. 2:13, 14) For some, it takes time to adjust to a clarification in understanding. Jewish Christians needed sufficient time to adjust their viewpoint. ([John 16:12]) Some found it hard to accept that circumcision was no longer a sign of a special relationship with God. ([Gen. 17:9-12]) Others, out of fear of persecution, were reluctant to stand out in Jewish communities. ([Gal. 6:12]) In time, though, Christ provided further guidance through inspired letters written by Paul.—Rom. 2:28, 29; Gal. 3:23-25. w18.10 24-25 ¶10-12

^ (Acts 15:1) Now some men came down from Ju·deʹa and began to teach the brothers: “Unless you get circumcised according to the custom of Moses, you cannot be saved.”

^ (Acts 15:19, 20) Therefore, my decision is not to trouble those from the nations who are turning to God, 20 but to write them to abstain from things polluted by idols, from sexual immorality, from what is strangled, and from blood.

^ (Col. 2:13, 14) Furthermore, though you were dead in your trespasses and in the uncircumcised state of your flesh, God made you alive together with him. He kindly forgave us all our trespasses 14 and erased* the handwritten document that consisted of decrees and was in opposition to us. He has taken it out of the way by nailing it to the torture stake.*

Or “blotted out.”

See Glossary.

^ (John 16:12) “I still have many things to say to you, but you are not able to bear them now.

^ (Gen. 17:9-12) God said further to Abraham: “As for you, you are to keep my covenant, you and your offspring* after you throughout their generations. 10 This is my covenant between me and you, that you and your offspring* after you will keep: Every male among you must get circumcised. 11 You must circumcise the flesh of your foreskins, and it will serve as a sign of the covenant between me and you. 12 Throughout your generations, every male among you eight days old must be circumcised, anyone who is born in the house and anyone who is not one of your offspring* and who was purchased with money from a foreigner.

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

^ (Gal. 6:12) All those who want to make a good impression in the flesh* are the ones who try to compel you to get circumcised, doing so only to avoid being persecuted for the torture stake* of the Christ.

Or “who want to look good outwardly.”

See Glossary.

^ (Rom. 2:28, 29) For he is not a Jew who is one on the outside, nor is circumcision something on the outside, on the flesh. 29 But he is a Jew who is one on the inside, and his circumcision is that of the heart by spirit and not by a written code. That person’s praise comes from God, not from people.

^ (Gal. 3:23-25) However, before the faith arrived, we were being guarded under law, being handed over into custody, looking to the faith that was about to be revealed. 24 So the Law became our guardian* leading to Christ, so that we might be declared righteous through faith. 25 But now that the faith has arrived, we are no longer under a guardian.*

Or “tutor.”

Or “tutor.”

Thursday, November 26

Caiaphas . . . had advised the Jews that it was to their benefit for one man to die in behalf of the people.—[John 18:14].

Caiaphas sent soldiers to arrest Jesus under the cover of night. Jesus was aware of this shameful strategy, so during his final meal with the apostles, he asked them to get some swords. Two would be sufficient to teach them a vital lesson. (Luke 22:36-38) Later that night, Peter used a sword to attack a member of the mob. No doubt, he was incensed at the injustice of Jesus’ nighttime arrest. ([John 18:10]) But Jesus told Peter: “Return your sword to its place, for all those who take up the sword will perish by the sword.” (Matt. 26:52, 53) This powerful lesson was in harmony with what Jesus prayed about earlier that night—they must be no part of the world. ([John 17:16]) Fighting injustice was something to be left to God. Consequently, we maintain our peace and unity. And as Jehovah observes our divided world, it must warm his heart to see the unity that exists among his people.—[Zeph. 3:17]. w18.06 7 ¶13-14, 16

^ (John 18:14) Caʹia·phas was, in fact, the one who had advised the Jews that it was to their benefit for one man to die in behalf of the people.

^ (Luke 22:36-38) Then he said to them: “But now let the one who has a money bag take it, likewise a food pouch, and let the one who has no sword sell his outer garment and buy one. 37 For I tell you that what is written must be accomplished in me, namely, ‘He was counted with lawless ones.’ For this is being fulfilled concerning me.” 38 Then they said: “Lord, look! here are two swords.” He said to them: “It is enough.”

^ (John 18:10) Then Simon Peter, who had a sword, drew it and struck the slave of the high priest, cutting off his right ear. The name of the slave was Malchus.

^ (Matt. 26:52, 53) Then Jesus said to him: “Return your sword to its place, for all those who take up the sword will perish by the sword. 53 Or do you think that I cannot appeal to my Father to supply me at this moment more than 12 legions of angels?

^ (John 17:16) They are no part of the world, just as I am no part of the world.

^ (Zeph. 3:17) Jehovah your God is in your midst. As a mighty One, he will save. He will exult over you with great joy. He will become silent* in his love. He will rejoice over you with shouts of joy.

Or “quiet; at ease; satisfied.”

Friday, November 27

The dragon became enraged at the woman and went off to wage war with the remaining ones of her offspring.—[Rev. 12:17].

In addition to offering bait, Satan tries to bully us into compromising our loyalty to Jehovah. For example, he can maneuver governments into banning our preaching work. Or he can prompt our associates at work or in school to mock us because of our desire to live by the Bible’s moral standards. ([1 Pet. 4:4]) He might also influence well-meaning family members to discourage us from attending meetings. ([Matt. 10:36]) How can we cope? First, we must expect this kind of direct assault—Satan is at war with us. ([Rev. 2:10]) Then, we need to see the bigger issue behind such incidents—Satan claims that we serve Jehovah only when it is convenient. He says that if we are pressured, we will turn our back on God. ([Job 1:9-11;][2:4, 5]) Finally, we have to rely on Jehovah for strength to face the issue. Remember, he will never abandon us.—[Heb. 13:5]. w18.05 26 ¶14

^ (Rev. 12:17) So the dragon became enraged at the woman and went off to wage war with the remaining ones of her offspring,* who observe the commandments of God and have the work of bearing witness concerning Jesus.

Lit., “seed.”

^ (1 Pet. 4:4) They are puzzled that you do not continue running with them in the same decadent course of debauchery, so they speak abusively of you.

^ (Matt. 10:36) Indeed, a man’s enemies will be those of his own household.

^ (Rev. 2:10) Do not be afraid of the things you are about to suffer. Look! The Devil will keep on throwing some of you into prison so that you may be fully put to the test, and you will have tribulation for ten days. Prove yourself faithful even to death, and I will give you the crown of life.

^ (Job 1:9-11) At that Satan answered Jehovah: “Is it for nothing that Job has feared God? 10 Have you not put up a protective hedge around him and his house and everything he has? You have blessed the work of his hands, and his livestock has spread out in the land. 11 But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike everything he has, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”

^ (Job 2:4, 5) But Satan answered Jehovah: “Skin for skin. A man will give everything that he has for his life.* 5 But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike his bone and flesh, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”

Or “soul.”

^ (Heb. 13:5) Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things. For he has said: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.”

Saturday, November 28

You do not know which will have success.—[Eccl. 11:6].

Even if it appears that the Kingdom message we preach is not reaching the hearts of people, we should not underestimate the impact of our sowing work. Granted, many people do not listen to us, but they do observe us. They notice our neat attire, polite behavior, and warm smile. In time, our conduct may help some to see that their negative views about us may not be correct after all. Sergio and Olinda, pioneers, relate: “Because of illness, we did not go to the square for a while. When we returned, passersby asked, ‘What happened? We missed you.’” Indeed, as long as we “do not let [our] hand rest” from sowing Kingdom seed, we have a valuable share in giving “a witness to all the nations.” ([Matt. 24:14]) Above all, we have the deep joy that comes from knowing that we have Jehovah’s approval, for he loves all those who “bear fruit with endurance”!—[Luke 8:15]. w18.05 16 ¶16-18

^ (Eccl. 11:6) Sow your seed in the morning and do not let your hand rest until the evening; for you do not know which will have success, whether this one or that one, or whether they will both do well.

^ (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ (Luke 8:15) As for that on the fine soil, these are the ones who, after hearing the word with a fine and good heart, retain it and bear fruit with endurance.

Sunday, November 29

Praised be the God . . . who encourages us in all our trials.—2 Cor. 1:3, 4, ftn.

Ever since humankind fell into sin and imperfection, Jehovah has proved that he is a God who gives encouragement. Immediately after the rebellion in Eden, he gave Adam’s future descendants reason to take courage. The prophetic promise written at [Genesis 3:15] would give humankind hope that eventually “the original serpent,” Satan the Devil, and all his evil works would be destroyed. ([Rev. 12:9;][1 John 3:8]) Jehovah’s servant Noah lived in an ungodly world where the only people who worshipped Jehovah were members of his family. With violence and sexual perversion rampant all around him, Noah could have become discouraged. ([Gen. 6:4, 5,][9,][11;][Jude 6]) But Jehovah told Noah that He was going to put an end to that wicked world and instructed him about what he must do to ensure his family’s safety. ([Gen. 6:13-18]) Jehovah proved to be for Noah a God of encouragement. w18.04 15 ¶1-2

^ (2 Cor. 1:3, 4) Praised be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of tender mercies and the God of all comfort, 4 who comforts* us in all our trials* so that we may be able to comfort others in any sort of trial* with the comfort that we receive from God.

Or “encourages.”

Or “tribulation.”

Or “tribulation.”

^ (Gen. 3:15) And I will put enmity* between you and the woman and between your offspring* and her offspring.* He will crush* your head, and you will strike* him in the heel.”

Or “hostility.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “bruise; strike.”

Or “bruise; crush.”

^ (Rev. 12:9) So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.

^ (1 John 3:8) The one who practices sin originates with the Devil, because the Devil has been sinning from the beginning.* For this purpose the Son of God was made manifest, to break up* the works of the Devil.

Or “from when he began.”

Or “destroy.”

^ (Gen. 6:4, 5) The Nephʹi·lim* were on the earth in those days and afterward. During that time the sons of the true God continued to have relations with the daughters of men, and these bore sons to them. They were the mighty ones of old times, the men of fame. 5 Consequently, Jehovah saw that man’s wickedness was great on the earth and that every inclination of the thoughts of his heart was only bad all the time.

Possibly meaning “The Fellers,” that is, those who cause others to fall down. See Glossary.

^ (Gen. 6:9) This is the history of Noah. Noah was a righteous man. He proved himself faultless* among his contemporaries.* Noah walked with the true God.

Or “blameless.”

Lit., “his generations.”

^ (Gen. 6:11) But the earth had become ruined in the sight of the true God, and the earth was filled with violence.

^ (Jude 6) And the angels who did not keep their original position but forsook their own proper dwelling place, he has reserved with eternal bonds in dense darkness for the judgment of the great day.

^ (Gen. 6:13-18) After that God said to Noah: “I have decided to put an end to all flesh, because the earth is full of violence on account of them, so I am bringing them to ruin together with the earth. 14 Make for yourself an ark* from resinous wood. You will make compartments in the ark and cover it with tar* inside and outside. 15 This is how you will make it: The ark should be 300 cubits* long, 50 cubits wide, and 30 cubits high. 16 You will make a window for light* for the ark, one cubit from the top. You should put the entrance of the ark in its side and make it with a lower deck, a second deck, and a third deck. 17 “As for me, I am going to bring floodwaters upon the earth to destroy from under the heavens all flesh that has the breath of life.* Everything on the earth will perish. 18 And I am establishing my covenant with you, and you must go into the ark, you, your sons, your wife, and your sons’ wives with you.

Lit., “a chest”; a large vessel.

Or “pitch.”

A cubit equaled 44.5 cm (17.5 in.). See App. B14.

Hebrew, tsoʹhar. Another view is that the tsoʹhar refers to a roof with a one-cubit pitch, or incline, rather than an opening for light or a window.

Or “the spirit of life.”

Monday, November 30

Keep encouraging one another and building one another up, just as you are in fact doing.—1 Thess. 5:11.

It would be an error on our part if we believed that we cannot be encouraging because we are not particularly communicative. It does not take much to be a source of encouragement—perhaps no more than a warm smile when greeting someone. If there is no smile in return, it could mean that there is a problem, and just listening to the other person may bring comfort. ([Jas. 1:19]) We all can be encouraging to a brother or a sister who is in need of comfort. King Solomon wrote: “A word spoken at the right time—how good it is! A cheerful glance makes the heart rejoice; a good report invigorates the bones.” ([Prov. 15:23,][30], ftn.) Paul shows that even singing a Kingdom song together can be a source of encouragement. ([Acts 16:25;][Col. 3:16]) Mutual encouragement will become more and more important as we see Jehovah’s day “drawing near.”—[Heb. 10:25]. w18.04 23 ¶16; 24 ¶18-19

^ (1 Thess. 5:11) Therefore, keep encouraging* one another and building one another up, just as you are in fact doing.

Or “comforting.”

^ (Jas. 1:19) Know this, my beloved brothers: Everyone must be quick to listen, slow to speak, slow to anger,

^ (Prov. 15:23) A man rejoices in giving the right answer,* And a word spoken at the right time—how good it is!

Lit., “in the answer of his mouth.”

^ (Prov. 15:30) Bright eyes make* the heart rejoice; A good report invigorates the bones.*

Or “A cheerful glance makes.”

Lit., “makes the bones fat.”

^ (Acts 16:25) But about the middle of the night, Paul and Silas were praying and praising God with song, and the prisoners were listening to them.

^ (Col. 3:16) Let the word of the Christ reside in you richly in all wisdom. Keep on teaching and encouraging* one another with psalms, praises to God, spiritual songs sung with gratitude,* singing in your hearts to Jehovah.*

Or “admonishing.”

Or “graciousness.”

See App. A5.

^ (Heb. 10:25) not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

December

Tuesday, December 1

He was moved with pity for them.—[Mark 6:34].

One of the most heartwarming aspects of Jesus’ personality is his ability to understand the challenges that we imperfect humans face. While on earth, Jesus was able to “rejoice with those who rejoice” and “weep with those who weep.” ([Rom. 12:15]) For example, when his 70 disciples returned with joy after completing a successful preaching assignment, Jesus “became overjoyed in the holy spirit.” (Luke 10:17-21) On the other hand, when he saw the effect that the death of Lazarus had on those who loved him, Jesus “groaned within himself and became troubled.” ([John 11:33]) What enabled this perfect man to be so merciful and compassionate in his dealings with sinful humans? First of all, Jesus loved people. He was “especially fond of the sons of men.” ([Prov. 8:31]) That love for people moved him to become thoroughly acquainted with the way humans think. The apostle John explains: “He knew what was in man.”—[John 2:25]. w19.03 20 ¶1-2

^ (Mark 6:34) Well, on getting out, he saw a large crowd, and he was moved with pity for them, because they were as sheep without a shepherd. And he started to teach them many things.

^ (Rom. 12:15) Rejoice with those who rejoice; weep with those who weep.

^ (Luke 10:17-21) Then the 70 returned with joy, saying: “Lord,* even the demons are made subject to us by the use of your name.” 18 At that he said to them: “I see Satan already fallen like lightning from heaven. 19 Look! I have given you the authority to trample underfoot serpents and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy, and nothing at all will harm you. 20 Nevertheless, do not rejoice because the spirits are made subject to you, but rejoice because your names have been written in the heavens.” 21 In that very hour he became overjoyed in the holy spirit and said: “I publicly praise you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have carefully hidden these things from wise and intellectual ones and have revealed them to young children. Yes, O Father, because this is the way you approved.

Or “Master.”

^ (John 11:33) When Jesus saw her weeping and the Jews who had come with her weeping, he groaned within himself and became troubled.

^ (Prov. 8:31) I rejoiced over his habitable earth, And I was especially fond of the sons of men.*

Or “mankind.”

^ (John 2:25) and because he did not need to have anyone bear witness about man, for he knew what was in man.

Wednesday, December 2

Strike everything he has, and he will surely curse you to your very face.—[Job 1:11].

Satan attacked Job’s belongings, robbing him of his wealth, his servants, and his reputation in the community. He attacked Job’s family, robbing him of his ten beloved children. Then he attacked Job’s body, robbing him of his health by afflicting him with painful boils that covered him from head to foot. Job’s wife was distraught and overwhelmed with grief; she urged him to give up, to curse God and die. Job himself wished for death, but still he kept his integrity. Then Satan tried a different method of attack. He used three men who were companions of Job. The men visited Job for days, but they offered no comfort. Instead they heartlessly lectured and scolded him. They claimed that God was behind his troubles and cared nothing about his integrity. They even suggested that Job was a wicked man who deserved the terrible things that were happening to him!—[Job 1:13-22;][2:7-11;][15:4, 5;][22:3-6;][25:4-6]. w19.02 4 ¶7-8

^ (Job 1:11) But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike everything he has, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”

^ (Job 1:13-22) Now on the day when his sons and daughters were eating and drinking wine in their oldest brother’s house, 14 a messenger came to Job and said: “The cattle were plowing and the donkeys were grazing beside them 15 when the Sa·beʹans attacked and took them, and they killed the servants with the sword. I am the only one who escaped to tell you.” 16 While he was still speaking, another one came and said: “Fire from God* fell from the heavens and blazed among the sheep and the servants and consumed them! I am the only one who escaped to tell you.” 17 While he was still speaking, another one came and said: “The Chal·deʹans formed three bands and made a raid on the camels and took them, and they killed the servants with the sword. I am the only one who escaped to tell you.” 18 While he was still speaking, yet another one came and said: “Your sons and your daughters were eating and drinking wine in their oldest brother’s house. 19 Suddenly a great wind came from the wilderness, and it struck the four corners of the house, so that it fell on the young people and they were killed. I am the only one who escaped to tell you.” 20 At that Job got up and ripped apart his garment and cut the hair off his head; then he fell to the ground and bowed down 21 and said: “Naked I came out of my mother’s womb, And naked I will return. Jehovah has given, and Jehovah has taken away. Let the name of Jehovah continue to be praised.” 22 In all of this, Job did not sin or accuse God of doing anything wrong.*

Or possibly, “Lightning.”

Or “ascribe anything improper to God.”

^ (Job 2:7-11) So Satan went out from the presence* of Jehovah and struck Job with painful boils* from the sole of his foot to the crown of his head. 8 And Job took a piece of broken pottery to scrape himself, and he was sitting among the ashes. 9 Finally his wife said to him: “Are you still holding firmly to your integrity? Curse God and die!” 10 But he said to her: “You are talking like one of the senseless women. Should we accept only what is good from the true God and not accept also what is bad?” In all of this, Job did not sin with his lips. 11 Three companions* of Job heard about all the calamities that had come upon him, and each came from his own place—Elʹi·phaz the Teʹman·ite, Bilʹdad the Shuʹhite, and Zoʹphar the Naʹa·ma·thite. So they agreed to meet together to go and sympathize with Job and comfort him.

Lit., “face.”

Or “with severe ulcers.”

Or “acquaintances.”

^ (Job 15:4, 5) For you undermine the fear of God, And you diminish any concern for God.  5 For your error dictates what you say,* And you choose crafty speech.

Or “your error trains your mouth.”

^ (Job 22:3-6) Does the Almighty care* that you are righteous, Or does he gain anything because you follow the course of integrity?  4 Will he punish you And enter into judgment with you for your reverence?  5 Is it not because your own wickedness is so great And there is no end to your errors?  6 For you seize a pledge from your brothers for no reason, And you strip people of their garments, leaving them naked.*

Or “Does it delight the Almighty.”

Lit., “strip off garments of the naked.”

^ (Job 25:4-6) So how can mortal man be righteous before God, Or how can one born of a woman be innocent?*  5 Even the moon is not bright And the stars are not pure in his eyes,  6 How much less so mortal man, who is a maggot, And a son of man, who is a worm!”

Or “pure.”

Thursday, December 3

The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom.—[Ps. 111:10].

Some kinds of fear are good for us. For example, we need to have a healthy fear of displeasing Jehovah. If Adam and Eve had developed that type of fear, they would not have rebelled against Jehovah. But they did rebel. After they did so, their eyes were opened in that they became fully aware that they were sinners. They could only pass sin and death on to their children. Because they could see, or understand, their condition, they became ashamed of their nakedness and covered themselves. ([Gen. 3:7,][21]) While we need to have a healthy fear of Jehovah, we do not need to have a morbid fear of death. Jehovah has made a way for us to gain everlasting life. If we commit a sin but are genuinely repentant, Jehovah will overlook our mistakes. He will forgive us in line with our faith in the ransom sacrifice of his Son. A primary way we show faith is by dedicating our life to God and getting baptized.—[1 Pet. 3:21]. w19.03 5-6 ¶12-13

^ (Ps. 111:10) The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom. All those observing his orders* show good insight. His praise endures forever.

Lit., “them.”

^ (Gen. 3:7) Then the eyes of both of them were opened, and they realized that they were naked. So they sewed fig leaves together and made loin coverings for themselves.

^ (Gen. 3:21) And Jehovah God made long garments from skins for Adam and for his wife, to clothe them.

^ (1 Pet. 3:21) Baptism, which corresponds to this, is also now saving you (not by the removing of the filth of the flesh, but by the request to God for a good conscience), through the resurrection of Jesus Christ.

Friday, December 4

There was not a man left of them except Caleb the son of Jephunneh and Joshua the son of Nun.—[Num. 26:65].

The Israelites had many reasons for showing appreciation. They were freed from slavery after Jehovah brought the Ten Plagues on Egypt. Then God saved them from disaster by destroying the entire Egyptian army in the Red Sea. The Israelites were so grateful that they sang a victory song of praises to Jehovah. But did they remain grateful? When the Israelites encountered new challenges, they soon forgot about all the good things Jehovah had done for them. They then revealed their lack of appreciation. ([Ps. 106:7]) How? “The entire assembly of the Israelites began to murmur against Moses and Aaron”—in reality, murmuring against Jehovah. ([Ex. 16:2,][8]) He was disappointed with the ungrateful attitude his people showed. He later foretold that this entire generation of Israelites would perish in the wilderness, with the exception of Joshua and Caleb.—Num. 14:22-24. w19.02 17 ¶12-13

^ (Num. 26:65) For Jehovah had said concerning them: “They will die without fail in the wilderness.” So there was not a man left of them except Caʹleb the son of Je·phunʹneh and Joshua the son of Nun.

^ (Ps. 106:7) Our forefathers in Egypt did not appreciate* your wonderful works. They did not remember your abundant loyal love, But they rebelled at the sea, by the Red Sea.

Or “grasp the meaning of.”

^ (Ex. 16:2) Then the entire assembly of the Israelites began to murmur against Moses and Aaron in the wilderness.

^ (Ex. 16:8) Moses continued: “When Jehovah gives you meat to eat in the evening and in the morning bread to satisfaction, you will see that Jehovah has heard your murmurings that you are murmuring against him. But who are we? Your murmurings are not against us, but against Jehovah.”

^ (Num. 14:22-24) However, not one of the men who have seen my glory and my signs that I performed in Egypt and in the wilderness and yet have kept testing me these ten times and have not listened to my voice 23 will ever see the land about which I swore to their fathers. No, not one of those treating me without respect will see it. 24 But because my servant Caʹleb had a different spirit and kept following after me wholeheartedly, I will certainly bring him into the land where he went, and his offspring will take possession of it.

Saturday, December 5

I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart.—[Matt. 11:29].

Jesus did not draw undue attention to himself by requiring an elaborate observance of his death. Instead, he told his disciples that once a year they should remember him by means of a simple meal. ([John 13:15;] 1 Cor. 11:23-25) The simple but appropriate meal shows that Jesus was not a proud person. We can be happy that humility is one of the outstanding qualities of our heavenly King. ([Phil. 2:5-8]) How can we imitate Jesus’ humility? By putting the interests of others ahead of our own. ([Phil. 2:3, 4]) Think back to the final night of Jesus’ earthly life. Jesus knew that he would soon experience a painful death; yet, he was deeply concerned about his faithful apostles, who would soon be grieving for him. So he spent the last night instructing, encouraging, and reassuring them. (John 14:25-31) Jesus humbly showed more concern for the welfare of others than for himself. What an excellent example he set for us! w19.01 21 ¶5-6

^ (Matt. 11:29) Take my yoke upon you and learn from me,* for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and you will find refreshment for yourselves.

Or “become my disciples (learners).”

^ (John 13:15) For I set the pattern for you, that just as I did to you, you should also do.

^ (1 Cor. 11:23-25) For I received from the Lord what I also handed on to you, that the Lord Jesus on the night on which he was going to be betrayed took a loaf, 24 and after giving thanks, he broke it and said: “This means my body, which is in your behalf. Keep doing this in remembrance of me.” 25 He did the same with the cup also, after they had the evening meal, saying: “This cup means the new covenant by virtue of my blood. Keep doing this, whenever you drink it, in remembrance of me.”

^ (Phil. 2:5-8) Keep this mental attitude in you that was also in Christ Jesus, 6 who, although he was existing in God’s form, gave no consideration to a seizure, namely, that he should be equal to God. 7 No, but he emptied himself and took a slave’s form and became human.* 8 More than that, when he came as a man,* he humbled himself and became obedient to the point of death, yes, death on a torture stake.*

Lit., “came to be in the likeness of men.”

Lit., “when he was found in appearance as a man.”

See Glossary.

^ (Phil. 2:3, 4) Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you, 4 as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (John 14:25-31) “I have spoken these things to you while I am still with you. 26 But the helper, the holy spirit, which the Father will send in my name, that one will teach you all things and bring back to your minds all the things I told you. 27 I leave you peace; I give you my peace. I do not give it to you the way that the world gives it. Do not let your hearts be troubled nor let them shrink out of fear. 28 You heard that I said to you, ‘I am going away and I am coming back to you.’ If you loved me, you would rejoice that I am going to the Father, for the Father is greater than I am. 29 So now I have told you before it occurs, so that you may believe when it does occur. 30 I will not speak with you much more, for the ruler of the world is coming, and he has no hold on me. 31 But for the world to know that I love the Father, I am doing just as the Father has commanded me to do. Get up, let us go from here.

Sunday, December 6

Please take pleasure in my voluntary offerings of praise, O Jehovah.—[Ps. 119:108].

Do you get a knot in your stomach each time you even think of raising your hand to comment? If so, you are not alone. The truth is that most of us feel some fear when we comment. Actually, those fears can be a good sign. They indicate that you are humble and view others as superior to you. Jehovah loves that quality. ([Ps. 138:6;][Phil. 2:3]) But Jehovah also wants you to praise him and to encourage your brothers and sisters at the meetings. (1 Thess. 5:11) He loves you and will give you the courage you need. Consider some Scriptural reminders. The Bible says that all of us make mistakes in what we say and how we say it. ([Jas. 3:2]) Jehovah does not expect us to be perfect, and neither do our brothers and sisters. (Ps. 103:12-14) They are our spiritual family, and they love us. (Mark 10:29, 30;[John 13:35]) They understand that our comments at times do not come out exactly right. w19.01 8 ¶3; 10-11 ¶10-11

^ (Ps. 119:108) Please take pleasure in my voluntary offerings of praise,* O Jehovah, And teach me your judgments.

Lit., “the voluntary offerings of my mouth.”

^ (Ps. 138:6) Though Jehovah is high, he takes note of the humble, But the haughty he knows only from a distance.

^ (Phil. 2:3) Do nothing out of contentiousness or out of egotism, but with humility* consider others superior to you,

Or “lowliness of mind.”

^ (1 Thess. 5:11) Therefore, keep encouraging* one another and building one another up, just as you are in fact doing.

Or “comforting.”

^ (Jas. 3:2) For we all stumble* many times. If anyone does not stumble in word, he is a perfect man, able to bridle also his whole body.

Or “make mistakes.”

^ (Ps. 103:12-14) As far off as the sunrise is from the sunset, So far off from us he has put our transgressions. 13 As a father shows mercy to his sons, Jehovah has shown mercy to those who fear him. 14 For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust.

^ (Mark 10:29, 30) Jesus said: “Truly I say to you, no one has left house or brothers or sisters or mother or father or children or fields for my sake and for the sake of the good news 30 who will not get 100 times more now in this period of time*—houses, brothers, sisters, mothers, children, and fields, with persecutions—and in the coming system of things, everlasting life.

Or “in the present time.”

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

Monday, December 7

Remember . . . your Grand Creator in the days of your youth.—[Eccl. 12:1].

In today’s world, that is not always easy. However, it is by no means impossible. Jehovah wants you to enjoy a truly successful and satisfying life. With God’s help, you can succeed, not just in your youth but throughout your life. To illustrate, consider a lesson we can learn from the Israelites’ conquest of the Promised Land. When the Israelites neared the Promised Land, God did not command them to sharpen their fighting skills or train for war. (Deut. 28:1, 2) Rather, he told them that they needed to obey his commandments and trust in him. ([Josh. 1:7-9]) From a human viewpoint, that advice would make no sense! But it was the very best advice, for Jehovah gave his people victory after victory over the Canaanites. (Josh. 24:11-13) Yes, obedience to God calls for faith, but that faith always leads to success. This truth does not change with the passing of time. It is just as valid today. w18.12 25 ¶3-4

^ (Eccl. 12:1) Remember, then, your Grand Creator in the days of your youth, before the days of distress* come and the years arrive when you will say: “I have no pleasure in them”;

Or “the calamitous days.”

^ (Deut. 28:1, 2) “And if you will without fail listen to the voice of Jehovah your God by being careful to do all his commandments that I am commanding you today, Jehovah your God will certainly put you high above all other nations of the earth. 2 All these blessings will come upon you and overtake you, because you keep listening to the voice of Jehovah your God:

^ (Josh. 1:7-9) “Only be courageous and very strong, and observe carefully the entire Law that Moses my servant commanded you. Do not deviate from it either to the right or to the left, so that you may act wisely wherever you go. 8 This book of the Law should not depart from your mouth, and you must read it in an undertone* day and night, in order to observe carefully all that is written in it; for then your way will be successful and then you will act wisely. 9 Have I not commanded you? Be courageous and strong. Do not be struck with terror or fear, for Jehovah your God is with you wherever you go.”

Or “meditate on it.”

^ (Josh. 24:11-13) “‘Then you crossed the Jordan and came to Jerʹi·cho. And the leaders* of Jerʹi·cho, the Amʹor·ites, the Perʹiz·zites, the Caʹnaan·ites, the Hitʹtites, the Girʹga·shites, the Hiʹvites, and the Jebʹu·sites fought against you, but I gave them into your hand. 12 So I sent the feeling of dejection* ahead of you, and it drove them out from before you—two kings of the Amʹor·ites. It was not by your sword and not by your bow. 13 Thus I gave you a land for which you had not toiled and cities that you had not built, and you settled in them. You are eating from vineyards and olive groves that you did not plant.’

Or possibly, “landowners.”

Or possibly, “panic; terror.”

Tuesday, December 8

Lord, whom shall we go away to? You have sayings of everlasting life.—[John 6:68].

Some today have been stumbled by an adjusted understanding of a Bible passage. Others have taken sides with apostates and other opposers who misrepresent our beliefs. As a result, some have deliberately begun “drawing away” from Jehovah and the congregation. ([Heb. 3:12-14]) How much better it would have been if they had maintained their faith and kept their confidence in Jesus, as the apostle Peter did! Others have left the truth gradually, perhaps without even noticing what was happening. A person who gradually leaves the truth is like a boat that slowly slips away from the riverbank. The Bible describes such a slow change as ‘drifting away.’ ([Heb. 2:1]) Unlike one who intentionally draws away from the truth, one who drifts away does not do so deliberately. However, such a person strains his relationship with Jehovah and is in danger of losing it. w18.11 9 ¶5-6

^ (John 6:68) Simon Peter answered him: “Lord, whom shall we go away to? You have sayings of everlasting life.

^ (Heb. 3:12-14) Beware, brothers, for fear there should ever develop in any one of you a wicked heart lacking faith by drawing away from the living God; 13 but keep on encouraging one another each day, as long as it is called “Today,” so that none of you should become hardened by the deceptive power of sin. 14 For we actually become partakers of* the Christ only if we hold firmly down to the end the confidence we had at the beginning.

Or “have a sharing with.”

^ (Heb. 2:1) That is why it is necessary for us to pay more than the usual attention to the things we have heard, so that we never drift away.

Wednesday, December 9

Your people will offer themselves willingly.—[Ps. 110:3].

Do you desire to receive further training so as to be better equipped to carry out your sacred service? If so, you may qualify to attend the School for Kingdom Evangelizers. This school gives training to spiritually-minded men and women who are in full-time service, so that they can expand theocratic interests in the field. Those who apply to attend this school need to be willing to accept any assignment when they graduate. Would you be willing to take advantage of this opportunity to reach out for greater privileges of service? ([1 Cor. 9:23]) As Jehovah’s people, we are moved to be generous—which is a manifestation of goodness, kindness, and love—and to care about others each day. When we do that, we gain joy, peace, and happiness. (Gal. 5:22, 23) Whatever your circumstances in life, you can find joy by imitating Jehovah’s generous personality and by being one of his precious fellow workers!—Prov. 3:9, 10. w18.08 27 ¶16-18

^ (Ps. 110:3) Your people will offer themselves willingly on the day of your military force.* In splendid holiness, from the womb of the dawn, You have your company of young men just like dewdrops.

Or “on the day your army mobilizes.”

^ (1 Cor. 9:23) But I do all things for the sake of the good news, in order to share it with others.

^ (Gal. 5:22, 23) On the other hand, the fruitage of the spirit is love, joy, peace, patience,* kindness, goodness, faith, 23 mildness, self-control. Against such things there is no law.

Or “long-suffering.”

^ (Prov. 3:9, 10) Honor Jehovah with your valuable things, With the firstfruits* of all your produce;* 10 Then your storehouses will be completely filled, And your vats* will overflow with new wine.

Or “very best.”

Or “income.”

Or “winepresses.”

Thursday, December 10

What God has yoked together, let no man put apart.—[Matt. 19:6].

Someone might ask, ‘Is there ever a basis for a Christian to divorce and remarry?’ Well, Jesus stated his view on divorce: “Whoever divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery against her, and if ever a woman after divorcing her husband marries another, she commits adultery.” (Mark 10:11, 12;[Luke 16:18]) Clearly, Jesus thus honored marriage and wanted others to do so. A man divorcing his faithful wife (or a woman, her faithful husband) on some pretext and marrying another was committing adultery. This is true because merely divorcing one’s mate does not end the marriage. In God’s eyes, the two would still be “one flesh.” Moreover, Jesus said that a man’s divorcing his innocent wife would make her subject to adultery. How so? Back then, a divorced woman might feel compelled to remarry in order to gain financial support. Such a remarriage would amount to adultery. w18.12 11 ¶8-9

^ (Matt. 19:6) So that they are no longer two, but one flesh. Therefore, what God has yoked together, let no man put apart.”

^ (Mark 10:11, 12) He said to them: “Whoever divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery against her, 12 and if ever a woman after divorcing her husband marries another, she commits adultery.”

^ (Luke 16:18) “Everyone who divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery, and whoever marries a woman divorced from her husband commits adultery.

Friday, December 11

At my guardpost I will keep standing.—[Hab. 2:1].

Habakkuk’s conversation with Jehovah gave him a calm heart. So he resolved to keep waiting confidently on Jehovah to act. This was not just a spur-of-the-moment reaction, for he repeated his resolve when he later said that he would “quietly wait for the day of distress.” ([Hab. 3:16]) What does Habakkuk’s resolve teach us? First, we must never stop praying to Jehovah, no matter what trials befall us. Second, we need to listen to what Jehovah tells us through his Word and organization. Third, we should patiently wait on Jehovah, fully trusting that he will relieve our pains in his own time. If we continue to talk intimately with Jehovah and listen to him with a waiting attitude, as Habakkuk did, we too will gain a calm heart, which will help us to endure. Our hope will strengthen our patience, which in turn will help us to rejoice despite all the adversities we may face. Hope gives us confidence that our heavenly Father will act.—[Rom. 12:12]. w18.11 15-16 ¶11-12

^ (Hab. 2:1) At my guardpost I will keep standing, And I will station myself on the rampart. I will keep watch to see what he will speak by means of me And what I will reply when I am reproved.

^ (Hab. 3:16) I heard and I trembled within;* At the sound my lips quivered. Rottenness entered my bones; My legs beneath me were shaking. But I quietly wait for the day of distress, For it is coming upon the people who attack us.

Lit., “and my belly trembled.”

^ (Rom. 12:12) Rejoice in the hope. Endure under tribulation. Persevere in prayer.

Saturday, December 12

Women should adorn themselves in appropriate dress, with modesty and soundness of mind.—[1 Tim. 2:9].

What is God’s view of stumbling others? Jesus said: “Whoever stumbles one of these little ones who have faith, it would be better for him if a millstone that is turned by a donkey were put around his neck and he were pitched into the sea.” ([Mark 9:42]) Those words express strong feelings! Since Jesus perfectly reflected his Father’s personality, we can be sure that Jehovah feels just as strongly about anyone whose callous actions stumble one of Jesus’ followers. ([John 14:9]) Do we share the view of Jehovah and Jesus? Have we made it our own? What do our actions reveal? For instance, suppose we are attracted to a certain style of dress or grooming that is likely to upset some in the congregation or that may well arouse passion in the minds of others. Will our loving concern for fellow believers override our personal preferences in style? w18.11 25 ¶9-10

^ (1 Tim. 2:9) Likewise, the women should adorn themselves in appropriate* dress, with modesty and soundness of mind,* not with styles of hair braiding and gold or pearls or very expensive clothing,

Or “respectable.”

Or “good judgment; sensibleness.”

^ (Mark 9:42) But whoever stumbles one of these little ones who have faith, it would be better for him if a millstone that is turned by a donkey were put around his neck and he were pitched into the sea.

^ (John 14:9) Jesus said to him: “Even after I have been with you men for such a long time, Philip, have you not come to know me? Whoever has seen me has seen the Father also. How is it you say, ‘Show us the Father’?

Sunday, December 13

Satan answered Jehovah: “Is it for nothing that Job has feared God? . . . Stretch out your hand and strike everything he has, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”—[Job 1:9,][11].

What makes integrity so vital that each of us needs it? You need integrity because Satan has challenged Jehovah, and he has challenged you. That rebellious angel smeared Jehovah’s good name by implying that God is a bad, selfish, and dishonest Ruler. Sadly, Adam and Eve sided with Satan, rebelling against Jehovah. ([Gen. 3:1-6]) Life in Eden had given them countless opportunities to strengthen their love for Jehovah. But at the time of Satan’s challenge, their love was not complete, sound, or whole. Another question arose: Would any humans remain loyal to Jehovah God out of love for him? In other words, are humans capable of showing integrity? That question came to the fore in the case of Job. ([Job 1:8-11]) Like us, the man was imperfect. He made mistakes. However, Jehovah loved Job for his integrity. w19.02 3-4 ¶6-7

^ (Job 1:9) At that Satan answered Jehovah: “Is it for nothing that Job has feared God?

^ (Job 1:11) But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike everything he has, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”

^ (Gen. 3:1-6) Now the serpent was the most cautious* of all the wild animals of the field that Jehovah God had made. So it said to the woman: “Did God really say that you must not eat from every tree of the garden?” 2 At this the woman said to the serpent: “We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden. 3 But God has said about the fruit of the tree that is in the middle of the garden: ‘You must not eat from it, no, you must not touch it; otherwise you will die.’” 4 At this the serpent said to the woman: “You certainly will not die. 5 For God knows that in the very day you eat from it, your eyes will be opened and you will be like God, knowing good and bad.” 6 Consequently, the woman saw that the tree was good for food and that it was something desirable to the eyes, yes, the tree was pleasing to look at. So she began taking of its fruit and eating it. Afterward, she also gave some to her husband when he was with her, and he began eating it.

Or “shrewdest; craftiest.”

^ (Job 1:8-11) And Jehovah said to Satan: “Have you taken note of* my servant Job? There is no one like him on the earth. He is an upright man of integrity,* fearing God and shunning what is bad.” 9 At that Satan answered Jehovah: “Is it for nothing that Job has feared God? 10 Have you not put up a protective hedge around him and his house and everything he has? You have blessed the work of his hands, and his livestock has spread out in the land. 11 But, for a change, stretch out your hand and strike everything he has, and he will surely curse you to your very face.”

Lit., “set your heart upon.”

Or “a blameless and upright man.”

Monday, December 14

He . . . sold all the things he had and bought it.—[Matt. 13:46].

To show how precious the truth of God’s Kingdom is to those who find it, Jesus told about a traveling merchant who was searching for fine pearls. He found one of such high value that he “promptly sold” everything he had to buy it. (Matt. 13:45, 46) Similarly, the truth we found—the truth of God’s Kingdom and all the other precious truths we learned from God’s Word—is of such high value to us that we willingly and promptly made the sacrifices needed to obtain it. As long as we value the truth, we will “never sell it.” ([Prov. 23:23]) Sadly, though, some of God’s people have lost sight of the value of the truth they obtained—and have even sold it. May that never happen to us! To show that we deeply treasure the truth and that we would never sell it, we must heed the Bible’s admonition to “go on walking in the truth.” ([3 John 2-4]) To walk in the truth involves living it—giving it priority in our lives and conducting ourselves in harmony with it. w18.11 9 ¶3

^ (Matt. 13:46) Upon finding one pearl of high value, he went away and promptly sold all the things he had and bought it.

^ (Matt. 13:45, 46) “Again the Kingdom of the heavens is like a traveling merchant seeking fine pearls. 46 Upon finding one pearl of high value, he went away and promptly sold all the things he had and bought it.

^ (Prov. 23:23) Buy* truth and never sell it, Also wisdom and discipline and understanding.

Or “Acquire.”

^ (3 John 2-4) Beloved one, I pray that in all things you continue to prosper and enjoy good health, just as you are* now prospering. 3 For I rejoiced very much when brothers came and bore witness about the truth you hold, as you go on walking in the truth. 4 No greater joy* do I have than this: that I should hear that my children go on walking in the truth.

Or “your soul is.”

Or possibly, “cause for thankfulness.”

Tuesday, December 15

By faith the walls of Jericho fell down after the people had marched around them for seven days.—[Heb. 11:30].

The Israelites were commanded not to attack Jericho but to march around the city once a day for six days and seven times on the seventh day. Some soldiers may have thought, ‘What a waste of time and energy!’ But Israel’s invisible Leader knew exactly what he was doing. Not only did his strategy strengthen the faith of the Israelites but it also spared them direct confrontation with Jericho’s mighty warriors. ([Josh. 6:2-5]) What can we learn from this account? We may not at times fully comprehend the reasons for new initiatives put forth by the organization. For example, we may at first have questioned the use of electronic devices for personal study, in the ministry, and at the meetings. Now we likely realize the benefits of using them if possible. When we see the positive results of such advancements despite any doubts we might have had, we grow in faith and unity. w18.10 23 ¶8-9

^ (Heb. 11:30) By faith the walls of Jerʹi·cho fell down after the people had marched around them for seven days.

^ (Josh. 6:2-5) Jehovah then said to Joshua: “See, I have handed over to you Jerʹi·cho and its king and its mighty warriors. 3 All you fighting men should march around the city, going around the city once. That is what you should do for six days. 4 Have seven priests carry seven ram’s horns before the Ark. But on the seventh day, you should march around the city seven times and the priests should blow the horns. 5 When the ram’s horn is sounded—as soon as you hear the sound* of the horn—all the people should shout a great war cry. Then the wall of the city will fall down flat, and the people must go up, each one straight ahead.”

Or “long blast.”

Wednesday, December 16

Lord, are you restoring the kingdom to Israel at this time?—[Acts 1:6].

Expectations about the Messiah, such as those held by Jesus’ disciples, doubtless led the people of Galilee to want Jesus to become their king. We can imagine that they were thinking that Jesus would be an ideal leader. He was an outstanding speaker; he could cure the sick; he could even supply food for the hungry. After Jesus fed about 5,000 men, he sensed the mood among the people. “Jesus, knowing that they were about to come and seize him to make him king, withdrew again to the mountain all alone.” ([John 6:10-15]) The following day on the other side of the Sea of Galilee, the enthusiasm may have died down some. Jesus then explained to the crowd the true nature of his work. He had come to bring spiritual, not material, benefits to the nation. “Work, not for the food that perishes, but for the food that remains for everlasting life,” he told them.—[John 6:25-27]. w18.06 4 ¶4-5

^ (Acts 1:6) So when they had assembled, they asked him: “Lord, are you restoring the kingdom to Israel at this time?”

^ (John 6:10-15) Jesus said: “Have the people sit down.” As there was a lot of grass in that place, the men sat down there, about 5,000 in number. 11 Jesus took the bread, and after giving thanks, he distributed it to those who were sitting there; he did likewise with the small fish, and they had as much as they wanted. 12 But when they had eaten their fill, he said to his disciples: “Gather together the fragments left over, so that nothing is wasted.” 13 So they gathered them together and filled 12 baskets with fragments left over by those who had eaten from the five barley loaves. 14 When the people saw the sign he performed, they began to say: “This really is the Prophet who was to come into the world.” 15 Then Jesus, knowing that they were about to come and seize him to make him king, withdrew again to the mountain all alone.

^ (John 6:25-27) When they found him across the sea, they said to him: “Rabbi, when did you get here?” 26 Jesus answered them: “Most truly I say to you, you are looking for me, not because you saw signs, but because you ate from the loaves and were satisfied. 27 Work, not for the food that perishes, but for the food that remains for everlasting life, which the Son of man will give you; for on this one the Father, God himself, has put his seal of approval.”

Thursday, December¬Ý17

No crushed reed will he break, and no smoldering wick will he extinguish.‚Äã‚Äî[Isa. 42:3].

Jesus understood the feelings of those who were figuratively like a bruised reed or the wick of an oil lamp about to go out. As a result, he was considerate, kind, and patient. ([Mark 10:14]) Of course, we do not have Jesus‚Äô insight and teaching ability! But we can‚Äã‚Äîand should‚Äî‚Äãbe considerate of the people in our territory. That includes how we speak to them, when we do so, and for how long. Today, countless millions have been ‚Äúskinned and thrown about‚Äù by corrupt and heartless commercial, political, and religious leaders. ([Matt. 9:36]) As a result, many people are cynical and without hope. How important, then, that we be kind and compassionate in our choice of words and also in our tone of voice! Indeed, many are drawn to our message not only because of our Bible knowledge or sound reasoning but also because of our genuine interest in them and our thoughtful manner. w18.09 31-32 ¬∂13-14

^ (Isa. 42:3) No crushed reed will he break, And no smoldering wick will he extinguish. In faithfulness he will bring justice.

^ (Mark 10:14) At seeing this, Jesus was indignant and said to them: ‚ÄúLet the young children come to me; do not try to stop them, for the Kingdom of God belongs to such ones.

^ (Matt. 9:36) On seeing the crowds, he felt pity for them, because they were skinned and thrown about like sheep without a shepherd.

Saturday, December 19

[Epaphras] is always exerting himself in your behalf in his prayers.—[Col. 4:12].

Epaphras knew the brothers well, and he cared for them deeply. His situation as Paul’s “fellow captive” did not blind him to the spiritual needs of others. ([Philem. 23]) And he did something about it. Is that not a mark of unselfish concern? Praying for our fellow servants of Jehovah has real force, especially when we remember them individually, such as by name. ([2 Cor. 1:11;][Jas. 5:16]) Think of those whom you can pray for by name. Like Epaphras, many of our brothers and sisters are praying for those in their congregation and for families who are carrying a heavy load of responsibility or who are facing serious decisions or temptations. In addition, we do well to remember those who have lost loved ones in death, those who have survived recent disasters and wars, and those who are enduring economic crises. Clearly, there are many brothers and sisters who need our prayers and who can benefit from them. w18.09 5-6 ¶12-13

^ (Col. 4:12) Epʹa·phras, a slave of Christ Jesus who is from among you, sends you his greetings. He is always exerting himself in your behalf in his prayers, so that you may finally stand complete and with firm conviction in all the will of God.

^ (Philem. 23) Sending you greetings is Epʹa·phras, my fellow captive in union with Christ Jesus,

^ (2 Cor. 1:11) You also can help us by your supplication for us, in order that many may give thanks in our behalf for the favor we receive in answer to the prayers of many.*

Or “because of many prayerful faces.”

^ (Jas. 5:16) Therefore, openly confess your sins to one another and pray for one another, so that you may be healed. A righteous man’s supplication has a powerful effect.*

Lit., “has much force when it is at work.”

Sunday, December 20

There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.—[Acts 20:35].

Paul was referring not only to sharing material things but also to giving encouragement, guidance, and assistance to those in need of these. (Acts 20:31-35) By word and example, the apostle taught us to give of ourselves—our time, our energy, our attention, our love. Researchers in the field of social sciences have also observed that giving makes people happy. According to one article, “people report a significant happiness boost after doing kind deeds for others.” Helping others, researchers say, is important to developing “a greater sense of purpose and meaning” in life “because it fulfills basic human needs.” Hence, experts often recommend that people volunteer for public service to enhance their own health and happiness. This comes as no surprise to those who accept the Bible as the Word of mankind’s loving Designer, Jehovah.—2 Tim. 3:16, 17. w18.08 22 ¶17-18

^ (Acts 20:35) I have shown you in all things that by working hard in this way, you must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

^ (Acts 20:31-35) “Therefore keep awake, and bear in mind that for three years, night and day, I never stopped admonishing each one of you with tears. 32 And now I entrust you to God and to the word of his undeserved kindness, which word can build you up and give you the inheritance among all the sanctified ones. 33 I have desired no man’s silver or gold or clothing. 34 You yourselves know that these hands have provided for my own needs and the needs of those with me. 35 I have shown you in all things that by working hard in this way, you must assist those who are weak and must keep in mind the words of the Lord Jesus, when he himself said: ‘There is more happiness in giving than there is in receiving.’”

^ (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

Monday, December 21

Stop judging by the outward appearance, but judge with righteous judgment.—[John 7:24].

Through his prophecy about our Lord Jesus Christ, Isaiah warms and reassures our hearts. Isaiah foretold that Jesus would “not judge by what appears to his eyes, nor reprove simply according to what his ears hear.” He would “judge the lowly with fairness.” ([Isa. 11:3, 4]) Why is this encouraging? Because we live in a world filled with bias and prejudice. We all long for the perfect Judge, who will never judge us by our outward appearance! Each day we make judgments about people. Yet, as imperfect humans, we are not able to judge matters perfectly as Jesus does. We tend to be influenced by what appears to our eyes. Nonetheless, when Jesus was on earth, he commanded us, not to judge by “the outward appearance,” but to judge “with righteous judgment.” Clearly, Jesus wants us to be like him and not judge others by their outward appearance. w18.08 8 ¶1-2

^ (John 7:24) Stop judging by the outward appearance, but judge with righteous judgment.”

^ (Isa. 11:3, 4) And he will find delight in the fear of Jehovah. He will not judge by what appears to his eyes, Nor reprove simply according to what his ears hear.  4 He will judge the lowly with fairness,* And with uprightness he will give reproof in behalf of the meek ones of the earth. He will strike the earth with the rod of his mouth And put the wicked to death with the breath* of his lips.

Or “righteousness.”

Or “spirit.”

Tuesday, December 22

[You] will hear a word behind you saying, “This is the way. Walk in it.”—[Isa. 30:21].

True, we do not hear God speak to us from heaven. He has, however, provided his written Word, the Bible, in which he gives us instruction. Additionally, Jehovah’s spirit moves “the faithful steward” to keep giving His servants their food supply. ([Luke 12:42]) What an abundance of spiritual food we receive in the form of printed and online material, videos, and audio publications! May God’s own words, as recorded in the Bible, give us confidence that Jehovah has everything under control and that he will reverse any damage brought on us by Satan and his wicked world. And may we be determined to listen intently to Jehovah’s voice. If we do, we will successfully endure whatever problems we now face and any challenges that are yet to come. The Bible reminds us: “You need endurance, so that after you have done the will of God, you may receive the fulfillment of the promise.”—[Heb. 10:36]. w19.03 13 ¶17-18

^ (Isa. 30:21) And your own ears will hear a word behind you saying, “This is the way. Walk in it,” in case you should go to the right or in case you should go to the left.

^ (Luke 12:42) And the Lord said: “Who really is the faithful steward, the discreet one, whom his master will appoint over his body of attendants to keep giving them their measure of food supplies at the proper time?

^ (Heb. 10:36) For you need endurance, so that after you have done the will of God, you may receive the fulfillment of the promise.

Wednesday, December 23

Jehovah said to Joshua . . . : “Moses my servant is dead. Now get up, cross the Jordan, you and all this people.”—[Josh. 1:1, 2].

Because Moses had been Israel’s leader for so long, Joshua may have wondered how God’s people would respond to his leadership. ([Deut. 34:8,][10-12]) One Bible reference work, referring to Joshua 1:1, 2, notes: “In both ancient and modern times a transition of leadership is one of the most precarious times in the security of a state.” Joshua must have had legitimate fears, but within a few days, he took decisive action. ([Josh. 1:9-11]) His trust in God was not misplaced. As the Bible record shows, Jehovah actually guided Joshua and His people, Israel, by means of an angelic representative. It is reasonable to think that this angel was the Word, God’s firstborn Son. (Ex. 23:20-23;[John 1:1]) With Jehovah’s help, Israel successfully navigated the transition from Moses’ leadership to that of Joshua. w18.10 22-23 ¶1-4

^ (Josh. 1:1, 2) After the death of Moses the servant of Jehovah, Jehovah said to Joshua* the son of Nun, the minister of Moses: 2 “Moses my servant is dead. Now get up, cross the Jordan, you and all this people, and go into the land that I am giving to them, to the people of Israel.

Or “Jehoshua,” meaning “Jehovah Is Salvation.”

^ (Deut. 34:8) The people of Israel wept for Moses on the desert plains of Moʹab for 30 days. Then the days of weeping and mourning for Moses were completed.

^ (Deut. 34:10-12) But there has never again arisen a prophet in Israel like Moses, whom Jehovah knew face-to-face. 11 He performed all the signs and the miracles that Jehovah had sent him to do in the land of Egypt to Pharʹaoh and all his servants and all his land, 12 along with the mighty hand and the awesome power that Moses displayed before the eyes of all Israel.

^ (Josh. 1:1, 2) After the death of Moses the servant of Jehovah, Jehovah said to Joshua* the son of Nun, the minister of Moses: 2 “Moses my servant is dead. Now get up, cross the Jordan, you and all this people, and go into the land that I am giving to them, to the people of Israel.

Or “Jehoshua,” meaning “Jehovah Is Salvation.”

^ (Josh. 1:9-11) Have I not commanded you? Be courageous and strong. Do not be struck with terror or fear, for Jehovah your God is with you wherever you go.” 10 Then Joshua commanded the officers of the people: 11 “Pass throughout the camp and give this command to the people, ‘Get provisions ready, because in three days you will cross the Jordan to go in and take possession of the land that Jehovah your God is giving you to possess.’”

^ (Ex. 23:20-23) “I am sending an angel ahead of you to guard you on the way and to bring you into the place that I have prepared. 21 Pay attention to him, and obey his voice. Do not rebel against him, for he will not pardon your transgressions, because my name is in him. 22 However, if you strictly obey his voice and do all that I say, I will show hostility to your enemies and oppose those who oppose you. 23 For my angel will go ahead of you and will bring you to the Amʹor·ites, the Hitʹtites, the Perʹiz·zites, the Caʹnaan·ites, the Hiʹvites, and the Jebʹu·sites, and I will annihilate them.

^ (John 1:1) In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was a god.

Thursday, December 24

A book of remembrance was written before him for those fearing Jehovah.—[Mal. 3:16].

Jehovah recognizes those who willingly serve him, and he writes their names in his “book of remembrance.” Having our name inscribed in Jehovah’s “book of remembrance” as his people comes with certain obligations. Malachi specifically stated that we must ‘fear Jehovah and meditate on his name.’ Giving our worshipful devotion to anyone or anything else would result in our name being removed from Jehovah’s figurative book of life. ([Ex. 32:33;][Ps. 69:28]) Hence, our dedication to Jehovah involves much more than a solemn promise to do his will and to submit to water baptism. These actions are brief, and they quickly become part of the past. Our stand on Jehovah’s side as his people requires an ongoing demonstration of our obedience to him both in the present and in the future—for as long as we live.—1 Pet. 4:1, 2. w18.07 23-24 ¶7-9

^ (Mal. 3:16) At that time those who fear Jehovah spoke with one another, each one with his companion, and Jehovah kept paying attention and listening. And a book of remembrance was written before him for those fearing Jehovah and for those meditating on* his name.

Or “thinking on.” Or possibly, “treasuring.”

^ (Ex. 32:33) However, Jehovah said to Moses: “Whoever has sinned against me, I will wipe him out of my book.

^ (Ps. 69:28) Let them be erased from the book of the living,* And may they not be enrolled among the righteous.

Or “book of life.”

^ (1 Pet. 4:1, 2) Since Christ suffered in the flesh, you too arm yourselves with the same mental disposition;* because the person who has suffered in the flesh has desisted from sins, 2 so that he may live the remainder of his time in the flesh, no more for the desires of men, but for God’s will.

Or “resolve; determination.”

Friday, December 25

Now that we have moved beyond the primary doctrine about the Christ, let us press on to maturity.—[Heb. 6:1].

This does not happen automatically. We need to “press on,” or keep working at it. Growing to maturity involves advancing to an increased level of knowledge and insight. That is why we have repeatedly been encouraged to read a portion of the Bible daily. ([Ps. 1:1-3]) Have you made that a personal goal? Doing such reading can give you greater insight into Jehovah’s laws and principles and a deeper understanding of God’s Word. The foremost law for Christians is the law of love. Jesus told his disciples: “By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.” ([John 13:35]) Jesus’ half brother James called love “the royal law.” ([Jas. 2:8]) Paul said: “Love is the law’s fulfillment.” ([Rom. 13:10]) This emphasis on love is not surprising, since the Bible tells us that “God is love.”—[1 John 4:8]. w18.06 19 ¶14-15

^ (Heb. 6:1) Therefore, now that we have moved beyond the primary doctrine about the Christ, let us press on to maturity, not laying a foundation again, namely, repentance from dead works and faith in God,

^ (Ps. 1:1-3) Happy is the man who does not walk according to the advice of the wicked And does not stand on the path of sinners And does not sit in the seat of scoffers.  2 But his delight is in the law of Jehovah, And he reads His law in an undertone* day and night.  3 He will be like a tree planted by streams of water, A tree that produces fruit in its season, The foliage of which does not wither. And everything he does will succeed.

Or “he meditates on His law.”

^ (John 13:35) By this all will know that you are my disciples—if you have love among yourselves.”

^ (Jas. 2:8) If, now, you carry out the royal* law according to the scripture, “You must love your neighbor as yourself,” you are doing quite well.

Or “kingly.”

^ (Rom. 13:10) Love does not work evil to one’s neighbor; therefore, love is the law’s fulfillment.

^ (1 John 4:8) Whoever does not love has not come to know God, because God is love.

Saturday, December 26

They embittered his spirit, and he spoke rashly with his lips.—[Ps. 106:33].

Although the Israelites provoked Jehovah, it was Moses who became embittered. His lack of self-control led him to speak without considering the consequences. Moses allowed the actions of others to distract him from keeping his eyes fixed on Jehovah. Moses handled the first incident correctly. ([Ex. 7:6]) Yet, it is possible that after dealing for decades with the rebellious Israelites, he had become tired and frustrated. Was Moses thinking mainly of his own feelings instead of how he could glorify Jehovah? If such a faithful prophet as Moses could be distracted and stumbled, the same thing could easily happen to us. Like Moses, we are about to enter a symbolic land, the new world that Jehovah has promised us. ([2 Pet. 3:13]) None of us want to miss out on that special privilege. To fulfill our goal, though, we need to keep our eyes fixed on Jehovah, always seeking to do his will.—[1 John 2:17]. w18.07 15 ¶14-16

^ (Ps. 106:33) They embittered his spirit, And he spoke rashly with his lips.

^ (Ex. 7:6) Moses and Aaron did what Jehovah had commanded them; they did just so.

^ (2 Pet. 3:13) But there are new heavens and a new earth that we are awaiting according to his promise, and in these righteousness is to dwell.

^ (1 John 2:17) Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire, but the one who does the will of God remains forever.

Sunday, December 27

You have conquered the wicked one.—[1 John 2:14].

Satan cannot force people to act against their own will. ([Jas. 1:14]) Out of ignorance, many work in harmony with Satan’s purpose. But after they learn the truth, each one makes a choice as to whom he or she will serve. ([Acts 3:17;][17:30]) If we are resolved to do God’s will, there is nothing Satan can do to break our integrity. ([Job 2:3;][27:5]) Satan and the demons have other limitations. For example, nowhere do the Scriptures indicate that they can read the mind or heart of an individual. Only Jehovah and Jesus are spoken of as having that ability. ([1 Sam. 16:7;][Mark 2:8]) If we do our best to speak and act in harmony with God’s will, we can be confident that Jehovah will not allow the Devil to do us any lasting harm. ([Ps. 34:7]) We need to know our enemy, but we do not need to be terrified by him. With Jehovah’s backing, even imperfect humans can conquer Satan. If we oppose him, he will flee from us.—[Jas. 4:7;][1 Pet. 5:9]. w18.05 26 ¶15-17

^ (1 John 2:14) I write you, fathers, because you have come to know him who is from the beginning. I write you, young men, because you are strong and the word of God remains in you and you have conquered the wicked one.

^ (Jas. 1:14) But each one is tried by being drawn out and enticed* by his own desire.

Or “caught as by bait.”

^ (Acts 3:17) And now, brothers, I know that you acted in ignorance, just as your rulers also did.

^ (Acts 17:30) True, God has overlooked the times of such ignorance; but now he is declaring to all people everywhere that they should repent.

^ (Job 2:3) And Jehovah said to Satan: “Have you taken note of* my servant Job? There is no one like him on the earth. He is an upright man of integrity,* fearing God and shunning what is bad. He is still holding firmly to his integrity, even though you try to incite me against him to destroy* him for no reason.”

Lit., “set your heart upon.”

Or “a blameless and upright man.”

Lit., “swallow.”

^ (Job 27:5) It is unthinkable for me to declare you men righteous! Until I die, I will not renounce* my integrity!

Or “I will not take away from myself; I will maintain.”

^ (1 Sam. 16:7) But Jehovah said to Samuel: “Do not pay attention to his appearance and how tall he is, for I have rejected him. For the way man sees is not the way God sees, because mere man sees what appears to the eyes, but Jehovah sees into the heart.”

^ (Mark 2:8) But immediately Jesus discerned by his spirit that they were reasoning that way among themselves, so he said to them: “Why are you reasoning these things in your hearts?

^ (Ps. 34:7) The angel of Jehovah camps all around those fearing Him, And he rescues them.

^ (Jas. 4:7) Therefore, subject yourselves to God; but oppose the Devil, and he will flee from you.

^ (1 Pet. 5:9) But take your stand against him, firm in the faith, knowing that the same kind of sufferings are being experienced by the entire association of your brothers* in the world.

Lit., “by your brotherhood.”

Monday, December 28

Commit to Jehovah whatever you do, and your plans will succeed.—[Prov. 16:3].

Suppose you plan to travel to a distant town for an important event. Getting there requires a long journey by bus. At the bus station, there are many buses. You need to board the bus that is going to your chosen destination! Boarding a bus going anywhere else would mean that you would head in the wrong direction. Adolescents today face a similar situation: a long journey, not by bus, but in life. At times they may feel overwhelmed by the opportunities and decisions that confront them. Youths, you can make it easier for yourselves if you have a good idea where you want to go in life. Will you focus your life on your desire to please Jehovah? That means including him in all aspects of life—education, employment, family responsibilities, and so on. And it means reaching out for spiritual goals. Young people who keep focused on serving Jehovah can be sure of his blessing in making a success of life. w18.04 25 ¶1-3

^ (Prov. 16:3) Commit to Jehovah whatever you do,* And your plans will succeed.

Lit., “Roll to Jehovah your works.”

Tuesday, December 29

Oh no, my daughter! You have broken my heart, for you have become the one I have banished.—[Judg. 11:35].

Jephthah kept his vow and sent his virgin daughter to Shiloh to serve at the tabernacle for the rest of her life. (Judg. 11:30-35) However hard this was on Jephthah, it may have been harder still on his daughter, who willingly complied with her father’s decision. (Judg. 11:36, 37) She thus relinquished the right to marry, to have children, and to preserve the family name and inheritance. If anyone, then, needed comfort and encouragement, she did. The Bible account states: “It became a custom in Israel: From year to year, the young women of Israel would go to give commendation to the daughter of Jephthah the Gileadite four days in the year.” (Judg. 11:39, 40) Do not unmarried Christians who use their singleness to give greater attention to “the things of the Lord” also deserve commendation and encouragement?—1 Cor. 7:32-35. w18.04 17 ¶10-11

^ (Judg. 11:35) When he saw her, he ripped his garments and said: “Oh no, my daughter! You have broken my heart,* for you have become the one I have banished. Now I have opened my mouth to Jehovah, and I am unable to turn back.”

Lit., “You brought me very low.”

^ (Judg. 11:30-35) Then Jephʹthah made a vow to Jehovah and said: “If you give the Amʹmon·ites into my hand, 31 then whoever comes out of the door of my house to meet me when I return in peace from the Amʹmon·ites will become Jehovah’s, and I will offer that one up as a burnt offering.” 32 So Jephʹthah went to fight against the Amʹmon·ites, and Jehovah gave them into his hand. 33 He struck them down with a very great slaughter from A·roʹer all the way to Minʹnith—20 cities—and as far as Aʹbel-kerʹa·mim. Thus the Amʹmon·ites were subdued before the Israelites. 34 Finally Jephʹthah came to his home in Mizʹpah, and look! his daughter was coming out to meet him, playing the tambourine and dancing! Now she was his one and only child. Besides her, he had neither son nor daughter. 35 When he saw her, he ripped his garments and said: “Oh no, my daughter! You have broken my heart,* for you have become the one I have banished. Now I have opened my mouth to Jehovah, and I am unable to turn back.”

Lit., “You brought me very low.”

^ (Judg. 11:36, 37) But she said to him: “My father, if you have opened your mouth to Jehovah, do to me as you have promised, since Jehovah has executed vengeance for you upon your enemies, the Amʹmon·ites.” 37 She then said to her father: “Let this be done for me: Let me be alone for two months, and let me go away into the mountains, and let me weep over my virginity with my female companions.”*

Or “weep with my friends because I will never marry.”

^ (Judg. 11:39, 40) At the end of two months, she returned to her father, after which he carried out the vow he had made regarding her. She never had relations with a man. And it became a custom* in Israel: 40 From year to year, the young women of Israel would go to give commendation to the daughter of Jephʹthah the Gilʹe·ad·ite four days in the year.

Or “regulation.”

^ (1 Cor. 7:32-35) Indeed, I want you to be free from anxiety. The unmarried man is anxious for the things of the Lord, how he may gain the Lord’s approval. 33 But the married man is anxious for the things of the world, how he may gain the approval of his wife, 34 and he is divided. Further, the unmarried woman, as well as the virgin, is anxious for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in her body and in her spirit. However, the married woman is anxious for the things of the world, how she may gain the approval of her husband. 35 But I am saying this for your personal advantage, not to restrict* you, but to move you to what is appropriate and to constant devotion to the Lord without distraction.

Lit., “to cast a noose upon.”

Wednesday, December 30

Angels . . . did not keep their original position but forsook their own proper dwelling place.—[Jude 6].

A significant number of angels joined Satan’s rebellion. Prior to the Flood, Satan lured at least some of them into having immoral relations with the daughters of men. The Bible reveals this truth by symbolically portraying the dragon as dragging a third of the stars of heaven with him in his fall. ([Gen. 6:1-4;] Rev. 12:3, 4) When those angels abandoned God’s family, they put themselves under Satan’s control. These rebels, however, are not just a mob of troublemakers. Satan has set up an imitation of God’s Kingdom, with himself as king. In the invisible realm, Satan has organized the demons into governments, given them authority, and made them world rulers. ([Eph. 6:12]) By means of his spirit organization, Satan exerts authority over all human governments. w18.05 23 ¶5-6

^ (Jude 6) And the angels who did not keep their original position but forsook their own proper dwelling place, he has reserved with eternal bonds in dense darkness for the judgment of the great day.

^ (Gen. 6:1-4) Now when men started to grow in number on the surface of the ground and daughters were born to them, 2 the sons of the true God* began to notice that the daughters of men were beautiful. So they began taking as wives all whom they chose. 3 Then Jehovah said: “My spirit will not tolerate man indefinitely, because he is only flesh.* Accordingly, his days will amount to 120 years.” 4 The Nephʹi·lim* were on the earth in those days and afterward. During that time the sons of the true God continued to have relations with the daughters of men, and these bore sons to them. They were the mighty ones of old times, the men of fame.

A Hebrew idiom that refers to angelic sons of God.

Or possibly, “because he acts according to the flesh.”

Possibly meaning “The Fellers,” that is, those who cause others to fall down. See Glossary.

^ (Rev. 12:3, 4) Another sign was seen in heaven. Look! A great fiery-colored dragon, with seven heads and ten horns and on its heads seven diadems;* 4 and its tail drags a third of the stars of heaven, and it hurled them down to the earth. And the dragon kept standing before the woman who was about to give birth, so that when she did give birth, it might devour her child.

Or “royal headbands.”

^ (Eph. 6:12) because we have a struggle,* not against blood and flesh, but against the governments, against the authorities, against the world rulers of this darkness, against the wicked spirit forces in the heavenly places.

Lit., “wrestling.”

Thursday, December 31

I will praise Jehovah, who has given me advice. Even during the night, my innermost thoughts correct me.—[Ps. 16:7].

God’s love for us is sometimes expressed through fatherly correction. David welcomed such kindly counsel. He meditated on God’s thoughts, making them his own and allowing them to mold him. When you in faith do the same, you too will grow in love for God and in your desire to obey him. You will also gain spiritual maturity and depth. A sister named Christin said, “When I do research and meditate on what I read, I get the feeling that Jehovah had this penned just for me!” It is no exaggeration to say that a spiritual outlook on life also gives you exceptional knowledge and insight by enabling you to see the world and its future through God’s eyes. Why does God give you such knowledge and insight? He wants you to set sound priorities in your life, to make wise decisions, and to look forward to the future with confidence!—[Isa. 26:3]. w18.12 26 ¶9-10

^ (Ps. 16:7) I will praise Jehovah, who has given me advice. Even during the night, my innermost thoughts* correct me.

Or “my deepest emotions.” Lit., “my kidneys.”

^ (Isa. 26:3) You will safeguard those who fully lean on you;* You will give them continuous peace, Because it is in you that they trust.

Or possibly, “those whose inclination is unshakable.”